<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the right reverend, the ministers of the Kirk of Scotland, of the Presbyterian perswasion the following defence, of the rights and liberties of the church ... / by Robert Park.</title>
            <author>Park, Robert, d. 1689?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 246 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22921</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12365031</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12365031</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55985)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 893:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the right reverend, the ministers of the Kirk of Scotland, of the Presbyterian perswasion the following defence, of the rights and liberties of the church ... / by Robert Park.</title>
                  <author>Park, Robert, d. 1689?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 171 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title: A defence of the rights &amp; liberties of the church.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [4]-[5]</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [5]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Presbyterian Church.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60402:1"/>
            <head>TO The Right Reverend, THE <hi>MINISTERS</hi> OF THE KIRK OF SCOTLAND, Of the PRESBYTERIAN Perſwaſion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The following</hi> DEFENCE, <hi>of the</hi> RIGHTS <hi>and</hi> LIBERTIES <hi>of the</hi> CHURCH, <hi>against the pretended</hi> Right <hi>and</hi> Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations <hi>of</hi> PATRONAGE; <hi>is moſt humbly Dedicated, by</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROBERT PARK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60402:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60402:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſubſtance of the following ſheets, was written many Years ago, mainly for the ſatisfying ſome ſcruples, of a worthy friend of the Authors. But the preſs hath for a long time, been ſo well guarded from the leaſt breathing, againſt the grievances, this poor Church, and Nation groaned under, that the publication was but little thought of.</p>
            <p>It having now pleaſed God, to raiſe up ſome worthy Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to appear for the intereſts and Liberties of this broken Church and People, and to endeavour a redreſs of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold oppreſſions; It was thought convenient, to offer theſe Papers, to the publick view and conſideration. I ſtand in too near a Relation, to the Author, to be thought impartial in his commendation. And tho' I could wiſh this diſcourſe had got his own laſt hand, and that it had not been left to run the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fate of other poſthumous works; yet I hope the main Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject will be found ſatisfyingly handled. There are beſides ſome other purpoſes incidently touched, and many ſountains for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſeveral important debates of the time, ſolidly and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly opened; which if well conſidered, may be ſerviceable, for advancing a Reformation of many moe Abuſes, than the particular deſign of theſe Papers Intends.</p>
            <p>I ſhall offer no Apology for the ſtyle. I hope it will be found diſtinct, plain and eaſie, and ſutable to the Nature of the Subject. I know nothing a ſtyle ſerves for, but to expreſs Men's Conceptions diſtinctly and without harſhneſs: And if that may be attained, without forced and ſtrained Rhetorications, which for the moſt part, produce no other effect, but <hi>a Darkning of knowledge with words;</hi> I cannot ſee, how a neglect of ſuch uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Trifles can be blamed. The native beautie of truth, ſtands no way in need of theſe artificial diſguiſes, that are uſed to ſet off adulterate wares. There are but too many in this Age, who have rendred both themſelves and their diſcourſes Ridicul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb facs="tcp:60402:3"/>by affecting new ſtrains of Eloquence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as they take it. The thinking part of mankind, is very ſenſible, that the neglect of a good old form, of ſound VVords and ſafe Expreſſions, hath made People forget and miſtake, many Ancient and ſolid truths. It is Pitifully mean and unbecoming to ſee the Clergy (as they muſt be termed) turn the Pulpit to a Theatre, and to hear Divines, Trick up and illuſtrate their diſcourſes with the ſimilies and Expreſſions of a Comedy or Romance, <hi>going down,</hi> (as it were) <hi>to the Uncircumciſed, for ſharpning of their Tools, as if there were no Smith in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubject of theſe Papers, is but very little treated of by any, eſpecially in this way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therefore the publication may perhaps be as neceſſary as ſeaſonable. If it can in the leaſt be ſervicable, for freeing the Church, of any part of her bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; I am ſure the deſign, both of it's Writing and Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, will be fully attained.</p>
            <p>I hope there will be few found ſo fond, of the Rights of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, as to be of the Opinion of <hi>Diego Lainez,</hi> one of the Fathers at <hi>Trent,</hi> who aſſerted, <hi>That it was a motion of the Devil, to offer to reduce Elections to the Ancient courſe: And that the Antiquity of that method, was a bad Argument for Reviving of it: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut that on the contrary, it ought to be ſuppreſſed, becauſe it was the Ancient cuſtome. For if the Church</hi> (as he Ridiculouſly enough pretends) <hi>had not found it inconvenient, ſhe would not have quite it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only wiſh, that People in their ſeveral Capacities, may ſeriouſly conſider, what the preſent conduct, of providence; ſeems to call them to: And that they may Act, both in this and other matters, ſo, as not to be wanting to themſelves and their Poſterity, in the ſettling of affairs, upon the ſolid and laſting foundations, of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace:</hi> leſt they verifie the Proverb, <hi>Sero ſapiunt Phryges.</hi> (which I need not tranſlate) And repent when it is too late, the loſs of ſuch a Golden oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, ſo wonderfully and unexpectedly, brought to their hand: And give the preſent and ſucceeding Generations cauſe to ſay, <hi>why was there a price, put in the hand of a Fool to get Wiſdom, ſeeing he had no heart to it?</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                  <date>Febr. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60402:3"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>Of the Original of</hi> Patronage Pag. 1</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>A general View of the</hi> Rights <hi>of</hi> Patronage. 17.</item>
               <item>Sect. III. <hi>The Opinion of our</hi> Reformers, <hi>&amp;c. concerning</hi> Patronage. 26.</item>
               <item>Sect. IV. <hi>The Ground and Argument for</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, <hi>from a</hi> Reſervation <hi>by the firſt Founders examined.</hi> 31.</item>
               <item>Sect. V. <hi>A farther examination, of this</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>from its own nature, and from the Nature of</hi> Pious <hi>and Charitable</hi> Deeds. 38.</item>
               <item>Sect. VI. <hi>The</hi> Reſervation <hi>pretended, can be no ground, for the</hi> Jus utile <hi>of</hi> Patron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. 53.</item>
               <item>Sect. VII. <hi>The denyal of</hi> It, <hi>can be no diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in gratifying of the Church: ſomething</hi> obiter, <hi>of the</hi> Dilapidation <hi>of the Churches</hi> Patrimony. 56.</item>
               <item>Sect. VIII. <hi>The ground of</hi> Patronage, <hi>from a grant or</hi> Conceſſion <hi>of the Church, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined.</hi> 63.</item>
               <item>Sect. IX. <hi>Afarther examination of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</hi> Conceſſion. 69</item>
               <item>Sect. X. <hi>Another ground for the Foundation of</hi> Patronage, <hi>from the neceſſity, of a</hi> Jus Oneroſum, <hi>examined.</hi> 73.</item>
               <item>Sect. XI. Patronage <hi>is no</hi> Inſtitution <hi>of</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Appointment, <hi>but a mannifest</hi> Uſurpation. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60402:4"/>Sect. XII. <hi>The power of</hi> Patronage, <hi>is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of the Inſtitutions of Christ, for the</hi> Election <hi>of the</hi> Paſtors <hi>of his Church.</hi> 97.</item>
               <item>Sect. XIII. <hi>The power of</hi> Patronage, <hi>is againſt the</hi> Freedom <hi>and</hi> Intereſt <hi>of Common</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. 113.</item>
               <item>Sect. XIV. <hi>The power of</hi> Patronage, <hi>hath been groſly</hi> Abuſed, <hi>&amp;</hi> Scandalouſly <hi>offenſive, without any</hi> Neceſſity <hi>or</hi> uſe. 120.</item>
               <item>Sect. XV. Patronage <hi>is a</hi> Symbolizing <hi>with</hi> Idolaters, <hi>and against the</hi> Doctrine <hi>and</hi> Diſcipline <hi>of this</hi> Church. 142.</item>
               <item>Sect. XVI <hi>A pretence that the Patron med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles with nothing of Election, or what is properly Eccleſiastical.</hi> 146.</item>
               <item>Sect. XVII. <hi>Another pretence, that the</hi> Church <hi>may reject the Perſon preſented in caſe of</hi> inſufficiency. 157.</item>
               <item>Sect. XVIII. <hi>Another pretence, from the diſtinction of</hi> Laick <hi>and</hi> Eccleſiaſtick Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronages. 162.</item>
               <item>Sect. XIX. <hi>Apretence, from the</hi> Failings <hi>and</hi> Miſtakes <hi>of</hi> Church Judicatories. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 167.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 17, line 14, for the <hi>Vandals,</hi> read and ſince the <hi>Vandals.</hi> p. 28. l. 21 for Prelacy it was, r. Prelacy. I ſay, it was. p. 80. l. 14. for all Civil. read all other Civil. p. 82. l. 22. for as a moſt, r. is a moſt. p. 115. l. 26. for there, r. other. p. 160. l. 11, for much, r. as much.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60402:4"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF THE RIGHTS &amp; LIBERTIES Of the CHURCH, In the <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> of Her PASTORS: AGAINST The <hi>Negative</hi> Intereſts of PATRONAGE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION. I. <hi>An Account of the Original of Patronage.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THE Deſign I have in theſe few Pages, is to Demonſtrate from Grounds of <hi>Scripture</hi> and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> the unwarrantablneſs and injuſtice of theſe Priviledges, Claimed and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted, in, and over the Church and People of God by the <hi>Patrons</hi> of Kirks and Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in reference to the Call and Maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60402:5"/>This I ſhall endeavour to performe, as diſtinctly, and with all the plainneſs, and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. I can find the ſubject will admit: And that ſo much the rather, That I know, thoſe for whoſe ſatisfaction I principally Write, are ſufficiently capable to diſcover, the weight of Truth and Reaſon, without the attendance of any Rhetorical Excurſion, or Embelliſhment of Expreſſion. And if I Err in any thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in matters, that are out of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Road, I expect the Reader will be Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dide and Favourable in his Cenſure.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Method which I ſhall obſerve in the proſecution of this Deſign, ſhall be,</p>
               <p n="1">1 To give ſome ſhort account, of what ſeems to have been the firſt Riſe and Original of the Rights of <hi>Patronage;</hi> with a view of its ſeveral Branches, as it hath been Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in and over the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Relation to the Miniſterial Call and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
               <p n="2">2 I ſhall endeavour to diſcover the Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs of theſe Grounds, that are, or may be adduced for a Foundation, to the Inſtitution of <hi>Patronage:</hi> whereby it will appear, how groundleſs and unjuſt the Claims and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Patrons,</hi> in this matter have been.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I ſhall offer ſome poſitive Reaſons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pretended Right it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60402:5"/>4. And laſtly, I ſhall examine ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, that may be alledged, for clearing that <hi>Patronage</hi> is not ſo injurious to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Church, as it is repreſented to be.</p>
               <p>To theſe Heads, as being the moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial and needful, to be handled in a Subject of this Nature, I ſhall confine what I have to ſay; and thence it is hoped, any thing elſe that might be expected in Relation to this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, will receive <hi>ſufficient</hi> light.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The <hi>right</hi> of <hi>Patronage</hi> may be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined,</hi> to be <hi>a Power to preſent and nominat, a perſon to be inſtitute in a vacant Church, Office and Benefice, by thoſe who are, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be, the Founders or Doters, of Kirks or Benefices. Poteſtas praeſentandi, aut Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi inſtituendum, ad Vacans Beneficium aut Officium Sacrum. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know There are many uſeleſs Debates, among the Canoniſts, concerning the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Patronage, which I ſhall not inſiſt upon; ſeing the Thing it ſelf is by the ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of this Church and Nation, but too well known.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Only I cannot omit to obſerve, that the very <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Title,</hi> of <hi>Patron,</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>ominous</hi> and <hi>unlucky,</hi> as Importing a kind of Servitude and Bondage, upon the Church.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60402:6"/>For as in the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws and Cuſtoms, a <hi>Patron</hi> (albeit the Name import Favour and Protection) was ſtill underſtood, to retain a very hard Intereſt, in the Perſons and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, of ſuch Servants, as he had manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and ſet free from their Bondage; and a Right of Reducing them to their former condition of Slavery, upon pretences of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, or a Carriage any way unſuitable, to the favour of Freedom they had received; ſo ſure I am, this pretended Right of <hi>Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage,</hi> (of which we are to treat) hath in theſe reſpects, been very anſwerable to its Name, in reſtraining and impeding, (under the fair Colour of Protection) the Church and People of God, from the Free and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Exerciſe of their Spiritual Liberties, and Priviledges, as we ſhall fully clear in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="5">V. To come then to the firſt part of the method propoſed, I ſhall not determine <hi>the Time</hi> when this <hi>Corruption,</hi> (for ſo I muſt call it, ſince <hi>Vetuſtas Erroris non Conſuetudo ſed Corruptela dicenda eſt</hi>) entred into the Chriſtian Church, The Canoniſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not fully agreed as to this. It may be very clear in the General. That it was the work of <hi>ſome time</hi> and Pains, to bring the rights of Patronage, to that Form and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60402:6"/>in which they have been exerciſed over the Chriſtian Church. <hi>Patronage</hi> was not an Inſtitution, That was framed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and perfected at one daſh. It is alſo very certain that <hi>ab Initio non fuit.</hi> It was not ſo much as heard of, in the <hi>pure and primitive</hi> times, but hath been by ſmall and inſenſible degrees dropt and ſown, in the field of the Church by the <hi>Enemy,</hi> among other <hi>Tares,</hi> while men were <hi>Aſleep,</hi> that is while the Church was unawars,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13, 25.</note> and not ſo watchful as need was; ſo that 'its little wonder the particular time of the Entry of this power be hard enough to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended upon.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. It may likewiſe be very clear, That ſince the foundation of Patronage, was the <hi>Building</hi> or <hi>doting</hi> of <hi>Kirks,</hi> and that the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, of ſuch <hi>Building</hi> and <hi>Doting,</hi> was not much allowed, and perhaps leſs practiſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the times of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, which was about the begining of the fourth Century; I ſay, from this it may be clear that before <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine's</hi> time, the priviledge of <hi>Patronage</hi> could not be introduced.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. And tho' ſome may alledge that in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60402:7"/>year of Chriſt CCCC. The fifth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil.</hi> 5. <hi>carthag. Can.</hi> 9. <hi>Council. Mile. vitan. Can.</hi> 16.</note> and thereafter in the year CCCCII. The Council of <hi>Millan,</hi> both in the times of the Emperors <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Arcadius,</hi> did deſire of the Emperors, that there might be ſome <hi>Perſons conſiderable</hi> for <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> appointed for <hi>defence</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> in her Rights, and goods or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> againſt ſuch as ſhould attempt, any Invaſion upon them; and that thoſe <hi>Perſons,</hi> came afterwards to get the name of <hi>Patrons</hi> or defenders of the Church: Yet theſe are not the Patrons we are Inquiring after.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII For as this ſort of <hi>Patronage</hi> was to be managed <hi>cum proviſione Epiſcoporum,</hi> by the Advice and Conſent of the Paſtors and Office-bearers of the Church; ſo it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a branch of the Magiſtrates Cumulative Power, <hi>circa Sacra,</hi> and only for defence of the Churches Patrimony, againſt Sacrilegious Miſapplications, and no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with the Call and Election of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry: nor had this ſort of <hi>Patronage</hi> any Privative, or Negative Intereſt, in their Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends or Maintenance Neither were theſe Patrons, accounted Church Officers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts will have the Patrons we are enquiring after to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor were thoſe <hi>Biſhops</hi> then <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60402:7"/>themſelves, becauſe they were a part of the Church that was to be defended. <hi>Et ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo potest eſſe ſibi patronus.</hi> Their truſt was with the Church's conſent, <hi>Elective</hi> and not <hi>Hereditary,</hi> and much leſs <hi>purchaſable</hi> for <hi>money</hi> as a part of a mans privat <hi>patrimony,</hi> and Fortune. I conceive it will be needleſs, to add any thing farther, upon the difference, that is ſo palpably evident betwixt theſe and our pretended Patronages, tho' it may be ſaid, that this Inſtitution was in ſome reſpect the foundation of theſe patronages we are in ſearch of, if we conſider that as at the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, this was a truſt in it ſelf not diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but rather in ſome caſes neceſſar and uſeful; ſo in after times it did by <hi>little</hi> and <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle degenerat</hi> into this pretended right of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage</hi> we are to treat of, to the ſubverſion of the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rch, for whoſe defence in the Lawful enjoymen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of her <hi>Patrimony,</hi> it was at firſt introduced<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And it may likewiſe be obſerved that thoſe perſons at the time of the Councils cited, were not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Patrons,</hi> but only <hi>Eccleſiarum Defenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide Caranz ſumm Concil. folio</hi> 126. <hi>&amp; folio</hi> 146.</note> &amp; Eccleſiarum Exequuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> vel <hi>Advocati;</hi> which clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhews the Nature of that truſt, to have been vaſtly different from the right of patronage, as it was afterwards practiſed.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60402:8"/>IX. But in the time of the Emperor <hi>Juſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> about the middle of the ſixth Century there appears ſome clearer Lineaments of the rights of <hi>Patronage;</hi> as in the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> 57.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Novel.</hi> 57. &amp; <hi>Novel.</hi> 123.</note> and <hi>Novel.</hi> 123 yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at this time, it is <hi>vaſtly ſhort</hi> of that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it afterwards came to, under the protection of the Canon Law, and many are of opinion that at this time, this Power did not extend any farther, than to the preſentation of the <hi>Minores Clerici</hi> (as they were called) and that it had no intereſt, in the <hi>Election</hi> of the <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> of the Church (who were then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> termed <hi>Epiſcopi</hi>) as they think is clear from the 123 Novel, where it is appointed, <hi>ut ad Electionem Epiſcopi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venirent omnes Clerici &amp; Primores Civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> So that if by the Rules of Analogy, we may be allowed to draw this power of preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or <hi>Commendation,</hi> as it was called, but not a <hi>jus etigendi:</hi> and apply it to our times, it will have place, in the Election of none of the Office bearers of the Church, but only in that of Readers, Precentors, Schoolma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Beddels and the like: For theſe are the Officers th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t correſpond to the <hi>Minores Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci</hi> of that time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thence they conclude, that it can never be proven, that before the year DC. Patronage had any intereſt in the <hi>Call</hi> of the <hi>Pastors</hi> of the Church.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60402:8"/>X. But be this as it will, it is pretty clear, that before theſe Novels, there was nothing like the priviledges of patronage in uſe: that right being not ſo much as once named, in all the former Laws of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, which were reduced and Compyled into a <hi>Body,</hi> by the ſame Emperor. And all the mention that is made of it in the Novels, is but in ſome few, to witt in the 1. 57. 67. 123. and 131. This may yet farther appear, from the very terms of <hi>praeſentatio, advocatio, guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias habere</hi> &amp;c. which have not the leaſt ſcent of the <hi>Saecula purioris latinitatis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">XI And as the priviledges of Patronage, were late of entring into the Empire, ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they have been ſome conſiderable time in uſe in the Empire and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have been brought thence, and ſettled in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">XII But be the time of the entry of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage what it will, that which ſeems to have given the firſt riſe and occaſion to it, was, the <hi>building</hi> of <hi>Kirks</hi> and <hi>Meeting-places</hi> for the publick worſhip of God, or the allocating and giving <hi>ground</hi> to build them on, or laſtly the <hi>Mortification</hi> or ſettlement of a <hi>Benefice</hi> or conſtant maintenance on ſuch as ſhould ſerve the <hi>Cure</hi> thereat: for upon ſuch acts the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of Kirks and Benefices did <hi>aſſume,</hi> or as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60402:9"/>others pretend, did <hi>Reſerve</hi> to themſelves and their heirs in all time thereafter, a priviledge and power, to nominat and preſent thoſe who ſhould ſerve as Paſtors at ſuch a <hi>Kirk,</hi> and a ſole Power of giving them a legal <hi>Right</hi> &amp; <hi>Title,</hi> to the <hi>Rents</hi> and profits of the <hi>Living</hi> during their <hi>Incumbency</hi> And that even albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſuch founders had not built the whole <hi>Kirk,</hi> or ſettled the whole benefice, but only a part of them: for the Canoniſts maintain, that he who builds but <hi>One</hi> corner of a Kirk, hath a right to the patronage, as well as he that builds the other <hi>Three.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">XIII. Many of the Canoniſts do grant, and it is very clear from the Canon law it ſelf, that the patrons did at firſt aſſume this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Decretal. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Tit.</hi> 38. <hi>Ca.</hi> 3.</note> rather by the <hi>Connivance</hi> of the Church, than by her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and deliberate <hi>Conſent,</hi> and far leſs by her <hi>poſitive</hi> appointment and <hi>Institution.</hi> And even the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> does acknowledge, that in many caſes. <hi>Jus patronatus ex uſurpatione quaeſitumeſt.</hi> The Patron on the one hand, counting this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be his due,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Trident. ſeſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>decret. de Reform. cap.</hi> 9.</note> in point of merit and deſert, and looking upon it as no ſmall degree of unthankfulneſs, in the Church, to gain ſay or oppoſe his claim to it. And the Church it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60402:9"/>may be alſo, thinking it hard on the other hand, in point of gratitude, to refuſe it: ſince the deſign of this priviledge, <hi>primo intuitu,</hi> might appear to reach no farther, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſome memory of ſuch good and pious deeds, that the <hi>Benefactors</hi> might not ſeem to have utterly loſt, what they devoted for pious uſes: it being indeed hard enough, at the firſt ſight, to diſcern, betwixt plauſible corruptions, and truly uſeful inſtitutions <hi>Inter triticum &amp; lolium</hi> (ſayes Jerom) <hi>Quamdiu in herbaest; &amp; nondum culmus venit ad Spicam, grandis Similitudo &amp; in diſcernendo aut nulla, aut peraifficilis diſtantia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that by ſuch concurring circumſtances of ambition, on the Patrons part, and of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliberate favour on the part of the Church, at a time, when, the myſtery of iniquity, had already wrought to ſome ſort of perfection, (for even in the Apoſtles days it had begun to work) and when Superſtition and Corruption, as well in Worſhip and Doctrine,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> as in Morals, was much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and humane Inventions were creeping in apace, into the room of the ordinances of <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> The Church was by degrees robbed of her Spiritual Priviledges, that the aſpiring humours of the great ones, might be Gratified with her ſpoils, and that their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60402:10"/>greatneſs might, under the ſpecious and plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Title of the Churches <hi>Patrons</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders,</hi> appear with the more luſtre and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor before Men: It being eſteemed no ſmall Addition to their Honour, and to the Intereſt they had over People, as to their Bodies and Temporal Concerns, to be likewiſe inveſted with a priviledge, that in a manner gave them a preheminence, over Peopl's Souls and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual intereſts; to that degree, that no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, without the Patrons expreſs and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive wartand and appointment, might have acceſs to ſerve <hi>in Sacris,</hi> at ſuch a Kirk, or have a legal Right and Title, to the rents and profits of a Benefice, tho' all others intereſſed, were ſatisfied to the full, with his ſufficiency, good Behaviour and faithful diſcharge of the duties of his function.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. Theſe and many other Corruptions of this Nature, the Lord in his righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did permit in the times of Darkneſs, as tending to introduce and keep up, an Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant fruitleſs and Idle Miniſtry, that ſtudied to be pleaſers of men and ſervants of their Luſts, (eſpecially of thoſe of their Patrons) that thereby, he might juſtly puniſh the World, for not receiving the love of the truth. And Particularly to puniſh, the unlawful inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, made by the corrupt Church-men and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60402:10"/>Clergy of theſe times, upon the civil Powers; permitting them, to prey on each others Rights and Priviledges, <hi>Jure quaſi Belli, ac lege talionis,</hi> till at length the whole frame of Church and ſtate, was turned to a Babel of Confuſion, and Egyptian Darkneſs. And tho' the practiſing of ſuch uſurpations, over the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Church, might in a time of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, be looked upon, as a ſin of Ignorance or weakneſs, yet in ſuch times of light, as God hath ſet us in, it muſt certainly be a ſin of a higher nature and Degree.</p>
               <p n="15">XV. The <hi>Superstition</hi> of theſe times, ſtill advancing, and particularly, that Anti-evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Opinion of <hi>Merit,</hi> taking daily deeper root, the Clergy (as they muſt be ſtiled) were not a wanting, to fiſh in theſe muddie Waters, and to make their beſt uſe of that occaſion, by inſinuating themſelves, upon weak and well meaning People, (eſpecially in the time of their Sickneſs) to make them part very liberally, with their goods and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the ſervice of the Church, and pious uſes, as they termed it. And they did ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie them, with the fears of Purgatory and Damnation for their Sins, on the one hand; and flatter them, with the hopes of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, pardon of ſins and Prayers for their Souls, and the honour they would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60402:11"/>to themſelves and their Poſterity, by ſuch good Deeds, on the other hand; that in a ſhort time, the poor Peoples blind and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious zeal, was ſcrewed to ſuch a pitch, as nothing was ſooner asked (eſpecially if not to take effect till after their Death) than it was given: So that as the Apoſtle ſayes in a different caſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.15.</note> they would have <hi>pluckt out their very eyes,</hi> for the ſervice of theſe rapacious Vultures.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. This is a Truth ſo inconteſtable, that the civil Powers in the moſt of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian States, found themſelves under an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity, to put ſome ſtop to ſuch a Torrent of ill diſpoſed Charity, as was likely to terminate in the Settling of the whole Lands and Poſleſſions, within their Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, In the hands of a ſort of Men, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon a Foraign Power, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to an exemption and independencie, from the Civil Authority of the States they lived in: As among many other Inſtances, that might be given, may appear from that one Law in our own Nation, prohibiting the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of Lands or Heritages by Perſons on Death-bed.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60402:11"/>XVII. It is well obſerved by the Noble <hi>du Pleſſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mornay, in his myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</note> that when the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Religion began to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in the <hi>Subſtance,</hi> People en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to cover their defection by retaining the <hi>Shadow,</hi> and to ſeem as Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious as ever, by building of Kirks, Chappels <hi>&amp;c</hi> And that in Actions of this nature, the worſt of Men, were ordinarly the moſt forward and devout, that thereby they might obliterat the memory of their former vicious Lives and Practiſes, both in themſelves and others. This is indeed a clear Paraphraſe, upon our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour's</hi> charge againſt the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, That they tithed the Mint and the Anniſe, and omitted the weighter Matters of the Law, Judgment, Mercy,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.</note> and Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. Things being brought to this paſs, it is little wonder, that the humour of building and doting of Kirks, began to increaſe; and the number of Patronages by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to multiply: ſo that in a ſhort time, few Kirks or Congregations, wanted ſome one or other for their patron. And many times when Patronage could not be claimed, upon the account of the building or doting of Kirks, there was ſtill ſome body found, who under the leaſt ſhadow of Reparations or otherwiſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60402:12"/>and in default of all, the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> as pretending himſelf, to be patron <hi>Supreme, Paramount</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> of all Kirks; and ſince the Reformation in this Church, our own Kings, as coming into the Pop's place (which by the way, is none of the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Succeſſions) aſſumed and uſurped this Priviledge. So that in a ſmall time, the Corruption was little leſs than univerſally ſpread.</p>
               <p n="19">XIX. Before we leave this Head, we may obſerve, that as that <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath in moſt of her Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſtill endeavoured to advance her own ſplendor and greatneſs, and her uſurped Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, over the Church and Conſciences of God's People, by an affected imitation of theſe intereſts, which the Secular powers of the Earth, have over the civil rights of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, expreſly contrare to the Precepts of our bleſſed Lord, <hi>Luke,</hi> 22. Which in this caſe deſerve a very ſerious and ſpecial conſideration;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke,</hi> 22.25. to the 31. <hi>Matt.</hi> 20 25.</note> ſo particularly, this inſtitution of Patronage, hath been fixed or continued and improven, to make ſome ſort of a reſemblance and parallel, in the Church, to that of <hi>Feudal Superiority</hi> and <hi>Vaſſalage,</hi> in uſe betwixt great Men and their followers. This ſeems to be pretty clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60402:12"/>intimate, by the very word <hi>Beneficium,</hi> which in its more proper acceptation, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the ſame thing with <hi>Feudum,</hi> or a grant of Lands, by a Superior to his vaſſal, for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary ſervices; tho' by a kind of <hi>Antinomaſia,</hi> that firſt ſignification, be in a manner now wholly diſuſed, and the other of a Spiritual or Church living, commonly if nor only, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood thereby. And hence it may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that as Patronage was fixed, or continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and improven, in imitation of <hi>Feudal Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorities,</hi> ſo as to order of time, its firſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor was not, till after the feudal Inſtitution: For the <hi>Vandals</hi> (who gave the riſe to the <hi>Feudal Contract</hi>) took the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> after the middle of the fifth Century. This may likewiſe confirm what was formerly hinted, that till the year DC. the Intereſts of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, in the <hi>Election and Maintenance</hi> of the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the Church was not known.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>A general View of the Rights of</hi> PATRONAGE.</head>
               <p>THe Canoniſts write of Patrons, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in ſome kind of office, &amp; having right
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60402:13"/>to a ſort of Stipend. The rights they aſcribe to them are ſhortly theſe</p>
               <p n="1">I. Firſt a <hi>Jus Honorificum,</hi> whereby the patron, had power to nominate the Paſtor, and give him right to the Benefice, and to have a ſplendid and Stately Seat, and a Burial place, in the Kirk; and a right of precedency, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Clergy, in ſolemn proceſſions, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In which they could not lay aſide, their Pride and Vanity, in their very neareſt approaches to God, in going about the Duties of his worſhip and ſervice: Nor in the moſt humbling Circumſtances of Death and Burial. And how ſuitable ſuch practices are, to the faults, of the Scribes and Phariſees,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.6. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.38. <hi>James</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>who did all their works to be ſeen of men, and loved the uppermost Rooms at feaſts, and the chief ſeats in the Synagogues, and greetings in the mercat place, and to be called of men</hi> Rabbi Rabbi; for which, our Saviour ſo ſharply rebukes them, any man may eaſily ſee. By this <hi>Jus honorificum,</hi> The Patron had alſo his name and Arms, and other badges of Honour, cut, engraven, or painted upon the entry, or walls of the Kirk, And upon the Bells, Chalices and other U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſils. And alſo was <hi>nominatim</hi> mentioned in the publick Prayers of the Church, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60402:13"/>are all phariſaical Fancies of the ſame Nature.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Secondly, they aſcribe to the Patron, a <hi>Jus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile,</hi> whereby if he, or his Poſterity became poor, and could not live <hi>aliunde,</hi> they were to be entertained and alimented, out of the Church Revenues, as ſome ſort of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence and retribution, for their having gratified the Church, by building and Erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Kirk, or mortifying a maintenance for the Incumbents.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Thirdly a <hi>Jus Oneroſum,</hi> whereby the Patron (as the Canoniſts tell us) was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidged, to repair the Kirk, and defend its Rents, from Dilapidations and Miſapplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. To have yet a more Diſtinct view, of this pretended Right of Patronage, eſpecially as it hath been practiſed in this Church, theſe particulars, among others, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Right of Patronage, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported a priviledge to <hi>look out</hi> (as the Apoſtles phraſe it) <hi>Nominat</hi> and <hi>Elect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 6: 3</note> the Perſon who ſhould be Paſtor, at ſuch a Kirk. I ſay, to <hi>Elect,</hi> for all that preceeds <hi>Tryal</hi> and <hi>Admiſſion,</hi> Is that which is properly called <hi>Election,</hi> as we ſhall ſee in the ſequel of this diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60402:14"/>V. Next it Imported a power, to make this nomination and Election, without being tied or oblidged, to acquaint, or conſult with either paroch or <hi>Presbitry,</hi> or even (dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prelacy) with the <hi>Biſhops</hi> themſelves, who were <hi>Ordinars</hi> of the <hi>Diocy,</hi> in which the Kirklay. And even, tho' the Lord in his providence, were offering the occaſion of a Perſon more worthy, and better qualified for the charge, yet the Patron might nominat, and preſent, the Perſon, whom he at his pleaſure had looked out, to the Presbitry or Prelates when in power, And require them by Law, yea charge them under the pain of Rebellion, (as the term is) To try and admit him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide parl:</hi> 1612. <hi>cap</hi> 1.</note> as Miniſter of that Kirk, if he were but found, in the leaſt meaſure <hi>Externally</hi> quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, according to the letter of the Church Laws and Canons, for the Office of a Paſtor in general; without any reguard of his being fit and proper for that particular People, or any other conſideration: and that tho' the whole Congregation concerned ſhould expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry declare their diſſent, from the Patron's No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Election, and had their eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, indiſputably more worthy and proper for the place, and much more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60402:14"/>VI. The right of Patronage, did alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Priviledge of giving the only Legal Right and Title, to the Paſtors maintenance, for ſerving the Cure at ſuch a Kirk; ſo that if a Miniſter lawfully Called and ordained, had entered to the Kirk, and had proved never ſo laborious, faithful and ſucceſsful, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his Duty; Yet unleſs his entry had been by the Patrons expreſs nomination and election, he might ſtill claim and exerce a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative intereſt, to ſtop and interrupt the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, in the peacable poſſeſſion and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his maintenance, till he took and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a preſentation from him; and that the Patron was not oblidged to give him, but at his own pleaſure, and on his own conditions.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Thirdly, the priviledges of patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, deſcended from thoſe who were the firſt Founders or Doters of a Kirk, or had other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe right to the patronage, from Father to Son, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> according to the common Degrees of Blood, and Rules of Succeſſion, without the leaſt diſtinction, whether the next Heir were capable to manage ſuch a Truſt, and to make a right choiſe of paſtors or not: yea, tho' the next Heir were a Woman, whoſe Sex, and many Infirmities, both of Body and Mind, debarr her (for the moſt part,) from any medling in publick Affairs, even of a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60402:15"/>Secular and Temporal Concernment, and much more in Eccleſiaſtical matters, in which the word of God expreſly diſcharges her to be admitted to any voice: yea, tho' the next Heirs ſhould be more than one, as in the caſe of Heirs portioners, in which, and many other caſes,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.35.</note> where the patrons happened to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they were either to concur (at leaſt the major part of them) in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, or otherwiſe they were to preſent <hi>alternis vicibus,</hi> conform to the Canon Law. <hi>Tranſmittitur hoc jus ad Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>de jure patronatus in</hi> 6.</note> nec intereſt an plures Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troni ſint, ſive unus; dummodo ſi plures ſint, in praeſentando omnes, velcerte major eorum pars, in Eundem conveniant; ac poſſunt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troni inter ſe paciſci, ut alternis vicibus ſinguli praeſentent.</hi> This Right being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, a part of a mans privat <hi>Patrimony,</hi> which he enjoyed, and had ſecured &amp; convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>him, and his Heirs,</hi> in the ſame manner as he had the reſt of his Fortune and Eſtate.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Next, not only was this priviledge <hi>Tranſmitted,</hi> to ſuch as were the Patrons neareſt <hi>heirs,</hi> but alſo, thoſe that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted, in the preſent Right of it, might and did, <hi>ſell</hi> and make over the ſame, to whom ſoever they pleaſed, in the ſame manner, as they might diſpoſe, of any other thing, that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60402:15"/>fell within the Compaſs of their <hi>Private Patrimony.</hi> And that without making any Diſtinction betwixt the ſelling of the Right of Patronage, alone, and by it ſelf (which the Canoniſts themſelves acknowledge to be groſly <hi>Simoniacal</hi>) and the ſelling of the lands, to which the Patronage is annexed; in which caſe the Canoniſts declare, it is Simony, to take any Addition of price, for the Lands, upon the account of the Patronage annexed: which our Patrons did not in the leaſt notice. And the very Council of <hi>Trent</hi> it ſelf prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteth ſuch <hi>Sales,</hi> under the pain of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> and <hi>forfeiture</hi> of the Right of Patronage, to be incurred <hi>ipſo facto.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil: Trident: ſeſs:</hi> 25 <hi>decret de reform: cap:</hi> 9.</note> In this (to our ſhame it muſt be ſaid) the Papiſts ſhew more Conſcience and tenderneſs, than our own Laws, and the moſt of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons do. They alſo diſcover more tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in reſpect of the perſons capable to be inveſted with the right of Patronage, when they maintain, that the patron looſeth his Right, and the Kirk becomes free of the ſervitude, <hi>ſipatronus ſit haereticus:</hi> whereas on the contrar our patrons, might and did <hi>ſell</hi> their Rights, to any they pleaſed, yea even to Papiſts, and ſuch as were under the higheſt Church cenſures.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. Farther, (as I have already hinted)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60402:16"/>all the Patronages, that before the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did belong to any Religious houſes (as they are termed) or to the Pope, as patron <hi>Supreme, Paramount</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> and all other Patronages, to which, another perſon, could not inſtruct a ſufficient right, were taken into the Kings hands, as ſucceeding to, and coming in their places, and were by him diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon, to whom he pleaſed, by rights un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Great Seal</hi> &amp;c And the truth is, this is a ſort of ſucceſſion. very ſutable to the Kings other pretences of Supremacy, and Headſhip of the Church, which in effect make him a new Pope, in a reformed Church, <hi>Rex idem hominum Phoebique Sacerdos,</hi> as if the deſign of the Reformation had not been, to <hi>ſeparate</hi> our ſelves from the unjuſt and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian power, uſurped over the Church, by the Popes; but meerly, to <hi>transfer</hi> it, from <hi>Italy</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and lodge it, in the perſon of the Prince, among ourſelves. And hence it is cleare, that tho' there be an ordinar diſtinction of Kirks, into elective and pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onate, which ſome urge for a conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance at Patronage; yet with us, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains not the leaſt ſhadow, of an elective Kirk, in the whole nation.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Seventhly the Canoniſts tell us, that the right of Patronage, was often granted,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60402:16"/>to ſuch as had not in the leaſt been Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors to the Church, in the Erection or dot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Kirks; And that <hi>per modum ſpecialis privilegii,</hi> granted be the Pope, <hi>ſolent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim pontifices, nonunnquam ſe àecretorum Dominos, ac Conditores oſtendere.</hi> That they may let the World ſee, they are the <hi>abſolute Maſters,</hi> &amp; unaccountable Arbiters, alſe well as the Makers of the Canons.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. Eightly, the Canoniſts alſo tell us, that the patron may commit and <hi>Intrust,</hi> his power of preſentation, to any other ſpecially authorized for that end. And thus we have frequently ſeen among our ſelves, the Factors and <hi>Chamberlanes</hi> of Noblemen and others, act by vertue of ſuch <hi>Commiſſions,</hi> in theſe matters.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. And laſtly, they alſo tell us, that ſuch patrons, as are preciſely paſt ſeven years of age, and far more ſuch as are within mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, may preſent <hi>by themſelves,</hi> without the advice or concurſe of their <hi>Tutors</hi> and <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators,</hi> tho' ſome of the Canoniſts do require, that <hi>Tutors</hi> and <hi>Curators</hi> do it <hi>in their Name.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60402:17"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>The Opinion of our Reformers</hi> &amp;c. <hi>concerning</hi> PATRONAGE.</head>
               <p n="1">I AS this corrupt cuſtom of Patronage, ſpread over the Church in general, ſo we find the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> in particular, wanted not her ſhare in the common Calamity. And accordingly we find this pretended Priviledge, zealouſly witneſſed againſt, by our worthy <hi>Reformers,</hi> who vigorouſly preſſed, for the removal of it. And we find alſo that other Foreign Churches, were ſenſible of the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, the Church lay under, by theſe priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. I cannot ſtay to inſert teſtimonies at large, the Reader may fully ſatisfie himſelf, in the matter, if he will be at the pains to look over the firſt and ſecond Books of Diſcipline,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>I Book of Difci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plia head.</hi> 4 2 <hi>Book of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin cap.</hi> 3. <hi>and</hi> 12. <hi>Gen. aſſemb.</hi> 1562. <hi>ſeſs,</hi> 3 <hi>Gen. aſſemb.</hi> 1586. <hi>ſeſs.</hi> 5. <hi>Synod Dordracen</hi>
                  </note> of this Church, the Acts of our general Aſſemblies, and the Acts of the Famous Synod of <hi>Dort.</hi> As for the opinion of particular Divines tho' they have but very little medled with theſe Matters, yet when ever they touch them, they declare them to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60402:17"/>a very grievous and burdenſome uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in ſome meaſure we may have occaſion to ſee, in the following part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="2">II. And truly no leſs could be expected from men of ſo much Piety and Zeal, for the Glory of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conc. Triden. Seſs.</hi> 25 <hi>decret. de Refor. cap.</hi> 9. <hi>ſeſs.</hi> 14. <hi>decret. de Refor. cap.</hi> 12 <hi>&amp;</hi> 13 <hi>&amp; ſeſs.</hi> 24. <hi>decret. de Reform cap.</hi> 18 <hi>Conc. Mogunt. cap.</hi> 68.</note> and the Intereſts of his Church, ſince even the moſt corrupt aſſembly that ever mett, I mean the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> is forced to acknowledge, the great prejudice, the Church ſuſtains, by the Rights of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, as is clear from what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready hinted and from their other decrees, in the years 1551 and 1563. And before them the provincial Council at <hi>Mentz</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> in the year 1549, was very ſenſible of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and oppreſſion, of theſe Privileges: as we may have occaſion to mention here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p n="3">III. But after the <hi>Shaking</hi> that theſe Rights of Patronage got, at our Reformation from <hi>Popery,</hi> the alteration of that comely and orderly Church Government, inſtituted by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and which we received both with Chriſtianity it ſelf, and in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with our firſt Reformation from <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> darkneſs, and under which, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny abuſes, both in Church and State, were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60402:18"/>ſo happily taken away, and ſo much of the purity and plenty of Goſpel Ordinances, with a moſt wonderful Succeſs eſtabliſhed; The alteration. I ſay, of this our Presbiterial Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, into Prelacy, gave this Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and many others new Root. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der prelacy a Government firſt and laſt violently obtruded upon this Church, contrary to the inclinations of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without any warrand from the word of God, or example either in pure antiquity, or other reformed Churches abroad, for no other end, but to bear down, the juſt and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Liberties of the Church, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of ſin, and in the Exerciſe of diſcipline, and to be ſubſervient for carrying on, the bad deſigns of a corrupt court party, for enſlaving of both Church and State, and conſtantly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, with a moſt Viſible and General de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, both in Worſhip and Morals. Under this Prelacy it was, that this and many other corruptions, and ſuperſtitions, were vigorouſly advanced and ſupported. The Prelats leaving no means uneſſayed, to inhaunce all the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages they could in their own hands, or in the hands of ſuch, as would contribute their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and intereſt, to promote the deſigns then on foot, for enſlaving this Church and Nation, under a yoak of Bondage and Superſtition, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60402:18"/>to keep out all ſuch, from any acceſs to the Work of the Miniſtry, as were in the leaſt ſuſpected, of a deſire to croſs theſe ill deſigns: ſo that at length, the Right of Patronage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo rooted and fixed, and ſo twiſted and inter woven, with other ſecular and civil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, that it was expreſly avowed and plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, as a part of a Mans <hi>private Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> the Rights whereof he had ſettled and confirmed <hi>to him and his heirs</hi> after him, as theſe of his other eſtate, by <hi>Charters</hi> under the <hi>Seals</hi> &amp;c. And might Lawfully ſell and diſpoſe of it, to whom he thought fit, as well as the reſt of his Fortune: And from which he could not be excluded, without the higheſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury and injuſtice.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Theſe Exorbitancies of patronage, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready mentioned, with many others too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to relate, (wherein our Patronages, are many times very different <hi>to the worſe,</hi> from theſe in the <hi>Canon Law)</hi> a man in reaſon would think, might be ſufficient without any farther enquiry or debate, to determine us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a Priviledge. But ſince this (as well as other corruptions) is to this day, by ſome perſons, with ſo much heat and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence aſſerted, and defended, tho' the juſtice of the publick Authority of the Nation, in aboliſhing theſe priviledges was in the year
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60402:19"/>1649, and ſeveral years thereafter very cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially acquieſced unto by the moſt of thoſe, who had the largeſt ſhare of them: I ſhall therefore in the next place, according to the method propoſed, with all the plainneſs and brevity I can, enquite into, and examine the Grounds, which are, or may be adduced, for a Foundation to the Rights of Patronage, which will yet farther diſcover the injuſtice and unwarrantable burdenſomneſs of this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</p>
               <p n="5">V. I hope I need not advertiſe the Reader, that it is not my deſign to fix the guilt of all the abuſes, with which I charge this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Priviledge, upon all the Patrons in the Nation: I know many of them are, and have been, very pious and worthy Perſons, and have been honoured, even in that capacity to do the Church very good ſervice, by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of honeſt and faithful Miniſters, in ſome times of defection. But after all I muſt in this diſtinguiſh, betwixt the <hi>intentio Rei,</hi> and the <hi>intentio Perſonae,</hi> or betwixt the tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Inſtitution it ſelf, and the honeſty of ſome Men, that have managed the ſame; it being the Law of God, and the Principles of Juſtice and Reaſon, and not men's Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that ſpecify their Actions to be good, or bad, as is very evident (to inſtance no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60402:19"/>in the caſe of <hi>Aaron's</hi> Golden Calf, and <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> which they intended for the true Worſhip of the God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.45. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.23, 24, 25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.41. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.28. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.15.</note> and yet the Spirit of God tells us, it was for the Worſhip of Devils, (which clearly overthrows all the <hi>Jeſuitick</hi> quibbles, about a right intention) And I muſt alſo ſay, that all the good that ever the Church had, or can have by the Right of Patronage, can never countervail the trouble and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age it hath occaſioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>The Ground and Argument for</hi> Patronage, <hi>from a</hi> Reſervation <hi>by the firſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THe firſt, and main, if not the only Ground, that with any colour of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can be urged, for a Foundation to the Rights of Patronage, is this; That it ſeems moſt undutiful and unreaſonable to deny that Priviledge, to ſuch as have deſerved ſo well of the Church, by building of Kirks, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of a conſtant Maintenance, on ſuch
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60402:20"/>as ſhould ſerve the Cure thereat, and which priviledge at the time of the <hi>grant,</hi> they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly <hi>reſerved</hi> to themſelves, and their <hi>heirs</hi> after them, &amp; whereof they accordingly have been ſo long in poſſeſſion: and that, if this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge be denyed, it will prove a great diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, for any to gratifie the Church, with ſuch favours, for the future.</p>
               <p n="2">II. This being as I have ſaid, the main ground, that can be urged in this matter, I ſhall take the more pains diſtinctly to diſcuſs it.</p>
               <p>For anſwer then to the firſt part of the pretence, from the <hi>Reſervation</hi> of Patronage, by the firſt <hi>Founders,</hi> and <hi>Doters</hi> of Kirks and Benefices, Theſe things may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Firſt, that if the Patrons will needs ſtand upon this pretence, of a <hi>reſervation,</hi> may we not on much better ground, retort, that the Patrons have forfeited their rights, if they had any, by their not performing theſe <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> on which only (if we may believe the Canoniſts) the Pope, and other Biſhops, granted, and the patrons accepted, the rights of Patronage? <hi>viz</hi> That the patron ſhould be oblidged, to <hi>uphold</hi> and <hi>repair</hi> the Kirk, when it is <hi>like</hi> to <hi>fall,</hi> or proves <hi>ruinous.</hi> 2. That he ſhould be oblidged to <hi>rebuild</hi> it, if it were <hi>burnt</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60402:20"/>or <hi>ſhaken down</hi> by an <hi>Earthquake</hi> &amp;c. 3. That he ſhould be oblidged to <hi>defend</hi> the benifice from being <hi>dilapidat</hi> or <hi>miſapplyed,</hi> and that he ſhould take care, that on all occaſions the <hi>Paſtors</hi> were <hi>furniſhed,</hi> with a due <hi>mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi> And as it is ſufficiently known, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſutably the Patrons have acted to all theſe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, ſo the burden of the moſt, if not the whole of this charge, is by Law laid upon the <hi>heretors</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of the reſpective <hi>paroches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. Next, I ſhall but mention what I have formerly marked of the Patrons forfeitur of their rights, by the <hi>ſale</hi> of their Patronages, contrare to the <hi>Prohibitions</hi> of the Canon Law and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">V. The Patrons muſt not take it ill to be told that the pretence of a <hi>reſervation,</hi> unleſs it be <hi>produced,</hi> is but <hi>gratis dictum,</hi> and can never be ſuſtained, as being againſt the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>preſumption</hi> of <hi>liberty;</hi> whereas all <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vituds,</hi> ſuch as Patronage is acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be, are never <hi>preſumed,</hi> but moſt be <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively</hi> and <hi>evidently inſtructed.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let them pretend what they will. I muſt make bold to ask them, <hi>Quomodo conſtat</hi> that ever ſuch a <hi>Reſervation</hi> was made; If they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not produce ſomewhat elſe, beſide their own aſſertion, we muſt tell them, that <hi>de non exiſtentibus, &amp; de non apparentibus idem eſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60402:21"/>Judicium:</hi> a thing that <hi>is not</hi> at all, and a thing that <hi>appeares not</hi> by <hi>evident proof,</hi> are in the ſame caſe. And there is no right or claim can be founded or ſuſtained upon either of them.</p>
               <p n="6">VI Fourthly, it is very improbable, that at a time in which <hi>Ignorance</hi> did ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, &amp; that the moſt part of all Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Conveyances, even of the moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant rights, were performed, without the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing</hi> of any <hi>act</hi> or <hi>deed in Writting: uſe</hi> and <hi>wont,</hi> and a ſort of <hi>moral honeſty,</hi> being, the <hi>best ſecurities</hi> any man had; I ſay, it is very improbable, that at ſuch a time, the building and doting of Kirks, was managed in ſo good form, as to have any <hi>written act</hi> or <hi>Instrument,</hi> either for the building or the dot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or for the <hi>Reſervation</hi> of the right of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, upon that account. And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently it is highly improbable, that ever ſuch <hi>Reſervations</hi> can be inſtructed, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. And it is moſt certain, that in theſe times when Kirks were firſt built, and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices ſetled, the <hi>Ignorance,</hi> or if you will the <hi>ſimplicity,</hi> both of this, and many other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, was ſuch, as we have deſcribed, and in ſome places continues ſo to this day, as (to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance no farther) may be ſeen, in ſome of the remot corners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> eſpecially theſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60402:21"/>of the northern Iſlands, of <hi>Orknay &amp; Zetland,</hi> where the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dal Rights</hi> (as they term them) are in uſe, and where Civility. Learning and good policy have not yet ſo far prevailed, as to wear out that old cuſtom, albeit it be worn out of moſt of the other parts of the Land.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Fifthly, as we have formerly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Right of Patronage at firſt, was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>after-Game,</hi> that <hi>creept in clandestin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and by <hi>ſtealth,</hi> upon the Church, than the effect of any <hi>poſitive</hi> inſtitution, or of any <hi>expreſs reſervation,</hi> made at the time of the <hi>founding</hi> or <hi>doting</hi> of Kirks. And tho' there may be ſome Kirks and benefices, that in lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, have been built and ſetled, ſince Learning and policy began to flouriſh in ſome greater meaſure than formerly, whereof the firſt and <hi>original foundations,</hi> bear ſuch a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation;</hi> yet as the number of ſuch will be found to be very ſmall, ſo theſe can ſay nothing, for a ground to the Rights of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, <hi>in general.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Sixthly it is undenyable, that the moſt part of Patronages are grounded upon meer <hi>cuſtom,</hi> and <hi>frequent acts of preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> without the leaſt pretence, to any <hi>reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of this nature; or they are founded on ancient <hi>preſcription</hi> paſt memory of man (and perhaps declaratory ſentences may be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60402:22"/>obtained thereon) as both our own <hi>Lawyers</hi> and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> do acknowledge: and thence that Council,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil: Trident ſeſs:</hi> 25. <hi>decret. de reform. cap</hi> 9.</note> doth rationally enough conclude, that in many caſes <hi>Jus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronatus plerumque ex uſurpatione quaeſitum eſt,</hi> that is, that for the moſt part it is uſurped without any warrand. And upon the ſame ground perhaps it is, that one of the moſt judicious of our own Lawyers, does ſo much inſiſt upon ane <hi>expreſs reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir, T: Hope.</hi> 2.</note> as neceſſar to the <hi>Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of Patronage; tho' perhaps he may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low preſumptions of long poſſeſſion, frequent Acts of preſentation and Infeſtments from the King, to be ſufficient <hi>in foro Juridico,</hi> to infer that <hi>reſervation,</hi> and to ſuſtain the right of Patronage, according to the courſe of our cuſtoms, which in this caſe were founded upon the Canon Law, before the Reformation, and were not antiquat by any publick conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on long after that time.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. Seventhly, the Patrons ſhifting to old Characters and Impreſſions, upon the Kirk walls, Bells, Chalices and other Utenciles, for probation of their Rights, does clearly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, they can inſtruct no ſuch <hi>Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">X. Eightly, the Canoniſts do grant, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60402:22"/>the Right of Patronage was ordinarly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute otherways than by ſuch <hi>Reſervations,</hi> when they tell us, that the Pope <hi>per modum privilegii,</hi> conferred this Right on whom he thought fit, tho' they had never beſtowed a Farthing upon the Church, as we have marked in the beginning of this diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. And laſtly, the ſame Canoniſts do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo acknowledge, that the Right of Patronage, hath been obtained many otherways, than by ſuch <hi>reſervations:</hi> for tho' the founders had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver claimed the Right of Patronage in their own time, nor their Children after them; yet they tell us, that the founders poſterity, for ſome Generations after, might, and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did, obtain a grant of the Right of Patronage, with the clauſe <hi>ex nunc, ut ex tunc</hi> &amp;c. And it is little to be doubted, but that <hi>in re antiqua</hi> ſuch as this neceſſarly behoved to be, the Pope and <hi>Roman Chancery</hi> were frequently influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the intereſt and power of parties, and other By-conſiderations, to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with very ſlender proofs, either as to the perſons who were the Founders, or as to the Relation of thoſe who claimed the Right, upon the account of their propinquity to them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when no other perſon appeared to oppoſe their claime: and it is very probable that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as in many other caſes where Rights or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60402:23"/>ſentences are exped <hi>abſente Reo,</hi> they might be ſatisfied with a naked alledgance, as to both theſe points, without any farther, if there was but the leaſt pretence of a general Citation <hi>&amp;c,</hi> to infer contumacy for not compearing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>A farther examination of this</hi> Reſervation, <hi>from its own Nature, and from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Pious and Charitable Deeds,</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. BUT not to inſiſt any farther on theſe grounds, we may obſerve in the next place, that ſuch <hi>Reſervations,</hi> tho' they were clearly Inſtructed in all Patronages, and that other methods of conſtituting theſe Rights had not been uſed; yet theſe <hi>Reſervations</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be here regarded. For as Lawyers tell us, unlawful Conditions adjected to a grant of any thing are null and ineffectual; and they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it as a rule that <hi>conditio illicita habetur pro non adjectâ.</hi> And therefore ſuch a <hi>Reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as this of the Right of Patronage, in the foundation of a <hi>Kirk</hi> or <hi>Benefice,</hi> being in it ſelf a Sinful and unlawful <hi>condition,</hi> without any warrand from the word of God, contrare to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60402:23"/>the Churches true Freedom and Intereſt, and inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of theſe Spiritual Liberties and Priviledges conferred upon her, by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> her only Head and Law giver (as we ſhall fully demonſtrate in the ſequel of this diſcourſe) it muſt be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, as if it had never been <hi>made,</hi> not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended either to be <hi>claimed</hi> or practiſed. <hi>Et quod ab initio non valuit, tractu temporis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valeſcere nequit.</hi> That which was void and null from the beginning, can never be made effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, by any tract or courſe of time, how long ſo ever. So that ancient poſſeſſion, can be no better Plea in this caſe, than it could be for many other unqueſtionably unlawful and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious cuſtoms.</p>
               <p n="2">II. But in the next place, it may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that who ever builds a Kirk, or gives ground for thur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, or ſettles a maintenance on the the Incumbents he does it either.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Per modum debiti,</hi> by way of debt or duty, or</p>
               <p n="2">2. He does it <hi>per modum Eleemoſynae,</hi> That is by way of Almes or free Charity. or</p>
               <p n="3">3. He does it, partly <hi>per modum debiti</hi> and partly <hi>per modum Eleemoſynae,</hi> partly the one way, and partly the other or,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Which is worſe, he does it from a <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical principle</hi> of <hi>Vain glory,</hi> and to be ſeen of Men. or,</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60402:24"/>5. Which is worſt of all, he does it out of an <hi>Opinion</hi> of <hi>Merit,</hi> thinking that he can thereby deſerve Life and Happineſs at the Hands of God.</p>
               <p n="3">III. To apply this diſtinction to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, let us conſider.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Theſe who has conferred ſuch good offices on the Church, as the building or doting of Kirks, <hi>per modum debiti,</hi> are ſuch as are He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retors or Proprietars of the whole Lands and Rents, within that bounds, in which the Kirk is ſituat, and for the benefit and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of the Inhabitants whereof. The Kirk is built, or the Benefice ſettled. And this ſort of <hi>Benefactors</hi> do no more in this, but what by the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> and much more, by the <hi>Revealed Will</hi> and <hi>Law of God,</hi> and the <hi>Municipal Laws</hi> and Cuſtoms, of the Chriſtian ſtate in which they live, they are oblidged, and might be legally compelled to do.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. For as it is a Principle acknowledged all the World over, that all reaſonable Creatures, and much more Chriſtians ought not only privatly and in ſecret, by themſelves and in their Families, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, joyntly, ſolemnly and in publick, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and adore, that Almighty God, who is the firſt fountain and author, and the Soveraign
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60402:24"/>Lord and Arbiter, of their lives and beings, and their Sole and only Saviour from the guilt and puniſhment of Sin: and on whom they muſt neceſſarly depend for every minuts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and for all their Temporal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs here, and Eternal Happineſs hereafter: ſo in conſequence of this <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>moral</hi> duty, they are alſo oblidged to have Temples, or large and convenient Meeting places (as the word ſignifies <hi>Templum quaſi tectum am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum</hi>) for that end, where they may be cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſheltered from the injuries of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in going about theſe duties. As alſo in conſequence of the ſame duty, They are likewiſe oblidged, to ſettle a ſutable mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, on ſuch as are ſequeſt rate and ſet a part from all other Imployments, to attend this Worſhip and Service, and to inſtruct their People in the Myſteries of Religion. <hi>Quando enim aliquid conceditur, id etiam concedi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur, ſine quo conceſſum ſubſistere non poteſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And accordingly we find the practice of all Nations, in all ages, how barbarous ſo ever hath been ſutable hereunto.</p>
               <p n="5">V. And therefore this being a Natural and acknowledged duty, the burden of it muſt neceſſarly be charged upon ſuch as have the <hi>only interest</hi> and property in the Lands and Rents, within that bounds: ſo that we may
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60402:25"/>ſafely conclude, that ſuch Benefactors as theſe, are ſo far from <hi>deſerving</hi> ſuch a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge over the Church, and her Liberties thereby, that (as our Bleſſed Saviour ſays) <hi>when they have done all that is Commanded them to do,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 17.</note> they muſt acknowledge themſelves, <hi>to be unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Servants, and that they have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what was their duty</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI Next, ſuch Heretors and <hi>Proprietars,</hi> tho' the whole charge does Naturally ly upon them, yet they have alwayes the concurrence, of the reſt of the Inhabitants of the bounds (tho' theſe have no intereſt of property in the Lands) And thereby a <hi>Proportional</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a <hi>greater releife</hi> of the <hi>burden:</hi> So that ſuch Benefactors do not in that caſe ſo much as their duty oblidges them to do, and therefore they do ſtill leſs deſerve ſuch a priviledge</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Laſtly we do not find that any of the People or Princes of Iſrael ſuch as <hi>David, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>  for all the vaſt expence of treaſure, they laid out, upon the building and repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, or upon the many Synagogues, that were ſpred up and down the Land, ſome whereof were built, at the privat charge of ſingle perſons,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 7th.</note> And thoſe Strangers and Foraigners too, who were under
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60402:25"/>no obligation, by being born within the Land ſo to do; I ſay, we do not find, that any of thoſe Princes or people, for all the vaſt expence they were at, did ever lay claim to the leaſt ſhaddow, of ſuch a priviledge, in reference to the Call and Maintenance of the Officers of the Chnrch</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. And under the new Teſtament, we find as little mention of ſuch a priviledge; for all the large poſſeſſions and donatives that were beſtowed by the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, upon pious uſes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32: <hi>to the end</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 8: <hi>Philip:</hi> 4: <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 4. <hi>Gal:</hi> 6.</note> were given freely and frankly, without reſerve. The practiſe of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> and of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> do indeed look another way; But ſure I am, neither their actions nor appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, will incline any man that is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether deſerted of God, to an imitation of their example. The native uſe we are to make of theſe Beacons, ſo <hi>early</hi> ſet up in the Chriſtian Church, is to Caution us from Steiring near theſe rocks, on which they Split.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. The ſecond ſort of Benefactors menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>viz</hi> thoſe who confer favours on the Church, <hi>per modum Eleemoſynae,</hi> or by way of pure almes and free Charity, are ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as having no civil intereſt or eſtate within
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60402:26"/>the bounds, do build a Kirk, or dote the ſame with a maintenance more or leſs, meerly from a principle of Compaſſion to the people, who dwell therein, and perhaps ly at a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or otherwiſe inconveniently, for other meeting places of publick worſhip; with a ſingle heart for advancing the Glory of God, and for promoting the ſpiritual intereſt and welfare of the Souls of his people. Theſe tho' they be the only perſons, that can be ſaid to confer real favour on the Church, and to do true acts of Charity, and ſo may ſeem to have a much fairer pretence to claim the Right of patronage, than any of the other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors, I mean the <hi>first Donors</hi> themſelves (for as to <hi>heires</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſors,</hi> they are terms very unſutable in this affair, as I have already hinted, and ſhall yet farther cleare) yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, we muſt ſtill conclude, that even thoſe can be allowed no ſuch priviledge.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Firſt, becauſe the deſign and nature of ſuch good deeds, can never be conſtructed ſo, as to deprive the Church of her freedom of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, which ſhe enjoyed before ſuch a grant: For this would truely bring thoſe Benefactors under the guilt of a deſign of <hi>Robbery,</hi> which is abſolutely inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of the nature and deſign of Charity.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. For if ſuch favours be really conferred
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60402:26"/>on the Church <hi>per modum purae Eleemoſynae,</hi> or by way of pure Charity, there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more unſutable, to the nature or deſign of alms-giving, or more deſtructive of it than either to aſſume, or expect, a recompence of gain, applauſe or any other temporal reward; and much leſs can ſuch an enſlaving privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as this of Patronage be expected: For <hi>almes</hi> as <hi>almes,</hi> look for no recompence or reward, from thoſe on whom they are beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 31.16 <hi>to</hi> 24 <hi>Job:</hi> 29.13. <hi>proverbs</hi> 19: 7. <hi>mat:</hi> 6</note> ſave that of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the Lord, to whom Gifts of that nature are ſaid to be lent, and who hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to repay them accordingly. And the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinar <hi>reddendo</hi> of <hi>pia animarum ſuffragia,</hi> from thoſe who receive the <hi>Almes,</hi> cannot be otherways underſtood, in any ſound ſenſe. Thus <hi>Job</hi> glories, that the <hi>Bleſſing of him that was ready to periſh, came upon him:</hi> And ſurely, he that takes or expects any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther return <hi>hath his reward</hi> (as our Saviour ſayes) and can expect no other. So that he who by ſuch good Deeds, expects to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain either a <hi>Jus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile,</hi> or a <hi>Jus Honorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> eſpecially that part of it, which is ſo prejudicial to the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> the Patron's <hi>negative</hi> Intereſts, in the Election and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Miniſtry, ſeems to ſay as much
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60402:27"/>as that he neither is <hi>that chearful and liberal Giver, whom the Lord loves:</hi> nor that he looks upon God, who hath promiſed to pay and requite him, to be a ſufficient Pay-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and therefore that he will betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a recompence, by this unſutable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. Secondly, That which is once given away, and conſecrate to the Lord for pious Uſes, is no more his that gave it, as is clear from the caſe of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 5.</note> and therefore no man can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to retain any private Intereſt in it. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legantly ſaid by <hi>Emanuel Comnenus</hi> the Emperor,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Novel</hi> 1. <hi>de execus. Teſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtum haereden ſcribere quis videtur, cum pauper ibus ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias ſuas dividi praecipit: cum enim Mendicans accipit Chriſtus astat, ac una cum illo manu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> porrigit: Quatenus nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> inquit <hi>uni ex minim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hiſce meis fratribus feciſtis, mihi feciſtis,</hi> &amp;c. That is a man ſeems to deſign Jeſus Chriſt for his Heir, when he ordains his goods to be diſtribute to the poor, for when a beggar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Almes, Chriſt himſelf ſtands by, and ſtretcheth forth his own hand with him, for <hi>in as much</hi> (ſays he) <hi>as you did it to the leaſt of my Brethren, you did it to me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. But to clear this yet farther, it may be obſerved, that any Right a Patron can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60402:27"/>to give a Paſtor, to his maintenance, is <hi>quoad</hi> the Paſtor, but a groundleſs pretence, and ſo a <hi>ſuper vacaneous</hi> and uſeleſs grant, the Paſtors Right to his maintenance, being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed in his perſon, by his lawful Call to the Miniſtry, and his faithful diſcharge of it: So that unleſs the Patron will pretend, that he can put a Miniſter in a <hi>ſpiritual ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity,</hi> and ſo claim the power of <hi>Ordination,</hi> (which is indeed Chriſt's Power committed to his Miniſters) as well as that of Election, he can give him no right to his maintenance, but ſuch as will be ſuperfluous: For as <hi>abundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia non vitiat,</hi> ſo neither does it ſtrengthen or confirm a right: And tho' what the Patron gives, ſhould be granted to be a confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet it can give no new right, <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatio enim nihil novi juris addit, ſed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquum jus tantum roborat)</hi> it being the Paſtors <hi>ſpiritual capacity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18.</note> and faithful diſcharge of his duty, and that <hi>only,</hi> which gives him a full and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Title to his Wages.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. Next it may be obſerved very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, that if what a man hath once given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and devoted to the Lord, for pious uſes, be no more his that gave it, then certainly the founder of a benefice, cannot expect to retain to himſelf, and much leſs to his heirs and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60402:28"/>a <hi>negative Intereſt</hi> in the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, with ſo little uſe and advantage, and ſo much prejudice, to the Church. And therefore tho' ſuch Acts of Favour and Charity, as are freely and gratui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly beſtowed on the Church, ſeem to plead more for the Rights of Patronage, than ſuch as are done, <hi>per modum debiti,</hi> or for ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyng of a <hi>Moral duty,</hi> and obligation, to which the Donor or Founder was <hi>previouſly</hi> engaged; yet there is none who perform ſuch Acts, out of the ſingleneſs of their Heart, and from a true principle of advancing the Glory of God, and a ſincere motive of Compaſſion, to their poor Brethren, that will <hi>ſciens volens,</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly and willingly, deſire or expect a Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo uſeleſs and yet ſo hurtful to the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Church, and the good of Souls. This were indeed <hi>a Flie in the Appothecaries Oyntment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">XV. The thrid ſort of <hi>Benefactors,</hi> to wit, thoſe who confer Favours on the Church, partly <hi>per modum debiti,</hi> and partly <hi>per mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Eleemoſynae,</hi> partly by way of debt, and partly by way of almes, and free Charity, are ſuch perſons as have ſome civil intereſt and eſtate, within the bounds where the Kirk lyes, but not the whole. And therefore their building or doting of a Kirk, is neither
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60402:28"/>wholly Duty, nor wholly Charity, but part of both. They being indeed previouſly oblidg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereto, but are not oblidged to do it alone, and without the Concurrence of the reſt of that bounds, for bearing their ſhare of the common Burden; ſeing he that ſo dots or builds is but one of many having intereſt. And thoſe Benefactors can as little as the former, expect to be gratified with the Priviledge of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, for the Reaſons already mentioned. For if neither he who acts in ſuch matters wholly <hi>per modum debiti,</hi> nor he who acts wholly and intirely <hi>per modum Eleemoſynae,</hi> can with any reaſon aſſume or expect ſuch a priviledge; Then alſo by a neceſſary conſequence, he who Acts in beſtowing ſuch favours on the Church, partly the one way, and partly the other, hath as little, if not leſs ground than either of them, to expect or aſſume the ſame.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. There is a fourth ſort of Benefactors (if they deſerve the Name) and thoſe are ſuch, as do their good deeds, meerly out of oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and from a Phariſaical principle of Vain glory, &amp; to be ſeen of Men, to gain the applauſe of the World, and not to advance the Glory of God, or the good of his Church. And for the moſt part thoſe Men beſtow their Favours, where there is little or no need, ſeldom or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſulting, how, or where, they may place
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60402:29"/>them, with moſt advantage for the publick good, but ſatisfie themſelves, if they can place them in ſuch a way, as they may bear moſt bulk in the eyes of the World. This is a truth ſo undenyable that it was certainly from this vanity, that the <hi>Monaſtries, Nunneries, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacies, Pryories, Cloysters,</hi> &amp;c. both in this and other Nations, before the Reformation from Popery; and in other Popiſh Countries to this day, were endowed with ſo many rich livings, that in ſome places they poſſeſt near, or above a third of the whole Land, in others near a full half, as the devotion (as it was then termed) or rather the ſuperſtitious folly, of a ſimple and ignorant People, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and intereſt of a cheating and idle Clergy, inclined them. Thus many Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men turned in effect to be <hi>Temporal Princes:</hi> And generally the intereſt of the Clergy in the Legiſlative Power, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the Government of theſe Nations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came very large upon the account of the great Intereſt and Authority they enjoyed, by ſuch ample Revenues and Poſſeſſions, which was the true Original, of making the Clergy the <hi>third Eſtate</hi> in the <hi>Conventions</hi> and <hi>General Councils</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> both in theſe Lands, and elſe where. But thoſe Benefactors, if they may be ſo named, are ſo fully expoſed by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60402:29"/>our Bleſſed Lord, in that 6. of <hi>Matth.</hi> and elſewhere,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.</note> that it will be needleſs to inſiſt any farther upon them. And certainly this ſort of men leſs than any of the former, deſerve any truſt or privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Church of God; Their <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> which is the principal, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the only Motive and Deſign of all their Actions deſerves much rather the Cenſures of the Church, than any encouragment, by truſting them with a power, that they are utterly incapable to manage with any meaſure of Wiſdom or Diſcretion, which are Qualities that men of ſuch a vain and oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive humor, are ſeldom or never bleſſed with.</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. As for the laſt ſort of Benefactors, To wit, ſuch as from an <hi>opinion</hi> of <hi>Merit,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch good Offices on the Church, thinking thereby to deſerve life and happineſs at the hands of God, and going about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſs by the works of the Law; it is little wonder that ſuch men, who do ſo highly injure and rob our bleſſed Lord and only Saviour, of the honour of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat ranſom and ſatisfaction, payed by him to divine Juſtice, for the ſins of his elect, as to think that they can merit eternal felicity by their own works, which is to ſay in effect, that they will be their own Saviours, and that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60402:30"/>Chriſt died in vain; I ſay it is but little won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſuch men ſhould expect to be gratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with a power to encroach upon the rights of the Church, and to rob the members of Chriſt, of their ſpiritual liberties and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, as well as they have robbed the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous head of his due honour. But ſure I am, there is no ſincere Chriſtian in the Church of God, but will think a priviledge of this nature, worſe beſtowed upon thoſe, than upon the worſt of the former ſort of Benefactors, And therefore I ſhall ſay no farther as to them,</p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. Laſt of all, as this pretence of a <hi>Reſervation,</hi> is of no weight in favours of the firſt Founders or Donors themſelves, whether they confer ſuch good offices gratuitouſly or otherways, to give them the acclaimed rights of Patronage, in Retribution and recompence; ſo it hath much leſs force, to continue the ſame in favours of their <hi>heirs,</hi> or others who ſucceed them on a <hi>ſingular title</hi> of <hi>Donation, Sale, Permutation,</hi> &amp;c. For as thoſe may be very far from being indowed, with the merits and qualifications, of the firſt Donor; ſo for the moſt part, they are ſo far from tracing his footſteps, and example, by gratifying the Church, that with all their hearts, they would be content, if it were in their power, to void and nullifie, their Predeceſſors deeds. And
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60402:30"/>as in civil offices, it is, or ought to be, the merits or qualifications, of the Office bearer himſelf, that is reſpected in giving him the truſt, <hi>nam in officiis Perſonae industria reſpicitur,</hi> which alſo is the main reaſon, why <hi>regularly,</hi> a Judge or Magiſtrat, tranſmits not his office to his Heirs after him, nor ſubſtitutes another in his place: So much leſs in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical offices</hi> (ſuch as the Canoniſts pretend the power of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage to be) and truſts that concern the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al intereſts of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the good of Souls, ought the ſame to deſcend to <hi>heirs</hi> or others acquiring right upon a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular title.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>The</hi> Reſervation <hi>pretended can be no ground, for the</hi> Jus Utile <hi>of Patronage.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. AS to what may be alledged from this pretended <hi>Reſervation,</hi> for foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the <hi>Jus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> of Patronage, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>utilitas hujus Juris,</hi> whereby the Canoniſts pretend, that if the Patron or his Children become poor, ſo as they cannot live another way, they muſt be alimented out
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60402:31"/>of the Rents of the Benefice, as ſome ſort of a Retribution, for their having gratifyed the Church, when they were in power, tho' this may be ſufficiently cleared by application of the Grounds already mentioned, yet I ſhall deſire the Reader farther to conſider theſe things.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Firſt, that if this <hi>Jus utile,</hi> be a right to which the Patron will needs pretend a valid and <hi>legal Title,</hi> ſo as he may purſue for it, by an ordinar action at Law, before the <hi>civil Magiſtrat,</hi> as he may do for other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, that fall within his privat patrimony, I do not ſee, how any ſuch right can be allowed: For that which is once conſecrat, and devoted to God for pious uſes, is no more his that gave it, as we have cleared from the fore cited in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Ananias</hi> &amp; <hi>Saphira</hi> &amp;c. And therfore no man can retain any privat intereſt in it.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Next, if the Patron or his Children be really in neceſſity, and reſtrict the right pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to a <hi>claim</hi> in point of <hi>Charity,</hi> I think no man will deny, but there lyes an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon the Church, to extend their <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to them, in giving them a portion of theſe goods that belong to the <hi>poor,</hi> as far as ſhe can, without prejudging of others, who may deſerve her Charity, as well, and perhaps better, tho' on a different account. But in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60402:31"/>ſuch a caſe this Claim muſt not be allowed ſo far, as to <hi>exhaust</hi> what was given at firſt; for this were indeed to <hi>drain</hi> the <hi>fountain</hi> of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> which would be a <hi>miſericordia crudelis</hi> (ſo to ſpeak) an unjuſt and cruel mercy. It is a general rule in the diſpoſal of <hi>Charity, to do good to all men in need,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galat:</hi> 6: 10:</note> but ſtill with a <hi>preference</hi> in, favours of ſuch <hi>as are of the houſhold of Faith:</hi> one part of duty, muſt not ſhoulder out an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Chriſtian prudence muſt be adhibit as much in this, as in other matters. And as the Canoniſts them ſelves do grant, that the Patron is not to be alimented, except when he is <hi>truly</hi> in <hi>neceſſity;</hi> ſo many of them acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that even then he is only to be entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of ſuch goods as are deſtinate for the uſe of the poor, and ſo as his part of Charity do not prejudge others. <hi>Patronus non est alendus, niſide reſiduis duntaxat quae alias ſunt pauperum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. Laſtly, this is a right ſo perſonal to the Patron himſelf and his family, that it can never be bought and ſold, or be tranſmitted to others, who acquire right upon a ſingular Title: And ſo many of the Canoniſts deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this <hi>Jus utile,</hi> to be a right meerly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal, <hi>et adeo Iuhaerens oſſibus Patroni, ut in alium transferri nequeat:</hi> for otherwiſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60402:32"/>the Church upon this account, might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidged many times, to aliment both the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron himſelf, and thoſe who acquire right from him, if both ſhould happen to fall poor at the ſame time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The denyal of Patronage can be no diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in gratifying of the Church: ſomething</hi> obiter <hi>of the Dilapidation of the</hi> Church's Patrimony.</head>
               <p n="1">I. AS to the latter part of the Ground propoſed, for a Foundation to the Rights of Patronage, to wit, that the deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the Priviledges acclaimed, will prove diſcouraging for any to gratify the Church for the future, tho' by what is already ſaid, it be ſufficiently anſwered, yet I ſhall add,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That it is moſt certain, that ſuch as look for no higher reward and encouragment, than what a Priviledge within time can give them, and ſet not their Hearts on the promiſes of God, for the <hi>reward of a more enduring Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> than what a preſent World can furniſh
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60402:32"/>them with, will never be capable to perform the leaſt Act of pure and cleanly Charity, which thoſe only who betake themſelves to the true grounds of encouragment, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and word of God, and are free of low and ſelfiſh ends, can practiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Next, the aſſuming of ſuch a priviledge as this, over the Church, will be ſo far from being an encouragment, that upon a ſerious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat Reflection, we ſhall find, that as ſuch an uſurpation does highly injure the intereſts of the Church; ſo it will much more endamage thoſe that are guilty of it. by making a Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the rewards that the Lord hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to true Acts of Love and Charity, flowing from ſincere principles and motives, and for ſingle and honeſt ends: and may provock the divine Juſtice, to pour out his wrath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and their families, for keeping up humane inventions in the matters of God, ſo prejudicial to the true privileges and intereſts of his Church. But this we ſhall have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to clear farther, in the progreſs of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Next, if theſe be the only terms and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, on which men will gratifie the Church, that ſhe ſubject her ſelf and her ſpiritual Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to ſuch a yoke of Slavery, as this Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge imports, I am ſure the Church will be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60402:33"/>better without ſuch Favours, than with them.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. If there were once a reaſonable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency ſettled upon the Church, for the maintenance of her Paſtors, and other pious and neceſſary uſes, or if what was once ſettled, and ſacrilegiouſly taken from her, were again reſtored, and that faithfully adminiſtrat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dilapidation, and miſapplication; there would be but little need of encouragement, for any farther additions. It hath been obſerved in all Ages, That exceſſe in this matter, hath been more fatal to the true intereſts of the Church, than any defect could be. Too much tends to introduce a depravation of Life and Manners in Church-men, and by a neceſſar connexion, alſo a Corruption in Worſhip and Doctrine: If Wordly riches, had been proper for advancing the work of the Goſpel, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who was Lord of all, had never been ſo ſcant in his allowance to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Apoſtles. It is an old obſervation, that when the Church had but <hi>Lignei calices,</hi> ſhe had <hi>aurei Epiſcopi,</hi> and when ſhe got <hi>golden chalices,</hi> ſhe got <hi>wooden Biſhops</hi> or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. The ſenſe is eaſily underſtood, tho' it be not exactly literal. So true it is that <hi>Religio peper it divitias, &amp; Filia Matrem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voravit.</hi> Religion brought forth Riches and the daughter devoured the Mother.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:60402:33"/>V. Laſtly, to ſay that the denyal of the priviledges of Patronage, is the cauſe of this diſcouragement, Is but the <hi>Fallacia non cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae pro cauſa;</hi> for the truth is, that which is the only cauſe of Peoples diſcouragement, in the beſtowing of their goods for pious uſes, is the ſcandalous and ſacrilegious miſmanag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the uncontraverted Patrimony of the Church, by miſapplying it contrary to its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and nature, of which there are no ſort of Men under Heaven, ſo guilty, as many of the Patrons are. The Lord himſelf tells his Servant Moſes, <hi>no devouted thing, that a man ſhall devout unto the Lord of all that he hath both of Man and Beaſt,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Levit.</hi> 27 28.</note> and of the feild of his poſſeſſion, ſhall be ſold and redeemed,</hi> (and much leſs ſacrilegiouſly rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed) <hi>every devouted thing is moſt holy unto the Lord. Deo dicata</hi> (ſays <hi>Amandus Pola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>) <hi>Ei Sacra maneant,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Polanus in Danel. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> nam ſi Is zelus in Rege idololatrico (ſcilicet Nebuchadnezare) fuit, ut cenſuerit vaſa Deo Iſraelis Sancta; non alio quam in ſui Dei, ſeu potius Idoli fanum, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuda, multo magis Chriſtiani Magistratus, bona illa quae tempore Papatus Deo dicata fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt, uſibus Eccleſiae relinquere debent: Imo quanto magis Epiſcopos id facere decet.</hi> i. e. That which is once devouted to God, ought
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60402:34"/>to remain Holy to him, for if the zeal of an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Prince, (to wit <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi>) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blidged him to believe that the Holy Veſſells of the God of Iſrael, were not to be otherways diſpoſed of, but for the ſervice of his own God, or rather his Idols temple, much more ought a Chriſtian Magiſtrat, to leave theſe goods for the uſe of the Church, which in the time of Popery were conſecrat for pious uſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſee and compare this with <hi>Ezra,</hi> 1.7.8, where all theſe Veſſells are returned to their right and proper uſe.</p>
               <p>Our own <hi>Rollock,</hi> inveighs very ſharply, againſt the ſacriledge of this Nation, in his time, in miſapplying to the uſe of privat Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, what was taken from the Popiſh Church, and citeth ſuch as are guilty, to anſwer it, before the Tribunal of the Soveraign and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Judge of all the Earth:
<note place="margin">Rollock in Dan.</note> and he tells them that tho' they ſlight and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect his warning, it ſhall be a ſtanding witneſs againſt them, to render them <hi>Inexcuſable</hi> &amp;c. And our famous and worthy Reformer Mr. <hi>Knox,</hi> (whoſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny I value above a thouſand others) In a letter dated, in Auguſt, 1571. direct to the <hi>general Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Stirling,</hi> ſpeaks his mind very freely on this ſubject, with all the earneſtneſs &amp; ſincerity of a Perſon, that was looking very
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60402:34"/>ſhortly to ſtep over the Threſhold of time, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Eternity. Take his own words,
<q>Becauſe (ſays he) the dayly decay of my Natural ſtrength, threatens me with a ſudden depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from this valley of miſery, therefore of Love and Conſcience I exhort you, yea in the fear of God, I Charge and Command you, <hi>that you take heed to your ſelves and to the flock of God</hi> — And that with the like uprightneſs, and ſtrength in God, ye gainſtand the mercileſs Devourers, of the Patrimony of the Church. If Men will ſpoil, let them do it to their own Peril and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. But communicat ye not with their Sins, of whatſoever ſtate they be, neither by conſent, nor by ſilence, but with publick proteſtation, make known to the World, that ye are innocent of ſuch robbery, which will er'e it be long, provock God's vengence on the Committers of it <hi>&amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </q> And I am ſure the experience of many Families in Scotland may confirm this. <hi>Religione muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ</hi> ſays a learned Lawyer) <hi>&amp; ſic ſtatu priori inverſo,
<note place="margin">Finkel hoc.t.</note> Patronus curabit ut bona Eccleſiae, &amp; piis uſibus legata, non tantum preſerventur, &amp; augeantur, ſed ad uſum alium aeque pium, convertantur: puta ad cultum alium divinum, ad ſalutem Rei pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae, ad conſervandum Ministerium, ad ſum
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60402:35"/>Scholarum, pauperes juvandos, Noſocomia condenda</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> When there is an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion, and by conſequence an inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the former ſtate of Affairs, a Patron ought to take care, that the goods of the Church, and what is left for pious uſes, be not only preſerved and augmented, but that they be applyed to other as pious uſes: as for the worſhip of God in a lawful manner, for the ſafety of the Common wealth, for the maintaining of the Miniſtry, for the uſe of Schools, the help of the poor, the building of Hoſpitals. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. I might add the joint Teſtimony of our own Church, in her Books of Diſciplin <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; many other things. But this being a head that I have but accidentally fallen upon, and a Subject that would lead me out a great length and much farther than the deſign of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe will allow, I ſhall leave it. Such as deſire farther information, may find enough, and too much, to ſatisfie their curioſity, in the publick records of the Nation. They may alſo conſult the learned <hi>Sir Henry Spelman's</hi> tractat <hi>de non temerandis Eccleſits,</hi> and his larger work of <hi>Teiths.</hi> They may alſo ſee D. <hi>Forbes</hi>'s <hi>gemitus Eccleſiae.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60402:35"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>The Ground of Patronage, from a</hi> Grant <hi>or</hi> Conceſſion <hi>of the Church, examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THe next ground that is urged, for a foundation to the rights of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, is, that the Patrons of Kirks and Benefices, enjoy the priviledge acclaimed, in reference to the Call and Maintenance of the Miniſtry, by a <hi>grant</hi> and <hi>conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> from the Church, and that conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a Lawful inſtitution and no uſurpation, <hi>volenti enim non fit injuria.</hi> In explication of the meaning of this <hi>grant and conceſſion,</hi> ſome take one courſe and ſome another. For ſome by this <hi>grant</hi> do underſtand, that the Church hath <hi>alienat</hi> and transferred her right of Election, and <hi>divested</hi> her ſelf of it, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Patrons. Other again do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by this <hi>conceſſion,</hi> that the Patron acts by vertue of a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from, and as <hi>Impower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by the Church, without founding on any higher ground of <hi>Property,</hi> in the priviledge, by vertue of ane <hi>alienation</hi> of the right of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection made by the Church to him. I ſhall examin this <hi>conceſſion</hi> diſtinctly in both ſenſes,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60402:36"/>the firſt in this, and the other in the next Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Before we paſs any farther, it may be obſerved, that this ground adduced for a foundation of the right of Patronage does, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently acknowledge, that the right and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge acclaimed, is <hi>primarly</hi> and <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> a <hi>Church power,</hi> which were enough without any farther to take off this pretence.</p>
               <p n="3">III. But to come particularly to the firſt ſenſe, in which this pretended Conceſſion may be underſtood, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Church hath a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enat her right of Election, and diveſted her ſelf of it, in the Patrons favours, it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered,</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Church is utterly incapable to alienat or transfer her Spiritual rights, and priviledges, or to diveſt her ſelf of them: theſe are intereſts that are not at her deſpoſal, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only intruſted by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> her <hi>ſole King</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> with the <hi>cuſtody</hi> and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration</hi> of them, for the good and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, of the preſent and ſucceeding generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Theſe rights are founded upon a higher Title, than that they can be altered and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from hand to hand, by pactions or promiſes betwixt man and man. In ſuch caſes the Church can do nothing againſt the truth,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60402:36"/>ſhe is not therein <hi>ſui juris,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6, 20, <hi>and</hi> 7; 23.</note> ye are not your own,</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle,) <hi>ye are bought with a price, be not ye the ſervants of men,</hi> do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave your ſelves, by loſing your Rights and Liberties. The Church can no more make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her Spiritual Rights and Priviledges, or ſubject herſelf to ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ge Lords &amp; new Lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers therein, than a woman can make over the right of her Body, which only belongs to her Lawful Husband, or an Innocent perſon, the right of his life, to a Murderer, <hi>nemoeſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ſuae vitae aut ſuorum membrorum,</hi> or than a Prince, the rights of his Crown and Kingdom, and the liberties of his People to a foraign power, or a perſon in <hi>Non-age,</hi> the right of his eſtate (as the Apoſtle expreſly tells us, <hi>That the heir differs nothing here from a ſervant:</hi>) or in a word, then the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators, and Governours of a City and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, can Alienat the Rights of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituents. All theſe and many other acts of the like nature, as to the tranſlation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty are but fruſtraneous &amp; ineffectual endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, like a man's attempt to raiſe a weight that is without, and above the compaſs of his natural ſtrength, <hi>Grave ſaxum Syſyphon urget.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. And tho' <hi>de facto,</hi> ſuch attempts may oft be made, yet <hi>de jure,</hi> they are void and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60402:37"/>without effect. And let the conveyance be expreſt under what termes, and carried under what cover or diſguiſe you will, the right ſtands ſtill <hi>Immoveable,</hi> and remains where it was at firſt, <hi>nemo poteſt niſi quod de Jure poteſt,</hi> we can do nothing againſt the truth but for the truth.</p>
               <p n="5">V. It is our Lord Jeſus Chriſt and he alone (who is the Church's only Head and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver) that hath power, to ſettle the rights and priviledges of his Church, in ſuch hands and ſuch order, as his infinite love and wiſdom thinks fit. All the right and power the Church hath in theſe, is only a naked Truſt, to keep and manage them, according to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and inſtructions of her Lord and Maſter. And when ſhe exceeds that, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bords and goes beyond her Commiſſion, ſo that all the tranſmiſſion ſhe can make, is but <hi>Jus a non habente poteſtatem,</hi> like a grant of the property of an eſtate, by a perſon, that hath no other right to it, but a naked commiſſion to uplift and collect the rents, for the uſe of the true Proprietar: And therefore the Church without her Lord and Head's conſent, can alienate or diveſt her ſelf, of none of her rights and priviledges, that have been purchaſed to her, at no leſs rate then the precious Blood of the eternal Son of God. And as there is not the leaſt ground to pretend, that ever
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60402:37"/>
                  <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> hath given ſuch a conſent; ſo there is far leſs ground to expect, that ever he will give it now, after he hath ſealed his laſt will and teſtament, in all things that concern the Kingdom of God, by his own death: and hath declared, that he will have it ſtand firm and unalterable, by men or Angels, till he come again. The Church can no more diveſt her ſelf of the right ſhe hath to elect her own Office-bearers, than ſhe can transfert the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Kingdom of Chriſt, to which that liberty is annexed. And happy is it for the Church and Saints of God, that their ſtock and Inheritance, is not in their own hand, and at their own diſpoſal.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>math:</hi> 6.13.20 <hi>luk:</hi> 12: 33.</note> It is far better ſecured, <hi>their treaſure is lodged, where neither moth nor ruſt does cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, nor theives break thorow and steal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. And as our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> hath the only right of property and power of diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the Church's rights and priviledges, ſo he is the only juſt and true <hi>Proprietar</hi> of her rents and patrimony: and when an office vaiks, the rents return to the Church her ſelf, as Proprietar under Chriſt, to be diſpoſed of for other pious uſes. And therefore if the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Canons have not only diſcharged the alienation of the Church's goods or temporal patrimony, but hath expreſly declared all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60402:38"/>relative to ſuch alienations utterly void and null, and have declared that the goods ſo alienat are ſtill the Church's own,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil: ancyrom. can.</hi> 15 &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>notwithſtanding</hi> of ſuch Bargains and Tranſactions; how much more muſt the Church be incapable, to alienat or diveſt her ſelf, of theſe Spiritual Rights and Priviledges, conferred upon her by her Head and King, and by him purchaſ'd, at no leſs Rate, than the price of his own moſt precious blood.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. And as <hi>de jure,</hi> The Church cannot make any ſuch alienation of her Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, ſo it is poſitively denyed, that ever ſhe hath <hi>de facto</hi> made the ſame. But on the contrare, it is moſt evident, that like the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>deut.</hi> 22: 25.</note> and yet raviſhed Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel under the Law, ſhe cryes and groans to the Lord, under the burden of ſuch an unjuſt force, and grievous uſurpation, as this pretended priviledge of Patronage is, and ſhall be demonſtrat to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60402:38"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>A farther Examination of this pretended</hi> Conceſſion.</head>
               <p n="1">I. THe ſecond <hi>ſenſe,</hi> in which this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Grant, or Conceſſion of the Church, as to the Right of Patronage, may be underſtood, is, that the patron acts by vertue of a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from, and as <hi>Impowered,</hi> by the Church: without founding upon a right of <hi>property,</hi> in the power of <hi>Election,</hi> by vertue of an <hi>Alienation</hi> of it, made by the Church. As to which, theſe things may be conſidered.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Firſt, that in this ſenſe alſo, the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this <hi>conceſſion,</hi> do clearly acknowledge, that the patron acts not, in reference to the <hi>Call</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> of the Miniſtry, <hi>Jure proprio,</hi> and by an <hi>intrinſick power,</hi> but by a power <hi>derived</hi> from the Church, and that therefore, it is the Church and not he, that hath the <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>original</hi> right, to meddle in theſe matters. And conſequently that the <hi>fountain,</hi> of the patron's power, is no <hi>civil,</hi> but a <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> right. And the true and natural conſequence of all, is,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60402:39"/>that therefore the Patron ought to follow the Church's <hi>inclinations,</hi> and not his <hi>own,</hi> in the management and adminiſtration of this power; and ought not to tye and oblidge the Church to follow his will and pleaſure in it. And next it follows as natively, that ſince the power, by which the Patron acts, is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be a <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> power, therefore he cannot without the groſſeſt <hi>Symony,</hi> fell and make <hi>Merchandice</hi> of it, as he may do of other things, that fall within the compaſs of his <hi>privat Patrimony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. In the next place, it is to be conſidered, that the Church hath as little warrand, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſuch <hi>conſtant, general, perpetual,</hi> &amp; <hi>unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Commiſſions</hi> (eſpecially upon ſuch as are none of the ordinar <hi>Officer-bearers</hi> of the Church) in reference to the <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> of a Goſpel Miniſtry, as ſhe hath to <hi>alienat,</hi> and diveſt herſelf, of the Rights and priviledges ſhe hath, to act ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For both theſe methods of <hi>conveyance,</hi> doe upon the matter, differ only in degree, which does not change the <hi>Kind</hi> or <hi>Species,</hi> but only the <hi>gradus ejuſdem speciei:</hi> or to ſpeak more properly, they are truly one and the ſame, under different terms. For in effect, a Man may <hi>ex naturâ rei,</hi> as fully and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>alienate,</hi> and <hi>diveſt</hi> himſelf of his eſtate,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60402:39"/>under the terms and diſguiſe, of a perpetual <hi>leaſe</hi> or <hi>tack,</hi> or under the terms of a <hi>constant</hi> and <hi>unaccountable Commiſſion,</hi> as he can do by the moſt formal Right, under the name and terms, of a full and <hi>abſolute Sale</hi> and Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. There being nothing more clear than that in both caſes, the ſame deſign of <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting</hi> the <hi>property,</hi> and of <hi>diveſting</hi> the <hi>first owner,</hi> Is made equally effectual in different Notions and Terms.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. But thirdly, if by a power derived from the Church, and by acting in her name, the Patrons underſtand an acting in the Nature of an ordinar <hi>Mandatar</hi> and <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> they muſt give up the cauſe. For 1. In this caſe, the Patron muſt be content (as all <hi>Manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> muſt) to ſubject himſelf to give an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> to the Church as his <hi>Constituent,</hi> how he behaves himſelf in that truſt.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Next, he muſt likewiſe be content to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what <hi>cenſures,</hi> the Church ſhall think fit to impoſe upon him, in caſe he be found to <hi>malverſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. Again, he muſt be content to follow the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> of the Church in his actings, and muſt not pretend to <hi>Oblidge</hi> the Church, to what he thinks fit, in the management of that <hi>Truſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">VII. Fourthly, the Patron muſt likewiſe be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60402:40"/>content, to <hi>quit,</hi> and <hi>lay down</hi> his <hi>Comiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and to give it up, <hi>into the hands</hi> of the Church, when ever ſhe ſhall think fit to <hi>re-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume</hi> the power into her own hand, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage it by her ſelf, without the aſſiſtance of ſuch a Deputy.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. He muſt alſo be content to let this <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Trust expire</hi> with himſelf, and ſo exclude his Heirs, and much more ſuch as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Right from him, <hi>titulo ſingulari,</hi> from any intereſt in it.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. And laſtly, he muſt paſs from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Name, and <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Patron,</hi> ſeing that (as hath been formerly obſerved) ſtill implies a <hi>Superiority</hi> in the Patron, and a <hi>Subordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or rather a <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> upon the Church, over which the Power is claimed and exerciſed, which is a thing abſolutely <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſistent</hi> with the nature of a <hi>Mandat</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion.</hi> For that on the contrare doth clearly imply, an <hi>Inferiority</hi> and <hi>Subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Perſon <hi>Intruſted,</hi> to thoſe from whom he receives his <hi>Commiſſion.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may confidently conclude, that if the Aſſerters of Patronage, can find no better foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, than this, to ground it upon, the leaſt breath will be able to overturn it.</p>
               <p n="10">X. And as in the former ſenſe, of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Conceſſion, ſo in this alſo, It is poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60402:40"/>denyed, that ever the Church hath grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch a <hi>Commiſſion.</hi> And the Patrons will find themſelves equally ſtraitned to prove, that ever the Church gave ſuch a <hi>general</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Commiſſion,</hi> as they will be to prove, that ever ſhe made an <hi>Abſolute alienation</hi> of her Rights. It is as certain that ſhe hath never made any ſuch <hi>conveyance,</hi> as it is evidently <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable,</hi> that ſhe ſhould make ſuch a Grant, in either of the ſenſes pretended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>Another ground adduced for the foundation of Patronage from the</hi> Neceſſity <hi>of the</hi> Jus Oneroſum, <hi>examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THe <hi>Jus Oneroſum</hi> aſcribed by the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, to Patrons, is adduced as a ground, to found both that and the other Rights of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage upon. For ſeing it is very neceſſar, that ſome perſons of <hi>credit</hi> and <hi>intereſt,</hi> ſhould be intruſted with a power to <hi>overſee</hi> and take care, that <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Benefices</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings,</hi> be not <hi>dilapidate</hi> and <hi>miſapplyed,</hi> but that the rents and profites of them be rightly imployed for their proper uſes; it may be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60402:41"/>preſumed there can no man be found ſo fit, and qualified, for ſuch a charge, or who will more narrowly, zealouſly and carefully, notice the matter, than ſuch as have been ſo <hi>piouſly</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, as to beſtow a <hi>Maintenance</hi> and Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Paſtors of the Church: eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the Paſtors be ſuch as are Nominat and Elected by themſelves: every Man being Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally very careful, to defend &amp; preſerve, that which in a manner is the work of his own hands.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Tho' this ground may be ſufficiently taken off, by what is already repreſented, yet we ſhall add ſome other conſiderations.</p>
               <p>And firſt, it may be conſidered that what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver force this ground may have as to the firſt <hi>Founders</hi> and <hi>Donors</hi> themſelves, and as to this <hi>Particular</hi> point of <hi>preſerving</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending</hi> the Church's <hi>Patrimony;</hi> yet it hath no force as to their <hi>Heirs,</hi> or others ſucceeding them upon a <hi>ſingular right and Title</hi> who for the moſt part (if it were in their power) would be content to have their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſlors Deeds and Grants, made in favours of the Church, declared <hi>null</hi> and <hi>void.</hi> And far leſs can this pretence conclude any thing, to found the other Priviledges of Patronage, relating to their <hi>Negative Interests,</hi> in the <hi>Call</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> of the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60402:41"/>III. Next it is but too evident, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be pretended, this care for <hi>Defence</hi> of the Church's <hi>Patrimony,</hi> from <hi>Dilapidation</hi> and <hi>Miſapplications,</hi> is the leaſt part of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron's buſineſs, or concernment. All the care he takes in this affair, being meerly, that no Body ſhall have Power to Dilapidate, or Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apply the Church's Rents and Livings, <hi>but Himſelf.</hi> And certainly in this reſpect, the Power of Patronage, may moſt juſtly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly, be termed a <hi>Jus oneroſum,</hi> a very <hi>grievous</hi> and <hi>burdenſome</hi> power to the Church of God: ſo that if there were a particular <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> appointed for preventing the <hi>Dilapidati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Miſmanagement</hi> or <hi>Miſapplying</hi> of the Church's <hi>Patrimony,</hi> and for puniſhing of ſuch as ſhould be found <hi>guilty</hi> of it, I am ſure, there is no ſort of Men in the Nation, that would feell the weight of Juſtice, more deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly, upon that account, than the moſt part of the Patrons themſelves, who, as they are <hi>de Facto,</hi> guilty, with many other Sacrilegious <hi>Impropriators,</hi> of the <hi>Dilapidating</hi> and <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>application</hi> of the Church's <hi>Livings</hi> &amp; <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> without the leaſt colour of <hi>Material Right,</hi> ſo they do pretend (as we may have farther occaſion to obſerve) that <hi>de Jure,</hi> they may lawfully retain in their own hands, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever part of the Benefice, they can agree with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60402:42"/>the <hi>Intrant</hi> to allow: And that in the caſes of vacancy, the <hi>Fruits</hi> and <hi>Profites</hi> of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, muſt return to their own <hi>private uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. But thirdly, the defence of the Church, in her <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Patrimony,</hi> and in her <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> alſo, Is indeed a thing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſar, and deſireable, and therefore it is a duty incumbent, not only on every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in power, in their ſeveral ſtations; but in a <hi>ſpecial manner,</hi> upon the <hi>civil Magiſtrat,</hi> who by his office is the Church's <hi>Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And not only is it the duty of all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats, but their <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Profit</hi> alſo, and it will likewiſe be their <hi>Comfort,</hi> that they have imployed all their Power and Intereſt, and brought all their Honour and Authority, to the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> for whoſe good our bleſſed Lord took upon him, the <hi>ſtate</hi> of a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> and <hi>ſends forth his Angels as miniſtring Spirits.</hi> But any power the civil Magiſtrat hath in theſe matters, is only a power <hi>circa Sacra,</hi> and no power <hi>in Sacris,</hi> with reference to a <hi>Negative Interest</hi> in the <hi>Maintenance</hi> of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, to which, they have a full and better Right, by vertue of their <hi>Spiritual capacity,</hi> and <hi>faithful Diſcharge</hi> of their duty therein, than all the Powers on Earth can give them. The Magiſtrats power is only <hi>Cumulative,</hi> whereby he may confirm
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60402:42"/>and maintain, the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Church, but no way <hi>privative</hi> of them. He may, and ought to interpoſe his Intereſt and Authority, for her defence in the injoyment of her Rights, but can neither deprive her of them, not confer or confirm the ſame, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of any other, that uſurps or invads them, to her prejudice.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Fourthly, it is the conſtant opinion of Divines, that the Church herſelf, hath power to cenſure, ſuch as are guilty of <hi>Symoniacal</hi> or <hi>Sacrilegious Dilapidations</hi> and <hi>Miſapplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of het <hi>Patrimony<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> And this they gather by due Analogy, from the Apoſtle <hi>Peter's</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 5, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.</note> of the puniſhment of Death upon <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> for their Sacrilegious Concealments, of what they had <hi>Conſecrate</hi> to God for the uſe of his Church: and from the carriage of the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the caſe of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> from whom the crime of <hi>Simony</hi> derives it's Name.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. But beſide all this, the word of God as it is compleatly perfect in every thing, ſo it is noways deficient, in ſettling inſtitutions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>Eccleſiastical,</hi> for the overſight of theſe matters. For in the Primitive and Apoſtolick times, we find, that the care of the <hi>Collecting</hi> and <hi>Diſtributing</hi> of the goods of the Church, was committed to the <hi>Deacons,</hi> who being
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60402:43"/>
                  <hi>ordinar</hi> and <hi>ſtanding Office-bearers</hi> in the Church, were countable to her, for their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and Cenſurable by her, in caſe they were found to Maleverſe. Theſe Office<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers had truly a kind of power <hi>in Sacris,</hi> or a lawful warrand to medle with a thing <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated</hi> and <hi>Devoted</hi> to God, for pious uſes. And as this office was in it ſelf moſt <hi>uſeful,</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> in the Church, and founded upon a lawful warrand, ſo it was ordinarly exerced by Men of <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Interest;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts,</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 23, 24, 25, 28.</note> and ſuch as were Eminent for <hi>Piety,</hi> as is clear from, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. And it is to be regrated, that the Church, for want of a <hi>Maintenance</hi> to ſuch Officers, ſtands depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the moſt part of their patrociny and protection</p>
               <p n="7">VII. They are ſtyled in the Scripture <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a word Importing <hi>the ſtanding over againſt a Man for help in the lifting of a burden, that is too weighty for him alone.</hi> And is a <hi>term</hi> that very properly, and more fully and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantly, expreſſeth the Nature and Deſign of this Office, than any word in our Language can. For without ſuch helps. (ſo our Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation renders the word) who may take upon them, the care of <hi>collecting,</hi> and <hi>diſpenſing,</hi> what was beſtowed upon the Church for <hi>pious uſes,</hi> the work of the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> could not but
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60402:43"/>meet with many Hinderances and Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For when the Paſtors of the Church, like the <hi>neglected</hi> Levits,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>muſt flee every one to his field,</hi> and be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in Secular Affairs, and Law ſuits, for recovery of their Livings, how is it poſſible that they can wait upon the duties of their fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as they ought? the diligent and Faithful diſcharge of the <hi>Ministerial Office</hi> is of it ſelf, without the unneceſſar addition of other civil Affairs, of ſo great a weight, and requires ſo much aſſiduity, and application, that it made even the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, one of the greateſt and moſt eminent Miniſters, that ever the Chriſtian Church had, cry out, <hi>who is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for theſe things?</hi> or how is it poſſible when the Paſtors of the Church,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2: 16.</note> are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigled in civil buſineſs, and debates, but they muſt turn cold and faint in that edge and zeal, that renders them uſeful and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Labourers in the Lord's Vine-Yard?</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. And tho' this office of <hi>Deacons,</hi> may ſeem to be among the loweſt, yet in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, it was of no mean account; Men of the beſt note and conſideration, for piety and wealth, were ordinarly intruſted with it, as is clear from that fore-cited place: And that becauſe of the great uſe and neceſſity, the Church had of them: And therefore <hi>in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60402:44"/>Diaconis, potius quam Paſtoribus, elegendis, curandum ut caeteris paribus, lautioris For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae Homines, qui infimum hoc officium Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, eligantur.</hi> Our own Church alſo, in the ſecond Book of Diſcipline,
<note place="margin">Dicks in loc.</note> treats at large, of this office, and of the charge of the Church's goods thereto In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. From all which we may very ſafely conclude, that tho' the care of the Church's Patrimony be no way to be neglected, yet there is no neceſſity, to erect a particular office for that end, diſtinct (as the Canoniſts would have it) from all Civil and Eccleſiaſtical offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Divine Appointment and Inſtitution, with which the Church and People of God are abundantly provided, as far as there is any need, by the infinite Love and Wiſdom of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> her only Head and Law-giver. This were indeed a moſt direct <hi>ſpecies</hi> of <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition</hi> to deviſe New and Onerous Inſtitutions <hi>ſupra quod ſtatutum eſt.</hi> And far leſs is it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar to inveſt any Office bearer of this Nature, with ſuch an additional Priviledge, as is claimed by the Patrons of Kirks and Benefices, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to a negative Intereſt in the Election and maintenance of the Miniſtry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60402:44"/>
               <head>SECT. XI. Patronage is <hi>no inſtitution</hi> of Divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but a manifeſt <hi>uſurpation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. BY what hath been ſaid, it ſufficiently appears, how groundlels this Right of Patronage is, which might be enough with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any farther, to Juſtifie the proceedings of the Publick Authority of the Nation, Anno. 1649, in the aboliſhing of this Priviledge: But that the <hi>Injustice,</hi> as well as <hi>Groundleſneſs</hi> of this Right, may yet more appeare, I ſhall in the next place, according to the method pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, offer ſome clear and convincing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt it, wherein I ſhall ſhun the repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what I have already ſaid, and keep the ſame plainneſs, I have hitherto obſerved.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The aſſertion we undertake to prove, is clearly this, <hi>That the Patron's pretended Priviledge of a negative Interest.</hi> &amp;c: <hi>about and concerning the Call and Maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, claimed by the Patrons of Kirks and Benefices, is a ſinful and unjuſt uſurpation, without warrand from the word of God, destructive to the true Liberties and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60402:45"/>Intereſts of the Church, and moſt ſcandal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly offenſive to all ranks of Chriſtians therein:</hi> as I think may be clear from theſe Grounds.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Firſt, this pretended Priviledge is no Ordinance nor <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of our Bleſſed Lord, There being no ground from Scripture, either by Promiſe, Precept, or Example, for inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſingle Perſon, with ſuch a Priviledge, as the looking out, Nomination and Election, of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, the principal Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice bearers of the Church of Chriſt: neither is it ſo much as pretended to be founded upon Scripture. It being confeſſedly of a farr later date and all that is alledged for it, is nothing elſe but ſome <hi>ſurreptitious</hi> Edicts, Canons and corrupt Cuſtomes, which (as Doctor <hi>Forbes</hi> of Corſs terms it) <hi>non leges ſunt, ſed labes.</hi> And therefore for any man or Angel, to give or aſſume ſuch a priviledge,
<note place="margin">In Epiſt: ante tract: de Simon:</note> where our Bleſſed Lord the Church's only King, &amp; Lawgiver, hath not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it, as a moſt ſinful uſurpation, over his Crown and Dignity, and a bold Invaſion upon the Rights of his dearly purchaſed ſpouſe.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. In all the Catalogues of the Officebear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church mentioned,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 12 <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.</note> in the Scripture, there is nothing like a Patronage recorded. And if thoſe Prieſts who Married the Daughters of <hi>Barzillai,</hi> and were called by their name,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezra</hi> 2: 61.</note> were
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60402:45"/>Juſtly counted as polluted, and were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the exerciſe of their Office (tho' Lawfull in it ſelf) becauſe they could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their deſcent from the Record; of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogies: And their removal ratified by the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the <hi>Tirſhatha</hi> or Governour, and they diſcharged to Eat of the moſt Holy things, till a Prieſt with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> ſhould ſtand up, and clearly declare God's mind in the caſe, and ſo ſupply the defect of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords: Then ſurely, and with a great deal of more Reaſon, ought the Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, to remove ſuch an unwarrantable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution as this of Patronage, till its Right to medle in the affairs of the Church, be clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtructed, from the Divine records of the Scripture: which I am ſure will never be done.</p>
               <p n="5">V. This is a ground that will be oppoſed by none, who own the Scriptures of God, to be the perfect Rule and Square, by which the Government of the Church is to be Regulate. And that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who is <hi>the great and Wonderful Counſeller</hi> and, <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Wiſdom, was Faithful in all his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe to him that appointed him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb:</hi> 3: 2.</note> For as the arrogating of ſuch a priviledge, without warrand from the word of God, is moſt derogatory to, and a high and injurious reflection upon the <hi>infinite
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60402:46"/>Love, Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> of our Bleſſed Lord, and directly implyes that he hath not ſufficiently provided his Church with a compleat method for Furniſhing, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of her own Office-bearers, without calling in the weak and Superſtitious devices of Men's invention to her aſſiſtance; So ſuch as dare offer to rectifie his Inſtitutions as defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, or to call in queſtion our Lord's <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> in this, may go a great length to queſtion his <hi>ability to ſave to the uttermoſt.</hi> There is a nearer and firmer connexion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe, than every one thinks: We ſee it clearly in the Popiſh Church: For as there was never a Society in the World, that invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moe ſuperſtitious Offices, ſuch as <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Arch-Deans, Chancellors, Officials Commiſſars,</hi> &amp;c. with ſo much Reflection upon the Wiſdom and Faithfulneſs of Chriſt, as King and Head of his Church; ſo no Society on Earth, has been more injurious to our Bleſſed Lord's Office of Prieſt-hood, in Robbing him of the honour of that compleat Satisfaction, payed by him to Divine Juſtice, for the ſins of his People. And it is undeniable, that as both this device of Patronage, and that <hi>Anti-evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical</hi> Opinion of <hi>Merit,</hi> owe their Original, to the ſame corrupt Fountain, ſo the Church's
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60402:46"/>ſad experience can teſtifie, that they have ſtill been found, to be mutual Abettors &amp; Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of each other, as we hinted before, and may have farther occaſion to obſerve hereafter.</p>
               <p n="6">VI And hence we may ſafely conclude, that the publick Authority of the Nation, in the yeare 1649, had all the Reaſon Imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſay,
<note place="margin">parl. 1649 cap:</note>
                  <q>that the priviledge of Patronage, was an Evil and Bondage, under which, both Miniſters and People in this land had long groaned, &amp; that it is a Popiſh cuſtom, brought in upon the Church, in the times of Ignorance &amp; Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</q> And the Canoniſts themſelves, ſuch as <hi>Lambertinus, Panormitan, Pistorius</hi> &amp;c. do expreſly acknowledge, that Patronage is a kind of ſervitude, upon the Church. <hi>Jus vocationis</hi> (ſays <hi>Ameſius) non poteſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prie eſſe, vel Epiſcoporum Dioeceſanorum, vel Patronorum,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e caſ: con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en: cap</hi> 25. <hi>Parl.</hi> 24.</note> vel Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratuum qua ſunt tales, quia Chriſtus qui miniſterium inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit, de iſtis ordinibus nihil ſingulare praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, nihil novi juris ipſis communicavit, &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiane ſine iis optime ordinatam reliquit.</hi> That is, the Right of calling Miniſters cannot proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong either to the Dioceſan Biſhops, nor to <hi>Patrons,</hi> nor to Magiſtrates as ſuch: becauſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60402:47"/>Jeſus Chriſt who appointed and inſtitute the the Miniſtry, hath preſcribed nothing ſingular concerning theſe orders, nor hath communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated any new Right to them, and hath left his Church very well ordered without them.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. And if theſe priviledges of Patronage be without Foundation, either from the word of God, or from moral uſe and neceſſity (as we have already proven, and ſhall yet farther clear) They can be nothing elſe, but unjuſt and unreaſonable <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations:</hi> And as uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, in all Societies are deſervedly very odious; ſo <hi>a fortiori</hi> in the Church of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, the moſt truly free Society on Earth, whoſe Liberties and Priviledges are purchaſed at no lower rate, than the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood of the Immaculat Lamb, and Eternal Son of God, they muſt be much more deteſtable. Sure I am if the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and judicious congregation in the Land, ſhould claim ſuch a Priviledge, in reference to the choice and maintenance, of the meaneſt ſervant in the Patron's Family; He would with a great deal of reaſon look upon it, as a moſt intolerable uſurpation and oppreſſion. For as our Patrons do maintain, that <hi>de jure,</hi> they are not oblidged, to ſeek the advice of either Presbitry or Paroch, to the Nomination and Election of a Paſtor, but that both are oblidg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60402:47"/>to accept the Perſon whom the Patron pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, if he be found in any meaſure, <hi>exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> qualified, for the Office of a Paſtor in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>general,</hi> without any other enquiry or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; So to do them right, the practice of Patrons in this matter, hath been no way diſagreeable to their claims, unleſs it be to the worſe.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. We have but too much Reaſon to apprehend, that this unjuſt and unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able uſurpation, is one of theſe crying Sins, by which God hath been provoked, in his Juſtice, to lay waſt and deſolate moſt of the great fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the Land. There are many ſtanding Monuments of God's wrath and diſpleaſure, againſt ſuch as medle in the affairs of his houſe, without his own warrand and appointment. <hi>Saul, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> are Recorded among others, not as idle Stories, but as warnings to Men, in all after-ages of the Church, not to partake in their ſins, left they alſo partake in their Plagues. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> had a much fairer and better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text,
<note place="margin">2: <hi>Sam:</hi> 6: 6 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 13: 9</note> to put his Hand to the Ark of the Lord, than any of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons have, for their acclaimed priviledges: He but touched the Ark of God, in a caſe, where he thought an extreme and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible neceſſity oblidged him to it: And yet the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60402:48"/>Lord will not let his <hi>raſh</hi> and prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Zeal,</hi> paſs unpuniſhed, becauſe he Acted without a warrand. For tho' he was a <hi>Levite,</hi> and as ſuch was commanded to carry the Ark on his Shoulders, (but not on a Cart) yet being no Prieſt, it was unlawful for him to touch it with his Hand.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb</hi> 4: 15.</note> And therefore the Lord is pleaſed to ſingle him out, and to make him an example of his Juſtice and Diſpleaſure, both for the general Sin of the Congregation, in carrying the Ark on a Cart, and not upon the Shoulders of the <hi>Levites,</hi> and for his own Particular Sin, in ſtretching forth his Hand, to touch it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Lawful call, tho' his pretext, and the ſeeming neceſſity of it, was ſuch, that even <hi>David, a man according to God's own Heart,</hi> was tempted to fret, at ſo heavy and unpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned a Puniſhment, of ſo ſlight and trivial a fault, as he thought this was.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. And that this power of Patronage, is no inſtitution of God's appointment, may yet farther be clear from this, that all Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful powers that are of God, are either <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> and Spiritual. For as to mixt powers, that is, ſuch as are neither purely Civil, nor purely Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtick, and ſuch as give the Office-bearers of the Church, an intereſt in the management of Secular
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60402:48"/>Affairs, and give Secular powers, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt <hi>in Sacris,</hi> we muſt freely diſown them, as having no foundation, eitherin Divinity, or good Policy, but expreſly contrary to both, and as having ever been found by the Church's dear bought experience, to be nothing elſe, but the weak devices of ambitious and aſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, to marr the progreſs of the Goſpel, and to bring the Church in ſubjection to a ſtrange head, <hi>Plants that are not of our Heavenly Father's Planting,</hi> and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming the Wiſdom of any Chriſtian Church, or State, to tolerat and allow. And certainly as the Magiſtrate or Civil powers of a Nation, have no warrand, to medle <hi>in Sacris,</hi> ſo there is no Conſcientious Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, but will find his charge ſo weighty, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any farther addition of ſecular Affairs, that he muſt ſay from the ſenſe of his own weakneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the great extent of the duties of his Function, with the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things? I Ergo tu</hi> (ſaies <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>Eugenius) Et uſurpare tibi, aut Dominans apostolatum, aut Apoſtolicus dominatum.</hi> Such a mixture as this, is manifeſtly contrary to the dictates of our Bleſſed Saviour, who hath expreſly told us, <hi>That his Kingdom is not of this World</hi> but a poor and contemptible handful (in the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60402:49"/>Eyes of Men) taken <hi>out of the World.</hi> And therefore as our Bleſſed Lord ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave any Inſtructions or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>ſee Luk</hi> 22.25. <hi>Math</hi> 20.25.
<hi>John</hi> 15.19.</note> to the Civil Powers, to
medle <hi>in Sacris;</hi> ſo he never gave any directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the Office-bearers of the Church, for the adminiſtration of civil Affairs: But on the Contrary (as we formerly hinted) expreſly diſchargeth the ſame. And therefore we may well give ſuch unwarrantable mixtures that ſutable <hi>Epiphonema, apage hoc mixtum genus hominum, prolemque biformem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">X And that this power of Patronage, is one of theſe amphibious and irregular Inventions, may be clear, not only from theſe many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Opinions of theſe Canoniſts themſelves on this Head, but alſo from theſe undenyable Grounds.</p>
               <p>For firſt, that this power of Patronage, is not a power truly civil, may be ſufficiently evinced from the Nature of theſe Acts, in which it is exerced, to wit, the Looking out, Nomination and Election of the Miniſtry, and the Negative intereſts acclaimed therein, and in their maintenance: All which are Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtick Nature, and ſuch as by the Holy Ghoſt, are always given to the Church, and to none other (as we ſhall ſee hereafter) And accordingly in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60402:49"/>and apoſtolick times, and ſome hundreds of years thereafter, the <hi>Looking out</hi> and <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, was ſtill managed by the Church her ſelf, without the interpoſition of Patrons: And the mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Miniſtry, was a part of that truſt, in which the <hi>Deacons,</hi> an ordinary and ſtanding Office in the Church, were imployed, as we have already ſeen.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. And tho' the conveyance and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the moſt part of Patronages, hath been from the Civil Magiſtrate, by rights un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great <hi>Seal</hi> &amp;c. yet this cannot prove that power to be truly Civil.</p>
               <p>For firſt, no Conveyance or Confirmation of a Right, can alter it's <hi>Nature,</hi> which it ſtill retains, come thorow what hands it will, and let it be diſguiſed under what terms you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>Nor 2ly. can any Law or Magiſtrate, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr</hi> or <hi>Confirm,</hi> a power that is <hi>Materially</hi> and in it ſelf Unjuſt and Unlawful: for it is not enough to make a power <hi>Materially</hi> Juſt and Lawful, that it be formally Legal. <hi>Shall the Throne of Iniquity</hi> (ſays the Pſalmiſt) <hi>have fellowſhip with Thee, that frames Miſchief by a Law?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal:</hi> 94.20. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 10.1.</note> And wo unto them</hi> (ſays the Spirit of God by the Prophet <hi>Eſaias) that decree an unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60402:50"/>decree, and who write grievous things that they have preſcribed,</hi> and it is an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged principle, <hi>Id tantum quis poteſt, quod de Jure poteſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And 3ly. Theſe Conveyances and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations of Patronage, by grants from the civil Magiſtrate were invented for no other end, but to put the Patron's uſurped power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of Civil authority, and to be an apron of fige leaves, to cover the Stain of <hi>Symony,</hi> with which the Patrons were moſt juſtly branded, when they Bought and Sold their uſurped Priviledges over the Church, with as little Scruple and Remorſe, as they would have bargained for a Yoak of Oxen.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this pretence is as Empty and Frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, for evincing the pretended Rights of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, to be a power truly civil, as if the gifted Brethren (as they are called) ſhould juſtifie their uſurpations, in preaching of the Goſpel, and Adminiſtrating the Sacraments, by alledging they had a power from the Civil Magiſtrate ſo to do.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. But in the next place, neither is this Priviledge, a power truly Eccleſiaſtick or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. For tho' theſe Acts in which it is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, be Spiritual and <hi>in Sacris,</hi> yet this can no more make it a truly Spiritual power, than the like Acts of the gifted Brethren, in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60402:50"/>the Goſpel, and Adminiſtrating the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, can make their aſſumed power to be truly Spiritual: Both theſe uſurpations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the ſame Antichriſtian and Anti-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Spirit.</p>
               <p>2ly. If the priviledge of Patronage, were a truly Spiritual power, or office, it could not be conveyed or tranſmitted, by Birth or Right of Blood. For under the new Teſtament, there is no ſuch Conveyance or Tranſmiſſion of Sacred Offices. A Miniſter enjoyes not his office, by the common Rules of Succeſſion and Birth, and much leſs a Patron.</p>
               <p>3ly. If Patronage were a truly Spiritual of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, it could not be bought and ſold, as a part of a Mans private Inheritance and Patrimony.</p>
               <p>4ly. Tho' the pretended right and power of Patronage, in proceſs of time, came to it's full ſtature, by being Authorized in the Canon Law; yet if we trace it back to it's firſt Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, it will be found to be nothing elſe, but a groundleſs and ſuperſtitious uſurpation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any wartand from the word of God, or conſent of the Church, and manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all the Ancient Eccleſiaſtical Canons, concerning the Election of Paſtors. <hi>Annon cuilibet notum est.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 13. <hi>de Reſurrect.</hi>
                  </note> (ſays the reverend <hi>Beza) pro electioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fuiſſe in Eccleſiam intruſos
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60402:51"/>Patronatus</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Tam aperte antiquis Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonibus repugnantes, quam Tenebrae Luci ſunt contrariae?</hi> Does not every one know (ſays he) that Patronages <hi>&amp;c,</hi> were obtruded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church, in the place of lawful Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as clearly againſt the ancient Canons, as Light is contrary to Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>And in his Treatiſe <hi>de notis Eccleſiae,</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighes yet more ſharply againſt ſuch abuſes, <hi>Collationes (inquit) ſive Ordinariae, ſive Devolutae quas vocant, &amp; Reſignationis Jura, ubi tandem niſi in Satanae Coquinâ ſunt exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatae</hi> &amp;c. Where (ſays he) were theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of Collation, either Ordinary or by Devolution (as they term them) firſt deviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but in the Devil's own Kitchine?</p>
               <p>And again, in his Confeſſion of Faith,
<note place="margin">Beze. <hi>confeſſ. fid. Chriſt. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>inter tract. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ol.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam receptum eſt, in Eccleſiis Chriſtianis jam conſtitutis, ut quis admitteretur ad functionem Eccleſiae, niſi Liberè &amp; Legitimè electus, ab Eccleſiâ cujus inter-era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Itaque tota ista nundinatio praeſentationum, pleni Juris Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronatus, Collationum, Reſignationum, &amp; alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum hujuſmodi ſcelerum, a Satina profecta eſt; quamvis ambigi non poſſit, quin iſta ab initijs magis laudabilibus profecta ſint.</hi> That is, it was never the cuſtom of any Chriſtian Church already conſtitute, that any man ſhould
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60402:51"/>be admitted to an Eccleſiaſtical Function, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he were freely and lawfully choſen, by the Church particularly concerned. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all that Trade and Trafficking of preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, the <hi>plenum jus</hi> of Patronages, Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Dimiſſions and other wicked Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that Nature, owe their original intirely to the Devil, tho' it is not to be doubted, but there were ſome plauſible pretexts for their firſt Inſtitution.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. Laſtly if Patronage be a power tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtick, then the Patron muſt have this power, either as an Office-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Church, or as a private Church Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and that he hath it neither of theſe wayes may be thus evinced.</p>
               <p n="1">1. as a Church Officer he hath it not, fro in all the Catalogues of Church Officers, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom,</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.</note> there is not the leaſt ſhadow of a Patron either as to Name or Thing.</p>
               <p>2ly. If he have this power as an Office-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Church, then he muſt either have it, as a Church Officer in general, and ſo it will belong to all Church Officers, and not to the Patron alone, tho' he were a Biſhop. <hi>Quod enim convenit tali, qua tali, convenit omm tali:</hi> or other ways he muſt have it as ſuch a Church Officer in particular, in which caſe likewiſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60402:52"/>all Church Officers of that Kind, ſhould have this power alſo, and not he alone, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before aſſigned, <hi>a quatenus ad omne.</hi> And the truth is, it is very difficult to conjecture, under what kind of Church Officers, a Patron can have the leaſt pretence, to liſt himſelf: but take him to which of them all he will, the power muſt ſtill be common to all the Officers of that kind, and not proper to him alone.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. And far leſs can the Patron have this priviledge, as a private Church Member, elſe every Church Member ſhould have it as well as he; the pooreſt and meaneſt Chriſtian in the Church of God, having no leſs Right to ſuch common priviledges, as are competent to all Church Members in general, than the greateſt and richeſt Patron. I ſhall not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how far ſuch an unjuſt uſurpation may ſtain and blemiſh the Patron's own Church-Memberſhip:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 2 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Jude v.</hi> 16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Col.</hi> 3: 11.</note> but ſure I am in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of common Right, there is no <hi>reſpect of perſons,</hi> for in Chriſt <hi>there is neither bond nor free.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60402:52"/>
               <head>Sect. XII. <hi>The power of Patronage is destructive of the Institutions of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>for Election of the Paſtors of his Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. AS we have aſſerted, that Patronage is no divine Inſtitution, and that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons have not the right of Electing the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor's of the Church; ſo we muſt alſo ſhew, to whom this Right of Election doth properly belong, leſt others that have as little Right, may lay claime to it, as it hath fallen out in the matter of the Church's Patrimony, which when it was taken from the Popiſh Clergy, who had no true Right to it, was not reſtored to the reformed Church, but to private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who, (to ſay no worſe) I am ſure had as little Right, as the former poſſeſſors.</p>
               <p n="2">II. And therefore the next ground, that we ſhall inſiſt upon againſt Patronage, ſhall be this, that as this power is no divine Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a manifeſt uſurpation, ſo (which is worſe) it clearly <hi>deſtroyes</hi> and renders uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the ordinances appointed by <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> the Church's only Head, for the Election of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60402:53"/>the Miniſters of his Church: And thereby car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with it, the guilt of Rejecting our Bleſſed Lord, from being King and Law-giver in his own Houſe, and of Eſtabliſhing ſtrange Lords and new Law-givers therein. For the Patrons Looking out, Nomination of, and pitching u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch a determinate perſon, to be a Paſtor of the Church, without the conſent of either Presbitry or People, does evidently take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ordinance of a free and unlimited E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, of ſuch as may be fitteſt for ſuch a charge, and moſt acceptable to the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerned, to be made by the Church Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories, and Church of believers reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, each of them acting, what is proper for their ſeveral places and ſtations, as being the only party intruſted with it, by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the ſole King and Law-giver in his own Church.</p>
               <p n="3">III. And tho' the Patron may ſometimes pitch upon, and <hi>preſent</hi> a perſon of true worth, yet as this is but meerly accidental, and the caſe does generally fall out quite otherwiſe; ſo nothing ſhould be done, to hinder the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of one more worthy: And a well qualified Paſtor may be one among a Thouſand, as it is Job. 33. <hi>Is enim eligendus</hi> (ſays Origen) <hi>ex omnibus, qui Doctior, qui Sanctior, qui omni virtute praeſtantior.</hi> That is, he that among
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60402:53"/>all is the Holieſt in Life, the moſt Learned, and the moſt Eminent in all manner of vertue, is the perſon that ought to be Elected: So likewiſe the free Election of ſuch, ought to be intirely left to theſe entruſted by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> therwith.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. The <hi>diſcerning of the Spirits,</hi> and the <hi>knowing of the Voice of</hi> Chriſt, in his Called &amp; Sent Servants, is the priviledge of the Church as ſuch, and does fit and qualifie the Church, and not the Patron, to make a due and ſuteable choice of her Paſtors, and therefore the Church, and not the Patron as ſuch, hath only right to medle therein. I ſay, the Patron <hi>as ſuch,</hi> hath not the right of Election, for tho' the Patron as a Church-Member, or as a Church-officer, in the Congregation where he lives (whether he be Elder or Deacon) may have that Voice and Concurſe in the Election, which the other Members and Office-bearers have, yet as Patron, and under that <hi>Reduplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> he can have no ſuch Right as the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge acclaimed amounts to.</p>
               <p n="5">V. And what ever diverſity of Judgment, may be found among Divines as to the ſeat of this Church power, yet it is agreed upon by all, that write on the Subject, and clearly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Scriptures, that this Power and Right of Election,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 14.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.</note> belongs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Church as ſuch, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60402:54"/>conſequently it cannot belong to the Patron, as a Negative Intereſt due to him in the extent acclaimed. And accordingly it is clear beyond all debate, that the Church was in the Actual poſſeſſion of this power and right of Election, for ſeveral hundreds of years, before ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice as Patronage, was heard of in the Chriſtian World. This is a truth as evident from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity as any thing can be, for in all the ancient <hi>Councils, Canons, Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Historians</hi> of the Church, there is not the leaſt mention of ſuch a priviledge as this of Patronage. And when ever they have occaſion to ſpeak of the Forms of the Election of Paſtors, they ſtill ſet down a method wherein the Church it ſelf does freely Elect, in every thing abſolutely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Rights of Patronage.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. There is not the leaſt hint in all theſe Ancient Writers, that with any ſhadow can be alledged for the power of Patronage. Some thing there is indeed, now and then mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for clearing and inſtructing the power of the Civil Magiſtrate <hi>circa ſacra:</hi> But that is an intereſt quite different from the Rights of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, and which does not at preſent fall in our way to debate.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60402:54"/>VII. It would be tedious, and to no purpoſe to offer to prove from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>See Padri. Paulo's Hiſt. of the Council of Trent. Cyprian Epiſt.</hi> 33, 34, 37, 55, 63.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Theodoret Hiſtor. tripart. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. <hi>lib:</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Socrat. Hiſt. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 28. &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Decret. diſt.</hi> 63. <hi>can.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quanto. Can. vota ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium &amp; Can. Sacro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chemnit examen Counc. Trident. parte page</hi> 408. <hi>&amp; ſeq. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionis Francoſurt. in</hi> 80. <hi>Didoclar, alt. Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcen</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  </note> the Intereſt of the Church, in the Election of her Paſtors, ſince it is a point that I have found very little contraverted. Theſe who are curious may conſult the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, even of thoſe Men, whom they call the <hi>Fathers at Trent,</hi> whereof many (as corrupt as they were) would gladly have had the Church reſtored, to her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Rights of Election, and many others both <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Writers, which it would be wearieſome to cite.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. But not to inſiſt any farther on theſe Topicks, let us follow <hi>Auguſtin's</hi> rule, <hi>Mitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ea quae ab utraque parte dicipoſſunt, &amp; ad Scripturae judicium revocetur controverſia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aguſtin. cont. Jul.</note> The cleareſt and fafeſt Methods, in Debates of this Nature, which concern the Intereſt of Chriſt and his Church, is to decide them by the ſentence of the Scriptures, <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, if they ſpeak not according to theſe, it is
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60402:55"/>becauſe there is no Light in them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay.</hi> 8.20.</note> Thus we find the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and multitude of Diſciples (for ſo was the Church of Believers then termed) meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for the Election of an extraordinary Office-bearer in the Church, viz. <hi>an Apoſtle,</hi> And a liſt made by them both (to wit the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Believers) of two, <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias.</hi> But the deſignation of the particular perſon for this extraordinary Office, they leave to the Divine Determination by Lot.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. And if the Apoſtles who were Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Christ,</hi> in all things that concerned his Kingdom, and did accordingly teach the Church practically, and by their own example, to obſerve all that was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.20.</note> conform to their Lord's farewel command, did proceed with conſent and concurrence of the Church, and people of God, to the Election of ſo <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary</hi> an Officer as an Apoſtle; It ſtrongly imports that it was their Maſter's mind, that they ſhould ſo do, not only in the particular Election of that Apoſtle, but alſo and much more in the choice of the Inferiour and Ordinary Office-bearers of the Church.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Thus we alſo find, that the Looking out, Nomination and Election, of the Deacons (whoſe Office is one of the ordinary tho' inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60402:55"/>Offices of the Church) is given by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Apoſtles, to the multitude of the Diſciples or ordinary Believers. In which Action theſe things are clearly evident.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the twelve <hi>Apostles</hi> call the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude together, and appoint Deacons to be choſen, and alſo appoint their determinate Number. <hi>viz</hi> ſeven; being ſo many as they judged would ſerve the Church's need at that time: as alſo they ordain and lay hands on theſe Deacons, after they are choſen, and and ſo ſtate and confirm them in their Office.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the multitude of Diſciples or Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, are left by the Apoſtles, to their own free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and diſcretion, in the Election and choice of thoſe ſeven, qualified as the Apoſtles had directed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Looking out, Nomination and Election of thoſe ſeven, is accordingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, by the multitude of Believers, <hi>In prima inſtantia,</hi> without the prelimitation of a previous Nomination, or Choice.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the ſame multitude of Beleivers <hi>preſent,</hi> or (as the word is) <hi>ſet</hi> theſe ſeven <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who ordain and lay hand upon them, and ſo inveſt and confirm them in the Office.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. And as in all Chriſt's Inſtitutions, ſo particularly in this of the Election of the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60402:56"/>Office-bearers of his own houſe, there appears a moſt Beautiful and Harmonious order. For as the Election of the <hi>first</hi> and <hi>extarordinary</hi> Officers of the Church, was immediately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Chief Paſtor &amp; Head of the Church, ſo the Election of the <hi>ſucceeding</hi> and <hi>ordinary</hi> Officers of the Church, is very conſequentially performed, by the inferiour Paſtors and Members of the Church <hi>reſpectively,</hi> each of them act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and keeping within the limits preſcribed, by the Chief Paſtor and Head of the Church.</p>
               <p n="12">XII Suteable to theſe excellent Patterns and examples ſet down in the Holy Scriptures, the General Aſſembly of this Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen: aſſemb</hi> 1649 <hi>ſeſſ.</hi> 40</note> in the directory for Electing of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters appoints the order thereof in this manner.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Presbitry ſends one of their own Number, to the Congregation for which a Miniſter is to be Elected: and he having preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before them, concerning the neceſſity of a well qualified Paſtor, and the great need that the People have, to be diligent and fervent in Prayer to the Lord, for ſuch; He is to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to them, that the Presbitry, out of their care for that People, will ſend them Preachers whom they may hear. But withall, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſeth
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60402:56"/>them, that if they deſire to hear any other, the Presbitry will endeavour to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, upon the ſute of the Elders of the Congregation for that Effect.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Within ſome competent time thereafter, The Presbitry is again to ſend a Miniſter to that Congregation, on a certain day before appointed for that end; who having then Preached, and intimat to the People, that they are to go about the Election of a Paſtor, the Seſſion is to proceed to it, the Miniſter that Preached moderating therein. And the Election being made, is to be intimate to the People. And if upon intimation they acquieſce and conſent to the Perſon choſen, then the Presbitry is to proceed to his tryals. But if the People diſſent from the Perſon Elected by the Seſſion, the Presbitry is to take cognition thereof, and after they have fully heard and conſidered the whole affair, they are to judge and decide in it. And where Congregations are unfit (as in ſome caſes they may be) to make any Election, the Presbitry is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them with a fit Paſtor.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. Our Reverend Brethren, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the province of <hi>London,</hi> incline to think, that the power of Election doth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narly
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60402:57"/>belong not ſo much to the People,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jus Divin: regim: Eccles: Pag.</hi> 98.99 <hi>in margine and Jus Divine: Miniſt: evang Pag:</hi> 12 7.</note> but rather to ſuch as are in Office when Judicially conveened. As for extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caſes I ſpeak nothing of them For theſe muſt have extraordinary remedies. But certainly, <hi>dum ſuppetit remedium or dina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, nunquam recurrendum est ad remedium extraordinarium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">XIV. Maſter <hi>Rutherfoord</hi> and others do unanimouſly agree, that what ever be the People's ſhare and intereſt in the Election of their Paſtors, it is indeed a deliberative and approbative, but not an Authoritative Action, yet as is ſaid, it is an Action truly Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, properly and only belonging to the Church, as ſuch: And that the People are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed very nearly concerned, in the right choice of their Paſtors, as being the moſt <hi>ſpecial ordinary means,</hi> appointed of God, for their Spiritual and Eternal welfare.</p>
               <p n="15">XV. From all which it is abundantly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the Right and power of the Looking out, Nomination and Election of the Office<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers of the Church of God, doth properly and only belong to <hi>the Church as ſuch,</hi> and no way to any ſingle perſon, upon the account of priviledge, or otherways, call him patron or what you pleaſe; and that the negative in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60402:57"/>of Patronage, are inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of, that unlimited freedom and liberty of Election, granted to, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> to his Church, for provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing herſelf with ſuch, as may be moſt fit and proper for bearing Office therein.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. I need not add after this, that the method of entring the Paſtors of the Church by Patrons, marrs that beautiful, conſtant and uniform order, that appears in all theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and inſtitutions, of which our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lord, <hi>who is a God of order, and not of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,</hi> Is the Author: And therefore we may very Juſtly conclude, it can be none of his: For by this method of Patronage, ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors are oblidged to enter by Patrons, and ſome without them, as in caſes where it is doubtful who hath right to <hi>Preſent,</hi> or where the Heirs of the laſt Patron are not entered (as we term it) or as the Civilians term it <hi>nondum adierunt haereditatem,</hi> And in many other caſes, which oft times put both Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and People to a ſtand, not knowing how to behave, and in the mean time the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation muſt unavoidably lye deſolate, at leſt for half a Year: for during that time, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, is not oblidged to <hi>Preſent.</hi> Again, ſome muſt enter by thoſe they call Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Patrons, as Biſhops. <hi>&amp;c:</hi> others by Laick
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60402:58"/>Patrons, whereof ſome are Courtiers, others Souldiers, or mean and Ignorant Mechanicks. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some muſt enter by Patrons reſiding at a diſtance in the country, others by thoſe that reſide neither in the Country nor Nation, yea and ſome by Women, as hath been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved: Some by one Patron others by many <hi>&amp;c. Miniſtri</hi> (ſays Doctor Ames) <hi>dati ſunt Eccleſiae a Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o, ut eadem or dinaria et certa ratione, poſſint ab omni Eccleſiâ procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari: ſed ſi ab alijs penderet vocatio, Eccleſia ſaepe deſtitueretur certa ratione ſibi miniſtros procurandi, et proinde talis Eccleſia eſſet a Christo Jnſtituta, quae non eſſet ſibimet ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens in ſeipſa.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>de caſ: conſcien. L:</hi> 4 <hi>C:</hi> 25 25</note> That is Miniſters are apointed by Chriſt in his Church, that by the ſame certain and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary method, they may be procured by every Church: But if the Call of the Miniſtry muſt depend upon others, the Church might oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be deſtitute of a certain method of procuring her own Paſtors, ſo that in that caſe, ſuch a Church ſhould be inſtitute by Chriſt, as were not ſufficient in it ſelf to provide for her ordinary Neceſſities. which is altogether inconſiſtent <hi>with the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom and Fidelity of Chriſt.</hi> And tho' this Author, it may be, <hi>underſtand the Church</hi> otherways than we do, yet that makes no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60402:58"/>in the preſent caſe. The Argumentis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cogent in what ever ſenſe the term be taken.</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. Nay which is yet worſe, this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Patronage, deſtroyes, or at leaſt weakens the very nature of a Miniſters Call, for the Call of a Miniſter muſt be Divine, and not humane, it muſt be of <hi>God</hi> and not of <hi>Men.</hi> The Call of the Apoſtles indeed, was neither of <hi>Men, nor by Men,</hi> their Office in the Church being extraordinary, &amp; long ſince determined. They were called immediately by the Lord himſelf, to be Ear and Eye witneſſes of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Miracles and Reſurrection, That they might afterwards deliver them to the World. as is clear from <hi>Acts</hi> 1.23. In which it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them to have any Succeſſors: whence it is that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> calls himſelf an Apoſtle born out of Time, Tho' his Call to the Office was immediatly by Chriſt himſelf, and he reckoned himſelf in other reſpects, to be not a Whit behind the very Chiefeſt Apoſtles. But the calling of the ordinary and ſtanding Officers of the Church,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15.89 10, 2 <hi>Cor: ij:</hi> 15.</note> ſuch as <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Ruling Elders, Doctors,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> tho' it be <hi>by Men,</hi> that is by the intervention of ſuch men, as have divine warrand and Commiſſion to Act therein; yet it muſt not be <hi>of Men,</hi> that is, it neither hath its Authority
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60402:59"/>from men, nor muſt it come thorow the hands of ſuch men, as have no warrand from <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> the Church's only Head and Law, giver to medle in it. For this were truly to make them the Servants of Men and not of God.</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. And that this method of calling the Miniſters of the Goſpel by Patrons, makes their Call to be partly Humane and <hi>of Men,</hi> I think will need but little to clear it, it being evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the riſe of the external Call (at leaſt) flowes from ſuch Men, as the Spirit of God never breathed the call of his ſent Servants by: and to whom the Looking out, Nomination and Election of the Paſtors of the Church, and the Preſenting them to the Church Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for Tryal and Admiſſion, was never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted or committed. And therefore a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Call in that method muſt at leſt in part, be Humane, and not Divine, And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently muſt be <hi>of Men,</hi> and not <hi>of God, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum enim ex quolibet defectu, bonum non niſi ex integracauſa.</hi> And as ſuch an unwarant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Mixture, cannot but <hi>pro tanto,</hi> very much weaken (I ſhall not ſay nulliſie) a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter's Call, ſo certainly it cannot but very much marr his Confidence, and obſtruct his Comfort, in the exerciſe of his Miniſtry: as we ſhall ſee hereafter. To this purpoſe,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60402:59"/>
                  <hi>Zanchius</hi> tells us, after he hath been ſpeaking of the Miniſterial call. <hi>Ex his autem omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus apparet, quam nulla ſit, vel non Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, eorum Dei Miniſtrorum, vel Eccleſiae Pastorum vocatio, qui ſolius Regis vel Reginae, vel Patroni, vel Epiſcopi, aut Archiepiſcopi, Diplomate, Bullis, Juſſu &amp; Judicio, fiunt vel Eliguntur; id quod dolendum est adhue fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri in ijs Eccleſiis, qui tamen purum Dei ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum habent, &amp; ſequuntur ut in Eccleſia</hi> Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That is, it is very clear how much either Null, or at leſt not Lawſul, the Call of thoſe Miniſters of God, or Paſtors of the Church muſt be, who take their Election, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Patents, Bulls, Warrands, or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of a King, Queen, Patron or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <hi>&amp;c</hi> Which yet to our grief, is done even in theſe Churches, who have and follow the profeſſion of the true word of God, as in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. And laſtly, the Aſſertors of this pretended power of Patronage, cannot deny, but it were moſt abſurd and unreaſonable, for any ſingle Perſon, how pious and judicious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to aſſume and take upon him, the Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, Nomination and Election, of all the Ruling Elders and Deacons of a Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And to oblidge the Church, to accept and receive, ſuch as he ſhould ſo Nominat and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60402:60"/>Elect, tho' thoſe (<hi>viz.</hi> the Ruling Elders and Deacons) be but the inferiour Officebearers of the Church, and the people of God no way ſo neerly concerned, in the right choice of them, as in that of their Paſtors, who are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God, as the moſt ſpecial ordinary means of their Salvation. And therefore for any Man without <hi>Christ's</hi> warrand, to aſſume the Nomination, and Election of the Paſtors of the Church, who are the principal Office-bearers in the Houſe of God, and in the right and due choice of whom, the good of Souls is ſo neerly concerned, muſt be much more abſurd and unreaſonable. And there is no ground that can be urged, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Patrons a priviledge of Electing the Principal Office-bearers of the Church, that may not with much more force and advantage, be preſſed, for giving him a power, to Elect the Inferiour Office bearers alſo.</p>
               <p>I grant the caſe is different, but ſtill I ſee no difference, that with any appearance of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, can be aſſigned, to determine the point in favours of the Right of Patronage, as to the Principal Office beaters, and not as to others, ſave this, that the Patrons ſettling of a Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, in favours of the Paſtors, muſt give him a greater Intereſt, in the choice of thoſe, than he can have in that of the others, on
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60402:60"/>whom he hath conferred no Benefice: And of how much weight this pretence is, we have already ſeen, and ſhall not repeat what we have ſaid upon this Head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>The power of Patronage, is against the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Intereſt of common Society.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. AS this power of Patronage is no Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but clearly inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of his Inſtitutions; ſo it is againſt the <hi>Freedom</hi> &amp; <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the Church, conſidered as a <hi>Common Society:</hi> It being a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge naturally Inherent in all free Societies, ſuch as Republicks, Cities, Colledges, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To Elect and Choice their own Rulers and Office bearers, of which Freedom, this priviledge of Patronage, does clearly Robb and Deprive the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">II. For if we may be allowed as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to gueſs at the firſt beginings of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to ſpeak what the common ſenſe of Mankind ſeems to Dictat, ſo long as any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men are kept together, only by a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al conſent, expreſs or tacit, to ſupercede force,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60402:61"/>and to live quietly, on what providence brought to their hands; They cannot be ſaid to have been under any proper Government: It being meerly good Humor, and nothing elſe, that kept them together, in any kind of Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. Man indeed is a Creature Naturally So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, and Society is a kind of Life, that they are by God and Nature deſigned to; as to mention no other conſideration, may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently manifeſt, from that one faculty they have, of Communicating their Thoughts to one another, by <hi>ſpeech;</hi> but if they live together only by bonds of good Nature, it cannot be expected that the Corruptions of Men, would let their Societie continue for any long time: ſo that when ever that bond of good Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to fail, they behoved either to quit one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother's company, or elſe betake themſelves to ſome ſort of Government; And this could on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be eſtabliſhed, either voluntarly and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent, whereby a ſuperiority and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, was given over the reſt to ſome one or moe, whom they thought fitteſt to manage it for the good of all: or otherways ſuch a Power and Superiority, was Ambitiouſly uſurped, by ſuch whoſe Reputarion and Authority for Wiſdom and Strength, made them conceive themſelves moſt Likely and Able to keep it: which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſerves the Name, nor ſatisfies the true
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60402:61"/>ends of Government, and ſo the Natural Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Election was ſubverted.</p>
               <p n="3">III. And therefore the like Freedom, in in chooſing of ſuch, as are fitteſt for bearing Office, cannot without the higheſt Injurie and uſurpation, be denied to, or wreſted from the Church, and people of God, the moſt truely free born Society on Earth, who with Abraham are Heirs of the World, and Heirs Annexed with Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.13. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8 17.</note> by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible love and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of whom, as her <hi>only Head</hi> and <hi>Law-giver,</hi> the Church is moſt fully and compleatly provided, with all the true and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary freedoms &amp; priviledges, of other Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, I mean <hi>free Societies,</hi> and not ſuch as are inſlaved to the power of others, where little or no freedom remains, all things being manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meerly for the private intereſt of ſome one or more, particular perſons or Families, to the prejudice and opreſſion of the reſt, either by a forced ſurrender, or an open invaſion of their Liberties, with little reſpect to any publick advantage, except in ſo farr as may conduce, for that private intereſt: And what ever may be ſaid of their Societies, yet the Church is utterly incapable, of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſuch ſurrender of her liberties, tho' this pretence (as frivolous as it is) be made
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60402:62"/>uſe of by ſome, for a ground to found the rights of Patronage upon, as we have already ſeen.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. There is another conſideration of a near affinity with this, that may very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be made uſe of, againſt the intereſt of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage: That as this power is againſt the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of comon Society, ſo it is alſo againſt the intereſt of the Church as a Society: For it being uncontroverted, that all pretending to any truſt in a Society, ought both to be qualified for it, and attend upon it, (as is clear in Church Affairs from the Canons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt non-reſidence) it is as evident on the other hand, that theſe things are no ways to be found in this our Patron: Seing the Patron by vertue of his pretended power and truſt, ſtands no wayes oblidged, to reſide within the paroch, nay nor ſo much as within the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Church, nor to be of the ſame profeſſion of Religion, His right of Patronage being as conſiſtent with his non-reſidence, and with his being Popiſh or other wayes heretical, yea with his being under the higheſt cenſures of the Church, inflicted for his notorious and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous wickedneſs, as the rights he hath to the other parts of his Eſtate. That being a right <hi>in Patrimonio,</hi> as well as the reſt of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60402:62"/>V. And how is it poſſible for any man in Reaſon to conceive, that a perſon in theſe caſes, ſhould be capable (tho' the priviledge ſhould be otherwayes never ſo alowable) to act in a matter of ſo high and tender concernment, to the welfare of our Lord's Spiritual intereſts, and the good of the Souls of his People? For when a Patron does not reſide in the Paroch; nor perhaps in the Nation, it is impoſſible for him to exerce his priviledge upon any rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal grounds and motives, or with any proper Judgement and Diſcretion of his own. All the light he hath to ſteer by being at beſt, but an <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of a naked hear ſay, either as to the life and qualifications of the perſon to be preſented, or as to what gifts are moſt ſutable, and proper for ſuch a people; he being equally and utterly ignorant of the need and condition of both, ſo that he muſt in this, be unavoidably left, to be acted and driven, by the ſoliſtations of his friends or ſervants, as ignorant, at leaſt as himſelf, or by other means leſs honeſt, without any Judgement of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, like a beaſt of burden,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 49 20.</note> as the Spirit of God ſtiles <hi>the man that is in Honour and underſtandeth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. And if the Patron be Popiſh, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways heretical, or under the cenſures of the Church, the matter is ſtill worſe, if worſe can
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60402:63"/>be. For all the Reaſon in the World, will oblidge us to preſume, that a Patron in theſe circumſtances, will neither be able nor deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to diſcern the Spirit of God (as in this caſe it is very neceſſary he ſhould) or to make choice of ſuch Paſtors, as may be according to Gods own heart, and may feed his People with knowledge and underſtanding: It being moſt certain, that on the contrary, ſuch a Patron will bend his whole force, for Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paſtors upon the Church, that may Act moſt ſutably, to his own corrupt and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious principles and deſigns, for advancing ſuch intereſts, as are incompatible with the honour of God, the Spirit of the Goſpel, the welfare of Religion, and the peace and quiet of the Church &amp; Nation, ſo that to intruſt any man in ſuch a caſe, with ſuch a priviledge as this of Patronage, were indeed <hi>oves lupo committere,</hi> to <hi>give the wolfe the wedder to keep:</hi> as the Proverb ſays.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Theſe are no remote and airy ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but ſuch as deſerve the moſt ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, eſpecially at ſuch a time as this, wherein there is ſuch a General and Viſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of knowledge and Piety; and Popery is not only tolerate, but in a manner authoriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. It may alſo be remembred
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60402:63"/>from former and latter times, how that many of the Nobility, and others who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided ordinarly at Court, or went abroad up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Foreign Employments, and had the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronages of many Kirks, and Benefices in their hands were wont upon the ſoliſtation of Friends and Servants, and many times from Motives, and to Ends, of a more dangerous and fatal conſequence, to ſend Preſentations, in favours of ſuch as they never ſaw in the face, nor ſo much as ever heard of, either before or after that time, without making the leaſt ſhadow of a previous Inquiry, into the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications and condition, of either Preacher or People: They being as unfit and inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to diſcern in either, as they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and inconcerned, to improve any diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very they ſhould make, for the good of the People, by looking out, and preſenting a Paſtor, that might be fit and proper for them. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ille Canon</hi> (ſays <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) <hi>ut a palatio mittatur is qui futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus est Epiſcopus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad vitam Solit. agentes.</note> Neither need we forget, how many that entered to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in this method, were the occaſion of no ſmall trouble to the Church of God in this Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:60402:64"/>
               <head>SECT. XIV. <hi>The power of</hi> Patronage <hi>hath been groſly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, and ſcandalouſly offenſive, without any neceſſity or uſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THE next Ground I ſhall inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, againſt the pretended right of Patronage, is, That as it is no Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, but clearly deſtructive of the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Chriſt, and of the Natural Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Intereſts of the Church, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a ſociety: So it is likewiſe an <hi>uſeleſs</hi> and <hi>unneceſſary</hi> Invention, and hath been the Fountain and Occaſion of many groſs <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſes,</hi> and moſt <hi>ſcandalouſly offenſive,</hi> to all ſorts of Chriſtians in the Church of God. And therefore ought not to be tolerat and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in any Chriſtian Church or State.</p>
               <p n="2">II. As for its uſefulneſs or neceſſity, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand, neither have I ever heard any thing pretended in its defence, from this Head. And it is impoſſible any end or uſe of it can be thought on, but what may very well, and far better be attained, by the due and orderly method of Election, ſet down
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60402:64"/>in the Scriptures. For as the Church is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, and much better provided for, in that method, by her infinitely wiſe and lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King and Head; ſo there needs no other right to give a Miniſter of the Goſpel a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Title, to his Maintenance and Living, but his ſpiritual Capacity, and faithful diſcharge of the duties of his Function. <hi>The Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (ſays our Lord) <hi>is worthy of his wages;</hi> ſo that unleſs the Patron will pretend, that he can ſtate a Miniſter in a Spiritual Capacity, and ſo aſſume a power of <hi>Ordination,</hi> as well as of <hi>Election</hi> (and truly he hath as good ground to claim the one as the other) he can give him no right to his <hi>Maintenance,</hi> as we have already proven. And therefore ſuch a power is not to be tolerate in the Church, by any Chriſtian Magiſtrate, who ought to uſe all his Power and Authority for God, and the edification of his People, by <hi>being a terrour to evil doers,</hi> and removing of ſuch corrupt and uſeleſs Inſtitutions, as put an obſtruction in the way of the precious Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Calling of ſuch as may be fitteſt for the Miniſterial Charge, as being the moſt ſpecial ordinary Means, both of his own, and his People's Eternal Happineſs.</p>
               <p n="3">III. And the Church having in her pureſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60402:65"/>times, enjoyed her lawfully called Paſtors, e're ſuch a thing as Patronage was heard of in the World, and when ſhe had no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magiſtrate to protect and defend her: It cannot but ſeem wonderful, <hi>Quorſum,</hi> or for what end, ſuch an Invention ſhall now be maintained, in, and over the Church, when there are Chriſtian Magiſtrates, who <hi>Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Officij,</hi> are bound to plead for, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her in her Rights and Liberties: ſeing all that is neceſſar, in reference to the Call of a Goſpel Miniſtry, and to their true Right and Maintenance, is far better provided for, by Methods of Divine Appointment. The right of Patronage is as little, and leſs <hi>uſeful,</hi> and I am ſure far more <hi>prejudicial</hi> in this cafe, than in the Call and Maintenance of Men of other Profeſſions, ſuch as <hi>Lawyers, Phiſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and common <hi>Mechanicks:</hi> Only men have ſtill a greater itch, to be medling in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God, without a lawful Call, than in other things, that of their own Nature, are ſubject, and by Divine Appointment are left, to a humane Regulation, <hi>nitimur in vetitum.</hi> And therefore, as we had once good reaſon to bleſs God, that the publick Authority of the Nation, in the Year 1649. had aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this corrupt cuſtom, ſo on the other hand it is to be regrated, that there hath not been
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60402:65"/>that ſame ſenſe of Juſtice ſince with a ſuteable acquieſcence, to their ſo juſt and rational De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination: eſpecially conſidering, that if there was any prejudice or loſs of Patrimony ſuſtained, it was on the Church's part, and not on the Patron's: as the Act 1649. will eaſily clear, to any that will be at the pains to peruſe it.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. In this manner do all Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and our own Writers in particular, argue againſt the ſuperſtitious Corruptions, and Ceremonies of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Churches. And the truth is, if we would but allow our ſelves calmly and without heat and prejudice, to conſider the matter, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be very ſurpryſing, to ſee, that men who pretend, to act for the good and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Church, ſhould yet hazard her Peace and Unity, and the ſcandalizing and offending, or the marring of the progreſs of their poor Brethren, in the ways of God, by forcing and violently impoſing upon them, <hi>as the only terms of Communion,</hi> under the pain both of Church Cenſures, and Legal Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, The practice of what themſelves confeſs, to be at beſt but <hi>indifferent,</hi> and no way <hi>neceſſar,</hi> either upon the account of a Divine Command, or Moral Uſe; And which their Brethren, upon ſolid and undenyable
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60402:66"/>Grounds, taken from the Word of God, and the Principles of the Reformation, believe to be ſuperſtitious and ſinful: Eſpecially, ſince they are forced to acknowledge, that theſe Inſtitutions, in which they both agree, are not only Lawful, but do likewiſe abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfie, all the neceſſary ends for which they are appointed; there being nothing alledged, in favour of theſe ſuperſtitious and unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary additions, but a pityful and empty ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of worldly decency and faſhionablneſs, ſo much decryed by the word of God, <hi>Be not ye conform to this preſent evil world,</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) and which in no equity can ever come in competition, with the leaſt hazard of loſing the Church Unity, or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the meaneſt of Chriſt's Followers. Theſe Practices muſt certainly render ſuch men juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obnoxious, to the heavy charge of Schiſm, and to that <hi>Wo</hi> denounced, by our bleſſed Lord, againſt ſuch, as ſhould be inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>ſee Matth.</hi> 18.7.</note> in bringing diviſions and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences into the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">V. But to leave this, and come to the next brench of this conſideration, we may obſerve, that as there are few, or no inſtitutions, either Civil or Eccleſiaſtick but what by reaſon of the weakneſs and wickedneſs of men, are ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be abuſed, and one way or another may
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60402:66"/>become, the cauſe or occaſion, of ſcandal and offence, to the people of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by marr their Spiritual Progreſs, in his wayes; ſo the abuſe and offenſiveneſs of an inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of its own Nature, <hi>uſeleſs</hi> and <hi>unneceſſary,</hi> hath alwayes been held, by all ſound Divines, to be a ſufficient plea againſt its farther <hi>uſe.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> determines this point with, a Zeal and a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 8:</note> very becoming the gravity and importance of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter, that even things, which <hi>extra caſum ſcandali,</hi> are in themſelves, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clearly Lawful and allowed, but in ſome reſpect almoſt neceſſary, are to be laid aſide, and forborn, in the caſe of ſcandal and offence. <hi>If meat</hi> ſays he, <hi>make my Brother to offend, I ſhall eat no Fleſh, while the world stands.</hi> And therefore, <hi>a fortiori,</hi> and much more ought ſuch things as are not only uſeleſs and unneceſſary, but clearly unlawful, and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the Intereſt of Chriſt's Spiritual Kingdom, and the Liberties of his Church to be forborn, and laid aſide, from farther uſe, when they become the cauſe and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of a conſtant and continued tract of groſs abuſes, and moſt ſcandalouſly offenſive to all ſort of Chriſtians, in the Church of God. This is a Conſideration, which I hope it will be needleſs, any farther to illuſtrat,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60402:67"/>to ſuch as are any way tender of the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Concerns of the Kingdom of God, or the good of Souls.</p>
               <p>And that the Right of Patronage hath been moſt groſly abuſed and moſt ſcandalouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, I think will be no hard task to prove. It will be much more difficult, fully to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate, the abuſes and offences it hath cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and occaſioned. I ſhall inſtance ſome few of them.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Firſt. That Patronage hath been abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Simony,</hi> and ſacrilegious dilapidation &amp; miſapplication, of the Church's Patrimony, The ſad experience of the Church in general, and of all the Corners of this land in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, can abundantly, and but too much wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I wiſh the charge were groundleſs. And the Simoniacal pactions, betwixt Patrons and Intrants occaſioned by this uſeleſs and corrupt priviledge, have been ſo many, and have been managed and carried on, in ſuch ſecret methods, and under ſuch a variety of diſguiſe, that it hath alwayes been found very uneaſie to trace them out.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Thus Intrants do ſometimes procure themſelves preſentations, by the means and intereſt of their friends. But this is not the worſt, tho' the provincial Council at <hi>Mentz</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> was deeply ſenſible of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60402:67"/>the prejudice, the Church ſuſtained by it, threatning the Patrons with the Church cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and forfeiture of their Rights, on that account. Take their own words, <hi>Res est pernicioſi exempli, &amp; quae pravam ſaepe Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae calamitatem affert, quod Patroni tum Eccleſiaſtici, tum Laici, propinquitate junctos, aut alijs meritis et officijs ſibi conciliatos, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis praeteritis, ad officia Eccleſiaſtica admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. Quos praeſenti conſtitutione provinciali, in Domino hortamur, et peremptorie monemus, ut a pernicioſo hoc conatu, ſibi tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perent: Alioquin ſeveritate paenarum, rigide cenſemus coercendos, ac talis beneficij collatione vel praeſentatione, ſaltem pro hac vice, aut progravitate exceſſus</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Council: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt: Cap:</hi> 68.</note> 
                  <hi>per omnem vitam privandos.</hi> That is, it is a practice of a moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Example, and oft-times is the occaſion of much trouble and calamity to the Church, that both Eccleſiaſtick and Laick Patrons, do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to Church Offices, thoſe who are their Relations, or others whom they reſpect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of their ſervice or dependance, without reſpect had of their age, or indowments paſſing by ſuch as would be more proper for the charge. Thoſe Patrons we do by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent provincial conſtitution, exhort in the Lord, and peremptorly require, to abſtain from theſe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60402:68"/>pernicious attempts, otherwayes we appoint them to be reſtrained by this ſeverity of the Church Cenſures and to be deprived of their Rights of Preſentation or Collation, either for that time, or according to the quality of the fault even for their whole Life.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Sometimes they purchaſe their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations directly for money, and think the price the beſt beſtowed part of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, if they can but ſo obtain them: and ſo the matter was frequently put to a fair Roup, and he that offered moſt gained it.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cartwright menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons a remarkable inſtance of this, P.</hi> 595.</note> And by ſuch courſes many times (eſpecially in <hi>England</hi>) Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the meaneſt Rank, and moſt ſordid Employments, <hi>ex inſima plebe,</hi> like <hi>Jeraboams</hi> Prieſts, and without the leaſt qualifications of humane li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature, if they could but read the common-Prayer, turned Miniſters, and got a benefice, while men that were of any parts and Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and diſdained to be guilty of ſuch baſeneſs, could obtain no acceſs to the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. Again, ſome times the condition up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Preſentations were granted, was, that the Intrant as ſoon as <hi>in titulo,</hi> ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the dilapidation of the benefice, and to the miſapplying of its Rents, by giving the Patron or ſome other for his behoove, a leaſe
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60402:68"/>and Tack of it for a rent and duty, far within the true worth. And it is much to be regrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that tho' the Law of the Land, ſtrike againſt the Crime of <hi>Simony</hi> in the General, That yet this <hi>ſpecies</hi> of it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Parl:</hi> 1612. <hi>Cap</hi> 1.</note> ſhould be expreſly allowed by ſtatute, to be practiſed without any Diſguiſe: Tho' even many Popiſh Writers, are aſhamed to own ſuch practices: And the forcited provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Council, held at <hi>Mentz,</hi> in the year 1549, prohibites to give ſuch Intrants inſtitution in the Benefice, and threatens them with depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, if ever ſuch practices be diſcovered. <hi>Alij ſcilicet Patroni</hi> (ſays that Council) <hi>de cenſibus beneficio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, partem ſihi retinent,
<note place="margin">Concil. Mogunt. ubi ſupra.</note> aut etiam in totum fructus beneficiorum intercipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, his quibus ea, ad ſpeciem infamis cupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates ſuae obvelandae, conferunt, Inanem modo titulum Reliquentes. — diſtricte praecipimus, ne quis Praelatus, ſeu Officialis ejus, ad quem munus inveſtiendi pertinet, ad beneficium, cui animarum Cura annexa eſt, quenquam investire preſumat, niſi qui</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>Cenſum iſtius Eccleſiae, ad ſuam ſuſtentationem, ſufficientem eſſe, eumque ſibi a Patrono integrum relinqui, docuerit: Alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin Inveſtituram talem, inanem et irritam, et Salut aris hujus inhibitionis temerarium
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60402:69"/>tranſgreſſorem, ipſo facto ab officio ſuſpenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, et arbitrio Ordinarij ſui puniendum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernimus. Eum vero qui praeſentationem, ſeu Collationem alicujus Beneficij. ſive Curati ſive non Curati, a Patrono receperit, cum tali pactione, ut Patronus de proventibus benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij portionem reſervet, ad tale beneficium pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibemus Investiri: Aut ſi poſt investituram, talem pactionem feciſſe deprehenſus fuerit, beneficio decernimus privandum, et eidem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficio alium Idoneum praeficiendum.</hi> That is, ſome Patrons do retain to themſelves a part of the Rents of the Benefice, yea, and ſometimes, they intercept the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of it, leaving nothing to theſe, upon whom, for a cover to their infamous avarice they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſame, but only a naked and empty Title. And therefore we peremptorly require, that no prelat nor official in his name, to whom the right of inſtitution pertains, preſume to give any man inſtitution in a benefice, to which the cure of Souls is annexed, unleſs he firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, that the rents of it are ſufficient for his ſuſtentation, and that they are left intire to him by the Patron: Otherways we decern the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to be void and null, and ordain ſuch Contraveeners of this wholſom prohibition to be <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ſuſpended, from their office, and to be puniſhed at the diſcretion of their Ordinary.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60402:69"/>And we doe likewayes prohibit, any ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as hath accepted of a preſentation, upon ſuch conditions from the Patron, to a Benefice, either with, or without Cure, to be inſtitute therein. And if at any time after the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a paction ſhall be diſcovered, we ordain him to be deprived of the Benefice, &amp; another fit Perſon to be put in his place.</p>
               <p n="10">X. At other times, the Intrants Friends, at tryſts or meetings, about Civil Buſineſs, with the Patrons, paſt from ſomething more or leſs of their juſt rights, In favours of the Patrons, <hi>hoc intuitu,</hi> that their Friend may be ſetled in the Benefice.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. Sometimes the Intrants Friends en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage for his dependence upon the Patron, and for his concurrence with him, in his deſigns for promoting a courſe of defection, and promiſe him the Intrants ſuffrage for that effect. And the truth is, Generally, this Right of Patron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, kept the Paſtors of the Church, in ſuch a ſneaking and flaviſh dependence, upon great Men, as was moſt unworthy the Dignity and Character, of a Miniſter of the Goſpel, or any man of Spirit to undergoe.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. Thus alſo gifts were beſtowed on the Patron's Wife, and Children, or on ſome <hi>Gehazies</hi> about him, wherein the Patron did oft times, meanly enough run his ſhare.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:60402:70"/>In ſhort there are as many ſeveral methods, of practiſing <hi>Simony,</hi> occaſioned by this one device of Patronage, as there are of making up the price or value of a bargain, betwixt Merchant and Merchant, and ſome of them diſhoneſt, diſhonourable and baſe, to that Degree, that it is much ſafer to paſs them over in ſilence, than to teach Men to repeat them by a fuller enumeration.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. But 2dly, this corrupt power hath not only expoſed Patrons and Intrants, but even the Churche-Judicatories and People themſelves, to a multitude of temptations. The Scandal and Offenſiveneſs of Patronage, in this reſpect, is but too well known. For theſe alſo very oft, partly from a ſhyneſs, to top with the great Ones, partly from the ſoliſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and flatteries, and ſometimes the threats that were uſed, for procuring the admiſſion of the Perſon preſented: And finding it hard, to withſtand the tyde and ſtream of the times, or to provide any effectual remedy againſt a growing evil, have been forced to ly by, and ſlight the due inquiry and tryal, of the life and qualifications of the Intrant, and to huddle up the whole matter <hi>perfunctorie, et pro more ſcholae</hi> only.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. And both Presbitry &amp; People were alſo many times deluded and abuſed, by the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60402:70"/>Patrons droping in of a preſentation (which he knew, and deſigned ſhould be rejected) once in the half year, that he might thereby preſerve his right of preſentation, from falling <hi>Jure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluto,</hi> into the hands of the Church: And that he might promote his own private and baſe ends, of miſapplying the profits of the benefice,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>parl.</hi> 13. <hi>I.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 135. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>I.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 163.</note> during the vacancy to his own uſe: The poor People in the mean while, being oblidged, to ſeek help from other Miniſters, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the leaſure of ſuch, as were, for the moſt part, as unable to decern what was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, to make a fit and well qualified Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as they were careleſs and unconcerned, to provide them with ſuch, to the great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of the planting of Kirks; whereby the poor people have been unavoidably forced, to ly deſtitute for a long time, of the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, ſo neceſſary a mean of their Eternal happineſs.</p>
               <p n="15">XV. Again, the power of Patronage hath been moſt offenſive, in being abuſed to the bringing in, and keeping up, of a corrupt, Ignorant, Lazie, and Scandalouſly prophane Miniſtry, in the Church of God. I need not enlarge upon this, it is a truth but too well known. The whole Nation can bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, That there was never a more Ignorant
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60402:71"/>Idle and Profane pack of men, that bare the name of Miniſters in any Chriſtian Church, ſince the firſt dawning of the Reformation from Popery, than many of thoſe, that were obtruded upon the Church, in the time of the late Prelates (to ſay nothing of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Prelates) when Patronage was exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in its full extent. The good Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and preſerve his Church from ſuch a Miniſtry.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. This power of Patronage hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo many times been laid hold on, when no other pretence would ſerve the turn, to eject Learned, Godly, Painful, and Succeſsful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or to diſturb them in the peacable Poſſeſſion of their livings, if their entry was not by the Patron's Preſentation, as being the only Legal Title that any man could have for the time. To abſtract from that ſtrange Cataſtrophe, that we ſee brought about in this Church, in the Years 1661, and 1662. upon the pretence of the want of Preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when yet for the time, Patronages ſtood aboliſhed.</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. It hath alſo been groſly ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and offenſive, by being an occaſion of bringing, the Bleſſed <hi>Goſpel</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Miniſters of it, into contempt: For as on the one hand, there is no ſecondary mean,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60402:71"/>that does more advance the eſteem and value of the Goſpel, in the hearts of People, than a ſutable and due reſpect, &amp; a chearful &amp; cordial ſubmiſſion, to ſuch as are imployed in the Miniſtry of it, as is very clear both from common Reaſon, and from the Apoſtles ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs with the Faithful upon that account. <hi>we beſeech you, brethren</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>to know them,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſe</hi> 5.12 13. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5 17 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.</note> which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you, and to esteem them very highly in love, for their Works ſake.</hi> And again, <hi>Let the Elders that Rule well, be counted worthy of double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, eſpecially they that labour in word and Doctrine</hi> (that is both preaching Presbiters and ruling Elders) For the Scripture ſays, <hi>Thou ſhall not muzzle the mouth of the Ox, that treadeth out the Corn: and the Labourer is worthy of his reward:</hi> So on the other hand, there is no ſtratageme, that ever Satan deviſed, that has had worſe, and more effectual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, for deſtroying that reverence and free ſubmiſſion, which people owe the Sent Servants of the Lord, than this device of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage hath had.</p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. And it is morally impoſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe for when people ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſappointed, of a perſon more worthy,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60402:72"/>and acceptable, on whom they had ſet their Eye for a Paſtor, and another obtruded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in his place, meerly by the Patron's Election, to whom they never conſented, and a Legal Force put upon both them and the Presbitry, to receive the Perſon Preſented, and to give him the Maintenance due to their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſtor; How is it poſſible, ſo long as men are men, and ſubject to paſſion and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but that the effect of ſuch untoward me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, ſhould be to produce, a very cold, backward, and unchearful Submiſſion and Obedience, to ſuch Paſtors? There being nothing that more alienates men's minds and affections, than ſuch courſes; and <hi>Love</hi> being the main ingredient in <hi>Reverence,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> the great Ground of a chearful and hearty Submiſſion, is it any wonder to ſee this a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where there is ſo much pains taken to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troy that which breeds it? or how is it poſſible that a People can be perſwaded, that a Paſtor is ſent of God for their good, when they ſee, that he hath ſtept out of God's way, and hath not entered by the right door of Chriſt's apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <p n="20">XX. Beſide all this the whole Nation can witneſs, that this method of forcing Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters upon People, without or againſt their conſent, and inclinations, hath had very ſad
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60402:72"/>and ſcandalous effects, by raiſing of Riots, and Tumults, to the great hazard of both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as well at the time of the entry as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, beſides the loſs and trouble the People ſuſtained, by ſubſequent proſecutions at Law, upon that account.</p>
               <p>Many other inſtances might be given, of the groſs abuſes and ſcandals, occaſioned by this corrupt and uſeleſs priviledge, but theſe may ſuffice. And the truth is, It is no ſavory imployment to rake into ſuch a Dunghil of Corruption.</p>
               <p n="20">XX. Only I cannot omit to obſerve, that which is the moſt Natural Effect, of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable mixture, that appears in ſuch a Call to the Miniſtry. For beſide the bad influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence this may have on People, to raiſe a juſt diſtaſte and prejudice in their minds, againſt ſuch miniſters, It cannot but alſo be very hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to a Miniſter himſelfe, in marring his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and obſtructing his comfort in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the duties of his function, when he ſees himſelfe diſabled (eſpecialy in times of trial and perſecution) to behave, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his truſt, with that vigor and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that becomes a Sent Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, and a Workman that needs not be aſhamed. To this purpoſe,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2 15. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1.</note> there is a paſſage of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:60402:73"/>in the ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> very remarkable, where he founds the cauſe of his not fainting, in the Work of the Lord, in the midſt of difficulties, upon the aſſurance he had, of his having received the Call of his Miniſtry from no other hand, but that which had been the Fountain of Mercy to him. <hi>Having received this Miniſtry</hi> (ſays he) <hi>as we have received Mercy, therefore we faint not.</hi> And hence it is, that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in all the Epiſtles, directed to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches, The Writer ſtill begins, with his Title of <hi>Apostle, Servant of Christ, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> &amp;c. thereby intimating, that their great ground of Confidence, and Comfort, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering the Meſſage of the Goſpel, was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the aſſurance they had, of their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Call to the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p n="21">XXI. This is a Truth that hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, by the experience of ſeveral Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in this Church. For tho' ſome of them were both faithful and diligent in their duty, to the intire ſatisfaction of their People; yet when they came to diſcover the ſinfulneſs of their entry, by this unwarrantable method of Patronage, they have been kept under long and ſad exerciſe of Spirit, and put to ſerious and deep humiliation before the Lord, e're they could attain to any meaſure of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60402:73"/>that they were authorized of God, to deliver a Meſſage in his Name, or could get their Conſcience brought to any calm and quiet, from the fears of being under the guilt of ſuch, as <hi>run unſent,</hi> or could think they had a good right to that <hi>Peace,</hi> which our bleſſed Lord left, as his laſt and farewell token, to his Diſciples, and in them to all his Sent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 20.21.</note> as the natural and kindly Effect, of their Lawful Call to the Miniſtry. <hi>Peace be unto you,</hi> (ſays our Bleſſed Lord) <hi>as my Father hath ſent me, ſo ſend I you,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">XXII. And many Miniſters, who have ſitten down with too much ſatisfaction, as to ſuch a Call, and way of Entry, have been made to ſee, that ſuch of their Brethren and People, as had skill to diſcern the Spirits, and know the Voice of Chriſt, in his Sent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, had thoughts of them very different, from their own. Theſe being able to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in ſuch Paſtors, but very little of that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and ſupport, which the Lord ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narly vouchſafes to beſtow, on his own Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, ſent upon ſuch a weighty and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Errand, as the delivery of <hi>a Meſſage of Reconciliation with God,</hi> to a People in his Name</p>
               <p n="23">XXIII. Others have but too much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60402:74"/>to ſtiffle, and bear down the checks of their Conſcience, in this matter, but have found themſelves very much ſtraitned, to own &amp; avow (as a Faithful Paſtor ſhould) that they had a Warrand and Commiſſion, to ſpeak to their People, in the Name of Chriſt, And if at any time, they ventured upon it, their Conſcience would ſtare them in the face, and tell them, that their people did with too much reaſon ſuſpect their ſincerity in it, ſeing their entry was not by the right Door, but that in ſome one or moe ſteps, they had clumb up another way.</p>
               <p n="24">XXIV. And as in times of trial and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, the checks of a man's Conſcience, do ordinarly turn more ſharp and uneaſy, ſo at ſuch times eſpecially; the comfort of ſuch Miniſters as entered by Patrons, have proven very faint and cold: and the truth is, it is but little wonder, That ſuch as have no <hi>ſparks to warm them at,</hi> in this caſe, but theſe of mens <hi>kindling,</hi> have <hi>this from the Lord's hand, that they ſhall lye down in ſorrow.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 50.11.</note> Confidence and Comfort (in theſe matters eſpecially) are mutual Supports, and Strengthners of each other, and there is no ſuch ground in the World, for both, as that calm ſerenity of Mind, and peace of Conſcience, which flowes from the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60402:74"/>aſſurance a man hath, of having regulate his Actions, (eſpecially when they relate to the matters of God, and his Church) by the Divine and Unerring Rules of the Scripture.</p>
               <p n="25">XXV. And tho' many pious and worthy Perſons, have entered to the Miniſtry in this method, yet it is to be conſidered, that <hi>multa ſunt toleranda in Eccleſiae, aut Reipublicae ſtatu perturbato, quae non ſunt approbanda.</hi> I ſhall not determine, how farr ſuch a tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be extended, but ſure I am, to argue from their practice at a time, when entry to the Miniſtry could not be otherwiſe had, to the keeping up of ſuch an abuſe when it may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, as it was once well taken away, is a conſequence beyond all rational comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thoſe Miniſters ordinarly, had the voluntar conſent, of the Church and People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed, which makes up the <hi>Substance</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> And if they had not this, I do not ſee how they could have been free of the guilt of having <hi>run unſent, ubi libertas Electionis</hi> (ſayes Doctor <hi>Ames</hi>) <hi>ab epiſcopis,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>de caſibus Conſ. Cap</hi> 25 § 29.</note> Magiſtratu, Patronis Imminui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quamvis Electio non ſit eo modo et gradu libera, quo oportet, Conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus tamen voluntarius, ut in Conjugio, ſic in Ministerio, licet iniquis rationibus procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, eſſentiam habet Electionis et vocationis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſario
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60402:75"/>Requiſitae.</hi> That is, tho' in ſuch caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, the Election be not in that manner, and to that degree, ſo free as it ought to be; yet the voluntary conſent of theſe intereſſed, as in the caſe of Marriage, ſo in this of the Miniſtry, hath the neceſſary Eſſence and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, of ane Election and Call.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV Patronage <hi>is a ſymbolizing with Idolaters, and against the Doctrine and Diſcipline of this Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THE laſt ground that we ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon, againſt the intereſts of Patronage, is, that it being a <hi>Popiſh</hi> device, without any uſe or neceſſity, ought even up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account to be rejected. I grant indeed, that it is no ſufficient Argument, ſimply to ſay, that a thing is deviſed or practiſed by the Popiſh Church, if it were founded on any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, either of <hi>means</hi> or <hi>precept,</hi> that is, if it were either <hi>morally neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively commanded;</hi> But we may well conclude, that the complying and ſymbolizing with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, in things <hi>unneceſſary,</hi> or even, things
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:60402:75"/>ſimply <hi>indifferent,</hi> is ſinful and unlawful. Thus we find the Lord prohibiteth his People, from complying with, or imitation <hi>of the Heathen, in cutting the Hair,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lev:</hi> 19: 27</note> or rounding the corners of the Head</hi> &amp;c: which are things in themſelves, at worſt but indifferent. And therefore, <hi>a fortiori,</hi> and much more, is it unjuſtifiable, to comply with Idolaters, In keeping up and maintaining ſuch <hi>Popiſh</hi> devices, as are not only in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, uſeleſs and unneceſſary, but are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes clearly prejudcial and deſtructive, to the intereſts and liberties of the Church of God; And have moreover a Natural Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, to foſter Superſtition, and an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evangelical</hi> Opinion of <hi>Merit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. And that this power of Patronage is of that nature, is abundantly clear, from what is already ſaid, in the begining and progreſs of this Diſcourſe. And to this day, where ever it is maintained in its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull Latitude, as in the <hi>Popiſh Churches,</hi> daily experience confirms the truth of this Charge. For, as Superſtition, and the Opinion of Merit, were the great Principles, that gave Birth and Life to this corrupt and uſeleſs Invention, and have multiplied Patronages to ſo vaſt a number, as will appear to any that will peruſe the Popiſh Writers: ſo it is but little wonder, that
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:60402:76"/>this power ſtill retain a native tendency, to foſter theſe breaſts, from which it drew its firſt ſtrength and aliment: There being nothing more natural, than for a thing both to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and be preſerved, by the ſame means, by which it began at firſt to have a Beeing. It were eaſie to enlarge upon this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but the thing it ſelf being abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clear, I ſhall leave it to the Reader's own conſideration, That will furniſh him with more than is neceſſar to ſet down in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which hath already exceeded the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity at firſt deſigned.</p>
               <p n="3">III. There are many other Grounds that might be inſiſted on, againſt the Intereſt of Patronage, but theſe already propoſed, I hope, upon due conſideration, will be found to be a ſufficient proof of our aſſertion, and the intended brevity of this Eſſay will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to enlarge any farther. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall only add, that this power of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, is contrary to the Doctrine, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and Government of this Church, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the firſt Dawning of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from popery (as hath been ſhewn in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of this diſcourſe, &amp; ſhall not now be reſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) which the whole Nation, hath ſo often, and Solemnly Vowed and engaged to Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. And it is hoped, that none, who have
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:60402:76"/>been Born and Baptized in this National Church, will upon ſerious and deliberate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, think this Device, which is ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable, uſeleſs and offenſive, and ſo prejudicial and deſtructive to the worſhip and ſervice of God, and the good of the Souls of his People; Of ſo much worth and value, as to run themſelves and their poſterity, by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and practiſe of it, under the hazard, that the breach of ſuch ſolemn Eagagments may bring upon them.</p>
               <p n="4">IV And what ever diſorder may bepretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Adverſaries of Religion, to have been in going about the <hi>Reformation,</hi> either in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other Countries; yet as it is not much to be admired, if in ſuch a horrid confuſion and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the affairs of both Church and ſtate were brought to at that time, there was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of an unavoidable <hi>ſuperpurge,</hi> upon a Body full of ſo groſs Humors, and fixed and inveterate Diſeaſes, where it was impoſſible for the beſt Phiſitians, at the firſt, to know the <hi>Quantum ſufficit,</hi> and the juſt and true Doſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for ſuch an untractable patient: Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally after all that they call Regular and orderly methods, had been ſo often attempted with out the leaſt ſucceſs: <hi>Omne enim pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, habet in ſe aliquid veneni: Et omne medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, aliquid violenti, et nullum est magnum
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:60402:77"/>exemplum, ſine aliqua mixtura injuſtitiae.</hi> There being no Drug, without ſome mixture of Poiſon, no Phiſick, without ſomething vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in it, nor any great example or advantage, without ſome ſmall loſs; which yet our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries will be very much ſtraitned to inſtruct. So ſure I am in the preſent caſe, this corrupt power of Patronage, was once taken away, not in any diſorderly manner, nor ſo ſuddenly as it might have been, but after a long tract of time, and much trouble and pains, was abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by publick Authority, in the moſt calm and deliberate method imaginable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XVI. <hi>A pretence that the Patron meddles with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Election, or what is properly Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiastical.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. I Come now to the laſt part of the method propoſed, which is to examine ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, as may be offered, to extenuate the injuries, that we have demonſtrate the Church ſuſtains, by occaſion of the corrupt and uſeleſs priviledges of Patronage, and to clear that the Church's prejudice thereby is not ſo great as it is repreſented to be.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:60402:77"/>II. The firſt pretence of this nature we meet with is, that the priviledge acclaimed, in the Call of a Miniſter, cannot be ſaid to be any right of Election: For when a Patron <hi>Preſents</hi> a Miniſter, he makes no formal <hi>Election,</hi> but leaves that, and all the reſt of the Eccleſiaſtical part, <hi>viz. Tryal</hi> and <hi>Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> intirely to the Presbitery. So that after <hi>Tryal, Election</hi> may follow or not follow, as the Preſbitery ſees cauſe. And the Preſbitery and Pariſh, may reject the perſon preſented, in caſe he be found inſufficient, or unqualified. And therefore the power of Patronage is not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious, to the intereſts of the Church, as it is repreſented to be.</p>
               <p n="3">III. This pretence conſiſts of ſeveral branches, which I ſhall handle ſeverally, the firſt is, that the Patron makes no formal Election, as to which it may be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that tho' in a <hi>formal, orderly,</hi> and <hi>Lawful Election,</hi> the <hi>Looking out,</hi> the <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and the <hi>Election,</hi> of a Paſtor, be diſtinct Acts; yet, as in other caſes, all uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and corruptions, are full of diſorder and confuſion, ſo particularly in this of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage alſo, theſe <hi>diſtinct Acts,</hi> are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <hi>Confounded:</hi> For whereas in the orderly way of the <hi>Looking out Nomination</hi> and <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:60402:78"/>of a Paſtor, there is a <hi>joint concurrence,</hi> of all concerned in it, To wit both of <hi>Church-Judicatories</hi> and <hi>Church of Beleivers</hi> reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, each of them acting, and keeping within their own Spheres, As 1. Both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in the <hi>Looking out,</hi> of ſuch perſons, as may be fit and proper, for ſuch a Charge. 2. They both concur in the <hi>Nomination,</hi> of ſuch as they have looked out. 3. They pitch upon and Elect, one of thoſe whom they have ſo Looked out and Nominate. And after all the Church <hi>Sets</hi> the perſon thus Elected <hi>before,</hi> or <hi>Preſents</hi> him to the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitery, for tryal and admiſſion.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. But upon the contrary, In this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Patronage, the caſe is quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. For here, the Patron <hi>by himſelf alone,</hi> and without, yea and often againſt, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and concurrence of any intereſſed, doth by <hi>one</hi> ſingle and confuſed Act of Preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both <hi>Look out, Nominat</hi> and <hi>Elect,</hi> what perſons he pleaſeth, for ſuch a Charge; and <hi>Sets</hi> them <hi>before,</hi> or <hi>Preſents</hi> them to the Presbitery, for <hi>tryal</hi> and <hi>admiſſion,</hi> paſſing by all others: Oblidging the Church to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and admit thoſe he hath preſented, if they be found in the meaneſt meaſure, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally</hi> Qualified, according to the letter of the Church Laws, for the Office of a Paſtor.
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:60402:78"/>So that what the patrons leave to the Church, is not to make any Election, that being done by himſelf to their hand, but only <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi> to find, whether the perſon Elected by the patron, be in any meaſure external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Qualified, for the Office in general or not; without reſpect to any Inquiry, whether he be fit for ſuch a people, or any other Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whatſoever.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Secondly this one ſingle and confuſed Act, including the <hi>Looking out,</hi> the <hi>Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the <hi>Election,</hi> and the <hi>Seting,</hi> or <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting</hi> of the perſon Elected, before the Church Judicatories, puts the perſon preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as far forward, in order to his <hi>Admiſſion,</hi> as all theſe diſtinct Acts, that both the Church-Judicatories, and Church of Believers in the moſt orderly and Lawful Method, can do. For the next ſtep after this, in both caſes, is to proceed to the <hi>Tryals,</hi> of the perſon pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon. And therefore the patrons <hi>One</hi> ſingle and confuſed Act, of Preſentation, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleats the Election, as well as all the other diſtinct Acts, And by the way, we may no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, what pains and trouble it coſt this Church, in former times to procure from the King, That in caſes where he was Patron, the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitery and Pariſh might ſend a liſt of Four to Court, out of which the King was to Elect One.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:60402:79"/>VI. Thirdly, tho' it ſhould fall out (as ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom if ever it doth) that after <hi>Tryal,</hi> both Preſbitery and People, ſhould fully approve of, and be ſatisfied with, the Perſon Elected by the Patron, both as to his fitneſs and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications for the Office of a Paſtor in general, and for ſuch a charge and People in particular, yet the Act of the Church in that caſe, may well be termed a ſubſequent and ſupervenient conſent, to an Election already made by the Patron, by himſelf, and without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence; but can never in any propriety of ſpeech, nor from the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Act,</hi> be termed the <hi>Election</hi> it ſelf. All that is here left in the Church's power, being indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but ſimply to <hi>find</hi> and <hi>declare,</hi> whether the Perſon <hi>Elected</hi> by the Patron, be ſufficient, And that only in ſo farr as concerns the meerly <hi>external</hi> qualifications, that are ſimply neceſſary, by the letter of the Church Laws, for the Office of a Paſtor in General. And ſure I am there is none that have any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of true Piery, or ſincerity, but will think, that to ſay no more, there is ſomthing farther requiſite, to be conſidered, in the Election of a Paſtor, that may be fit and proper for the particular charge, of ſuch and ſuch a People, who may be <hi>One among a Thouſand,</hi> as it is <hi>Job.</hi> 33. which in the method of Election
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:60402:79"/>by Patrons, can never fall within the reach of the cogniſance of the Church, (who only are, and can be, the proper and diſcerning Judges of it) to inquire into. And tho' the Church, as ſhe is bound, ſhould dipp upon theſe farther conſiderations, and thereupon find cauſe, to reject the Perſon preſented by the Patron; yet her determinations therein, would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarded, as being abſolutely inconſiſtent with the exerciſe of the priviledge of Patronage; the Patron being oblidged to ſtand to the iſſue of no other inquiry, but what Concerns the meerly <hi>external</hi> and <hi>common qualifications,</hi> that are ſimply neceſſary for the office in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, as I have already ſaid.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. As to the ſecond branch of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, it is very clear, both from what hath been juſt now ſaid, and from what is ſaid in the former part of this diſcourſe, that <hi>Tryal</hi> and <hi>Admiſſion,</hi> make not up all the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal part of a Miniſters Call. The Church-Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories and People, have a farther intereſt, in the <hi>Election</hi> of ſuch as are to be members of the one, and Paſtors of the other, as hath been ſufficiently cleared. And tho' this were all the Eccleſiaſtical part, yet even that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be left untouched by the Patron: For to ſay nothing of what the Canoniſts maintain, that ſuch as are preſented <hi>ab <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitatibus,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:60402:80"/>ſeu generalium ſtudiorum Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legijs,</hi> are to be admitted without any tryal or Examination; which clearly takes away try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al from the Church, tho' there can no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptionly in the caſe for theſe Patrons, to lay aſide the tryal of the perſon preſented, Except in ſo farr as concerns, his knowledge in ordinary literature, I ſay, beſide this, it is very clear, that the Church cannot be free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited, in the tryal and admiſſion, ſo long as the Patron, leaves not the Church to a free choice, and ties not himſelf to her free choice; but on the contrary, binds up the Church to the Election made by him.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. And tho' Patron ſhould be tied to the Church's free Election, either by Law, or by his own conſent, yet he would ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as ane unwarrantable, uſeleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary obſtruction, to the planting of the Church, with fit and well qualified Paſtors. They being ſtill oblidged to depend upon an extrinſick power, for compleating of their Call, as if it were defective without him.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. And as the ſad experience of the Church in general, (if men would doe themſelves the favour, to ſee things as they are, and without prejudice and prepoſſeſſion) hath in all Ages, ſufficiently demonſtrated, that there is no method under Heaven, that can regular the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:60402:80"/>Inventions of men, in the matters of God, ſo as to keep them within any tolerable bounds; ſo the experience of our own Church in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, hath confirmed this truth beyond all contradiction.</p>
               <p n="10">X. We all know, (to give no other inſtance) what proviſions and limitations, were made by the Church, by King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth his own conſent, in the Year 1600. with all the Caution, that humane foreſight or providence, could deviſe, for reducing of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> to ſome kind of <hi>Moderation,</hi> as they term it, to which the Biſhops themſelves did conſent, ſubſcribe and ſolemnly ſwear, and the King in perſon, in the General Aſſembly, did ratifie the whole matter: All the freedoms and liberties of <hi>Preſbitery</hi> being confirmed by parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And we know as well that all the bonds that could be put on the <hi>Prelates</hi> did in a ſhort time (as many did then foreſee) prove nothing elſe, but Ropes of Sand, and as uncapable to bridle the luſts of that corrupt and Ambitious party, as a <hi>Fiſh-book, or a Thorn would be to catch the great Leviathan,</hi> Job 41. In ſhort, all theſe caveats, and injunctions, ſolemn Vows, Oaths, and Promiſes were broken, and the Biſhops mounted to their uſual Grandeur and Lordly Dominion over the Church, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them all. The Church complains
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:60402:81"/>and cryes out, on that violent and treacherous alteration of her eſtabliſhed Government. And the Biſhops find themſelves oblidged to meet and conſult, how to vindicate themſelves, from ſuch terrible Imputations. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they publiſh an Apology in <hi>Latine,</hi> and addreſs it to all Chriſtian Churches, at home and abroad. An Apology that as it diſcovers their Treatchery and Perjury, to be a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and horrid piece of Villany; ſo it clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells us, what effect the moſt wiſe and prudent regulations, of ſuch humane Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the matters of God will have: And may ſerve the Church, for a conſtant beacon, to beware of taking the like meaſurs for the future. Take their own words, <hi>Conditiones istae,
<note place="margin">Refultatio libelli de regimine Eccles. Scotican.</note> pro tempore magis, quo contentioſis rixandi anſa prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riperetur, quam animo in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum obſervandi acceptae.</hi> That is, their deſign in theſe ſolemn Promiſes Vows and Oaths, was never to keep them, but only to ſerve a Turn, and to lull the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto ſome ſort of a calm and ſecurity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the clamor, that was raiſed upon the apparent alteration, of the Eſtabliſhed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church.</p>
               <p>An Apology indeed <hi>Ingenuous</hi> enough, and very becomming the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>ſincerity,</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:60402:81"/>of that party, who ſtill incline to follow the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the old <hi>Serpent,</hi> without any mixture of the <hi>Innocence</hi> and <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the <hi>Dove,</hi> but I am ſure it were ſcarce credible, that ever any, that pretended, to the name of a <hi>Clergy-Man,</hi> or to the Title of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, and Spiritual Fathers of the Church, ſhould make uſe of it, if they themſelves, had not publiſhed it to the World. And there is no Crime their Adverſaries could charge them with of ablacker Nature, than this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence faſtens upon them.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. But this not being my preſent deſigne, having only faln by accident upon this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; The true uſe of it, that at preſent we intend, is, that it would be a piece of ſtupid, and ſinful folly, after ſuch a warning, to run ourſelves, upon theſe Rocks, on which the peace and ſafety of the Church, hath been ſo oft ready to ſplit. If in ſuch caſes we ſhould be-take ourſelves, to rely on our own pitiful and weak Counſels and projects, and reject, the inſtitutions of the <hi>Infinite</hi> and <hi>unſearchable, Love</hi> and <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> of God, we ſhould true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be <hi>guilty of forſaking the Fountain of Living Waters, and of Hewing out to our ſelves, Ciſterns, broken Cisterns, that can hold no Water,</hi> And ſhould take the moſt compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous method, that could be,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerm</hi> 2.13 <hi>Levit</hi> 26</note> to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:60402:82"/>provoke the Lord, to puniſh us yet ſeven times more, for all our iniquities</p>
               <p n="12">XII. The true Rule in theſe caſes, is, that ſince ſuch Inſtitutions, as are not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, abſolutely neceſſary, either by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Means, or Precept, and do of their own nature, ſo much tend to Corruption, Oppreſſion, Scandal and Superſtition, tho' never ſo well regulat, are ſtill ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and exceed all bounds; Therefore, the beſt, and only way, to prevent their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancies, is altogether to Caſhier them, from any other farther uſe.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. I ſhall only add, that as the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of <hi>Viſitations,</hi> was very fit and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, for enquiring into the lives and carriages of the paſtors of the Church, after they were admitted and ſettled; ſo it is ſufficiently known, that the patrons of Kirks and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, have ſtill endeavoured, with all their force, to put a ſtop to the exerciſe of theſe <hi>Viſitations,</hi> as knowing that moſt of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of their Nomination, were as little, or leſs able, to endure ſuch a ſcrutiny, as they were unſatisfactory, at their firſt admiſſion. I ſhall not mention, what other Reaſons, the patrons had, for ſuch a kindly protection of thoſe men: they may be eaſily gueſſed, tho' I am ſure with little credit, to either party.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:60402:82"/>
               <head>SECT. XVII. <hi>Another pretence, that the</hi> Church <hi>may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Perſon preſented, in caſe of</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency.</head>
               <p n="1">I. THE next pretence that may be made uſe of, to alleviat the guilt of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, in its uſurpations over the Liberties of the Church, is this, That the Pariſh or Presbitery, may reject, or refuſe to admit, the perſon Elected by the Patron, in caſe, that after tryal, he be found inſufficient, or unqualified, either as to parts or manners. And therefore the Church can be at no loſs by the Rights of Patronage.</p>
               <p n="2">II. It muſt certainly be an other force, than that of Reaſon, that can draw ſuch a conſequence. This method of arguing, is juſt the ſame, as if a man ſhould ſay, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to ſtop the entry of a Robber into a houſe, or to put him out after he is entred, becauſe any harm he can doe, may be eaſily either diverted, or repaired, ſure I am this is very
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:60402:83"/>ſar from our Bleſſed Lord's method of reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 29. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.39.</note> 
                  <hi>If</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the good man of the houſe, had known, in what watch the Thief would come, he would have watched, and not have ſuffered his houſe, to have been broken up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. If <hi>evil muſt not be done, that good may come of it;</hi> and if the Jeſuitick Quibbles of a <hi>good intention,</hi> cannot juſtifie a bad action; much leſs is evil to be tolerate and allowed, becauſe 'tis poſſible to prevent, or repair its bad effects, <hi>Nam quod poſſibile est eſſe, poſſibile eſt non eſſe,</hi> one <hi>may be</hi> anſwers another, That which may be, may alſo not be. There is ſtill a hazard in the matter, and Chriſtian prudence oblidges us, to ſhun even the <hi>leaſt appearance of evil,</hi> as far as we may. The true rule in ſuch caſes, (as I already marked) is, to aboliſh an uſeleſs and dangerous cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, or rather <hi>corruption,</hi> ſince <hi>vetuſtas er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris non conſuetudo, ſed corruptela dicenda est;</hi> and then indeed the conſequence will be good, that the Church can be at no loſs by it, <hi>Mortui non Mordent,</hi> ſays the proverb.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. And next, beſide that the power of Patronage, doth unneceſſarly expoſe Intrants to diſcouragement, by being rejected for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency,</hi> and alſo expoſeth the Church-Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories, to an unjuſt and cauſeleſs <hi>odium</hi>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:60402:83"/>and reproach, of too much rigor and ſeverity, which if the right of Election were in the Church's own hand, as it ought to be, would be very much prevented, I ſay, beſide this we have already obſerved, what true <hi>liberty,</hi> this power of Patronage leaves to the Church, in the choiſe and tryal of her Paſtors. And when ever the Presbitery rejects the Perſon preſented, upon any head that is not ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, upon his <hi>Inſufficiency</hi> and <hi>Scandal,</hi> the Patron looks upon his priviledge, as highly injured, he being oblidged to ſtand to no ſuch determination: And when ever they reject upon <hi>Scandal</hi> or <hi>inſufficiency,</hi> unleſs it be moſt palpably and clearly manifeſt, which is not alwayes neceſſary, for a Paſtor ought not only to be <hi>free of Scandal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2, 7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</note> but as the Apoſtle poſitively requires, he ought to be of <hi>an intire fame,</hi> and known good report; I ſay, if ſuch inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency be not palpably manifeſt, there is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently a terrible outcry, and a conſtant foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation laid of many tedious Appeals, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigious Debates, concerning the <hi>quantum ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit</hi> of a Paſtors qualifications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from one Church-Judicatory to another, with little credit to the Patron, and far leſs to the Intrant. And upon this conſideration alone tho' there were no other, the Church's freedom in the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:60402:84"/>tryal and admiſſion of her Paſtors, is very much hindered, as the Liberty of Marriage in the caſe of waird Vaſſals, is abridged by the Power and Intereſt of the Superior, and the niceties of the <hi>feudal customs.</hi> And certainly as their is no ſort of contract in the World, wherein a perfect liberty and freedom of choice, ought more to predomine, (if I may ſo ſay) then in that of Marriage; ſo the Church, by the appointment of God, hath much freedom, in the Election of her Paſtors, which are his Spiritual Husbands. And as any force or undue influence, in the one caſe is very odious, ſo in the other likewiſe it is no leſs ſo. The Simile is eaſily underſtood and therefore I ſhall urge it no farther. A waird holding in ſuch caſes as this, is certainly a very <hi>hard</hi> and dangerous Tenure.</p>
               <p n="5">V. But beſides, when a perſon preſented by the Patron is rejected by the Presbitery, the Patron's right ſtands ſtill intire, to Elect and preſent <hi>de novo,</hi> ſome other perſon <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> with the former, and ſo the Church moſt of new again, be inviegled in the ſame troubles and perplexities, and all to no purpoſe or uſe.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Again, in the Election of Paſtors by the Patrons, the Church and People intereſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have little or no power to withſtand the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:60402:84"/>admiſſion, or to nullifie the Election, more than any meer Stranger, that will undertake, to prove the <hi>inſufficiency,</hi> or <hi>Scandalous</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, of the perſon preſented.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. And to ſay, that an inſtitution, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the Church and People of God, hath ſo long groaned, and which was forced and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded upon her, without the leaſt ſhadow of a warrand, from the word of God, or the leaſt pretence of uſefulneſs, for promotting their Spiritual good and edification, is no way injurious to the Church, implyes a manifeſt contradiction.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Laſtly, and I ſhall add no more, tho' the Patron ſhould preſent none, but ſuch as are ſome way fit; yet the Church's liberty and freedom of Election, remains ſtill under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint: For tho' the Church ſhould have power to reject never ſo many; yet a people ſhall never come to enjoy the Paſtor, they chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire, and that would be moſt acceptable to them, ſo long as the patron, and not the Church her ſelf, retains the right or power of Election. And certainly the ſenſe of ſuch a grievous oppreſſion, cannot but make all that are any way tender, or concerned in the intereſts of the Church of Chriſt, eſpecially thoſe that have been witneſſes of a far different State of affairs, and of the great advantages
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:60402:85"/>that attended it, to be ſerious and fervent, in prayer to God, for removing, and averting ſuch a Bondage and Slavery, from the Church and people of God, for the future.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVIII. <hi>Another pretence from the distinction of Laick and Eccleſiastick</hi> Patronages.</head>
               <p n="1">I. THere is another pretence made uſe of, to extenuate the guilt, of the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power of Patronage, that is much boaſted of by many (tho' I confeſs I am unable to diſcover where its ſtrength lies) who grant that indeed there are many cogent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt <hi>Laick</hi> Patronages, as they term them, and that theſe may be and have been, very injurious, to the intereſt of the Church, but that yet <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> Patronages, may be very uſeful. If you ask them what they mean by theſe, they cannot tell, but ſtill they tell you, <hi>Eccleſiastick</hi> Patronages, are very uſeful, becauſe they are in the Church's own hand, as the very word imports. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the plain ſenſe of this, (if it have any) I take to be this, that it is very fit this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhould be intruſted, in the hands of Biſhops, who are <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> Officers and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:60402:85"/>Governours, but not in the hands of others.</p>
               <p n="2">II. I cannot ſtay to examine this diſtinction tho' I can hardly be perſwaded it is good Senſe as it is ordinarly uſed, ſince the moſt part of the Patronages, that belonged to the Biſhops, may truly be termed <hi>Laick</hi> Patronages, both in reſpect of their <hi>Original,</hi> the moſt of them having been at firſt ſetled, in the hands of the <hi>Laity</hi> (as they are termed) and alſo in reſpect of their <hi>conveyance,</hi> which was by a grant from the Civil Magiſtrate, by rights under the <hi>Great Seal</hi> &amp;c. And beſides the true meaning of this diſtinction, (paſſing by the Notion and uſe that Lawyers have and make of it) is, it ſeems, to be taken, not from the <hi>quality</hi> of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> in whoſe hands a Patronage is ſetled, whether they be perſons in a <hi>Civil</hi> or in an <hi>Eccleſiastick</hi> Capacity; but from the <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of the <hi>stock</hi> and <hi>fond,</hi> out of which the Kirks were built, or the benefices ſetled: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the ſtock was out of the <hi>private Patrimony</hi> of any man, whether he was of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> or of the <hi>Laity,</hi> the Patronage muſt be <hi>Laick:</hi> and if it be out of the Patrimony of the Church, the Patronage muſt be <hi>Eccleſiaſtick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. But not to inſiſt on theſe Topicks, this pretence is abſolutly groundleſs. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the Argument adduced, ſtriks equally againſt all for of Patronages,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:60402:86"/>and againſt all ſuch negative intereſts, in the Election or Maintenance, of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as are not of Divine appointment and inſtitution.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Next, Biſhops have no more warrand from Scripture, for ſuch an intereſt, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, than others have. And the power of Patronage hath been as groſly abuſed, if not more, and as ſcandalouſly offenſive, and I am ſure more prejudicial to the intereſts of the Church, and to the thriving of Religion, when in the hands of the Biſhops, than when in the hands of other perſons. And there is no ground from Scripture, either by precept, promiſe or example, that any one Church Officer, ſhould ordinarly be intruſted, with ſuch an intereſt and priviledge, in the Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, Nomination and Election, and in the Maintenance or Living of the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="5">V. But to cut of all farther debate, we ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſclaime any ſuch Officer in the Church, as a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in a ſenſe ſuperior to, or diſtinct from an ordinary preaching <hi>Preſbiter</hi> or Elder: Theſe terms are of one and the ſelf ſame ſignification in the Scripture, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to any, that will be at the pains to read the Texts, where ever the word Biſhop is mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And I know no man or Angel, that hath
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:60402:86"/>power to ſeparate, what the Spirit of God in the Scripture has joyned, and made one and the ſame. And conſequently a Biſhop can have no ſuch priviledge. <hi>Non entis nulla ſunt acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, nullae affectiones, nullae proprietates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. And tho' prelacy were a Lawful Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as it is not, and tho' the Prelates were Succeſsors to the Apoſtles, as they moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly pretend, (ſince as we already cleared, it was impoſſible the deſign of their Office, could admit of any Succeſſion) yet ſure I am in this priviledge of Patronage, they never did, nor doe follow the example of the Apoſtles: For even the Apoſtles themſelves, in the Election of <hi>Matthias,</hi> to be one of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, made uſe of the Concurrence of the People: And in the ordination of the Paſtors of the Church, they made uſe of the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, both of the Presbitry and People. And if they joined the Presbitry and People, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to an intereſt, in relation to the higheſt acts of the Miniſterial Call, they queſtionleſs alſo left them a ſhare,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.14</note> in the Looking out, Nomination, and Election, of the ordinary paſtors, <hi>Nam qui vult majus, vult etiam minus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act</hi> 15.2: 25.27 <hi>Act:</hi> 13.1: 2.3.
<hi>Act.</hi> 14 27: 28:</note> Nay which is more, the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Teachers of the Church, and others did concurr, in ſending out of the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:60402:87"/>very Apoſtles themſelves, to ſome ſpecial pieces of their Miniſtry. And accordingly the Apoſtles, think it not below their Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to give them an account how they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved in their Commiſſion. So that let the Prelates pretend <hi>Succeſſion</hi> to whom they will, they can never pretend to be Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, to whom a <hi>Sole power</hi> of <hi>Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and <hi>Ordination,</hi> was as much a Stranger, as to any Preſbyter in the Church.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. But laſtly, if by Eccleſiaſtick Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronages, the Lawful Church Judicatories, be meant, tho' in that caſe, both the Title of Patronage, and the extent of power thereby underſtood, muſt be rejected; yet there is no doubt, but the Judicatories of the Church, have a very ſpecial hand, and intereſt, in the Looking out, Nomination and Election, of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and have a power <hi>Miniſterially</hi> to authorize them, for their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and to ſend them forth, to <hi>Labour</hi> in <hi>the Lord's Vine Yard.</hi> And by conſequence, do alſo <hi>Miniſterially</hi> inveſt them, with a Right to meddle with their Maintenance. A Miniſters only Right thereto, being a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful call to the Office, and Faithful diſcharge of his duty, in it, as we have formerly marked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:60402:87"/>
               <head>SECT. XIX. <hi>A pretence from the failings and miſtakes of the Church Judicatories.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="1">I. THE laſt pretence that I ſhall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, is this, that Presbitries and People are not infallible, but are ſubject to Miſtake, and Erre, in the Election and Choice of Paſtors, as well as the Patrons. And therefore the Patron's Power of Election, is no more injurious to the Church, than ſhe is to her ſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">II. For anſwer to this, it may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Firſt;</hi> That the lawful and ordinary me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, of Electing the Paſtors of the Church, being an Ordinance and Inſtitution, of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Appointment; and the power of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, on the contrary, being nothing elſe, but an uſeleſs Invention of Men, and a moſt groundleſs and unreaſonable Uſurpation upon the Church, and clearly inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of, the Inſtitutions of <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> The Church and People of God, may very ſafely and confidently, rely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, upon the Lord, for his Bleſſing and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:60402:88"/>direction, in the right choice of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, when they Act in a way of his own appointment; which they who Act in ſo unjuſt, and unwarrantable a method, as this of Patronage, have no ground to expect. And tho' the Lord, for wiſe and holy ends, may ſome times leave his Church and People, to themſelves, and let them fall in errors and miſtakes, in this as well as in other caſes; yet duty muſt not be forſaken, for fear of failings, in the performance. We muſt both Pray to God, for a diſcovery of what is duty, when it is unclear to us, and when it is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, we muſt Pray for ſtrength and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, to perform it a right, and then ſet about it, in the Lord's ſtrength, with a humble confidence, and dependance upon him, for his bleſſing and direction, <hi>who hath never ſaid to the houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſeek ye my face in vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. Next, tho' as is already ſaid, there be no inſtitution, either in Church or State, but what by Reaſon of the Weakneſs, and Corruption of Men, may be abuſed; yet this is no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground, for laying aſide an inſtitution, that is either <hi>morally neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>poſitively, enjoined</hi> by God The only rule and remedie in this caſe, is, <hi>Tollatur abuſus et maneat uſus,</hi> let the matter be regulate by Acting in it, according to the word of God, which
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:60402:88"/>fully and clearly diſcovers, what both Church-Judicatories and People, may, or may not do in the caſe. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the contrary the abuſe and offenſiveneſs of <hi>unneceſſary</hi> &amp; <hi>unwarrantable</hi> inſtitutions, does ſtrongly militate, againſt their farther uſe. If the Presbitry do at any time miſcarry, in a way that they are warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God to follow, we muſt pray that God may purge his own Houſe, and purifie the Sons of <hi>Levi:</hi> And the help and aſſiſtance of Superior Church-Judicatories, muſt be made uſe of. And in caſes of general and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick defection, the Civil Magiſtrate may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his power, <hi>circa Sacra.</hi> But thoſe miſtakes, can never warrand us to leave the inſtitutions of the infinite love and wiſdom of God, and betake our ſelves to our own weak and witleſs inventions, in the matters of God. Chriſt's <hi>promiſed preſence</hi> with his Church, may be a ſufficient encouragement for his People, to cleave and adhere to him, in wayes of his own appointment: Whereas thoſe who <hi>go astray,</hi> and <hi>follow crooked Paths,</hi> ingyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, as <hi>Officious</hi> and <hi>Buſie Bodies,</hi> in the affairs of the Church, without a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Call; can expect nothing, but that God in his Juſtice, ſhould leave them to be a Snare, both to themſelves and others Certainly, were theſe things really believed (as all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:60402:89"/>they do) peoples practiſe would be very far different, from what it is. But ſuch is the Atheiſm of mans heart, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>while we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the truths of God with our Lips, our Hearts are too oft far from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. I begin now to be weary, of notice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch trifles. And the truth is, it might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing, to hear men otherways rational, offer ſuch empty pretences, inſtead of Solid and Convincing reaſons, if the cauſe would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any better. But it is <hi>Vitium Cauſae,</hi> and ſo we need no more admire, to ſee a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs inevitably cleave to the ableſt Wits, in the defence of what is unjuſtifiable, than to ſee the ſtrongeſt of men, ſuccumb in raiſing a weight that is above his natural ſtrength to undergo. The ſtrength of mens Spirits, as well as of their Bodies, have their limits, and are not infinite. And ſince I mind nothing farther that can be objected, but what with very much eaſe, may receive a full ſolution, from the Grounds already repreſented. I think it will be needleſs, to give either the Reader, or my ſelf, any farther trouble on this Subject.</p>
               <p n="5">V. I ſhall only add, that it is the duty of all God's People in this land, to wreſtle with God, that he may incline the hearts of all Ranks of Men, in their ſeveral ſtations and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:60402:89"/>capacities, to return to a hearty and cordial Compliance with, and a chearful Acquieſcence in the juſt and rational Determinations, that were once made by publick Authority, in this Nation, both in this, and other ſteps of a true Reformation. And that the Lord may not be provoked by a too open Contempt, of the Goſpel of Peace (the <hi>Crying Sin</hi> of the Nation) and our ſinful ſlighting of his Mercies, to ſuffer his Church, after ſo much wreſtling, to ſink under her preſent Bondage and Captivity, by reaſon of this, and other unjuſt and grievous uſurpations, into which after ſo many, and great Deliverances, we are again, for our Sins, brought into Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
